Please welcome to the stage CAP
Executive Vice President for External
Affairs and Programs, Miguel Rodriguez.
>> Good morning everyone. Uh welcome to the
2026 Cap Ideas Conference. We're really
excited to have you all here. Uh my name
is Miguel Rodriguez. I'm the executive
vice president for external relations
and programs here at CAP and I'll be
serving as MC today. Uh we'd like to at
the outset start uh thank our sponsor uh
MS now our media sponsor and welcome
those joining on their various
platforms. Uh we'll be getting underway
in just a few minutes. So, please grab a
cup of coffee, another muffin, settle in
for what's going to be a really
jam-packed day full of uh amazing uh
leaders and uh ideas. Um the first
portion of our program program is going
to be focusing on affordability. It's an
issue that's on almost every American's
minds and we'll hear from four leaders
as well as a newly minted governor. and
they're not just going to talk about the
problems, but they're going to offer
their ideas and their policy solutions
to tackle these problems. And I think
that's going to be a recurring theme
throughout the day. We're not just going
to outline problems. We're going to
share with you uh ideas and policies uh
that will uh tackle these issues that
we're facing. Now, on to some
housekeeping. I'll keep this brief. Um
we'll take a break around 10:25 uh
following uh Governor Cheryl's remarks.
Um for those of you joining online, uh
you'll also be able to during these
breaks enjoy some online content being
uh moderated by our own Colin Seaber. Um
uh throughout the day, our our panelists
uh may get some questions. You'll see
some QR codes. By all means, please feel
free to scan them and we'll get them in
the queue. Um We'll get to as many as we
can, time permitting. Um, and finally,
one incredibly important um,
housekeeping item, the bathrooms and the
Mayflower Hotel are on the lower level.
Uh, so if uh, you need to use the
restroom, you'll see some signage
outside. Uh, but again, please settle
in. Welcome to the 2026 Ideas
Conference. We're excited to have you.
Thank you.
[applause]
It was my view that one of the [music]
things we lacked was a place that was
really generating a new set of ideas
that could power progressive politics.
The Center for American Progress has
ideas that changed [music] the world.
Since opening our doors in 2003, CAP has
played a major role in developing the
governing agenda for the country. From
leading the push to end the Iraq war to
being the first think tank to support
marriage equality to launching a new
healthc care framework that led to the
Affordable Care Act and a new climate
agenda that led to the inflation
reduction act. The mission of CAP has
been to improve the lives of all
Americans through strong leadership,
organized action and of course big
ideas. We have hosted important leaders
to discuss a new path forward. I believe
that the only way to govern is by
delivering the big things that help
people.
>> I want to lay out what is an [music]
economic war plan because any successful
vision of America must start with an
economy [music] that works for everyone.
>> My road map, AI for America, identifies
how to ensure we continue to lead in
artificial intelligence. This week
[music] you gave a speech about how
faith can address some of these
monumental challenges.
And we have an agenda to make life more
affordable immediately and in the long
run. From a [music] health care plan
that lowers costs to an energy plan that
would help states lower rates and invest
in the grid to a housing plan that would
lower rents while building millions of
new homes. The country is hungry for a
new direction with new ideas and new
leaders. Welcome to the ideas
conference.
Please welcome to the stage cap
president and CEO Nerra Tanden.
>> Good morning everyone. How you doing?
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> Good morning everyone. How you doing?
[laughter]
We are excited to host thinkers,
activists, leaders, Americans from
across the country to this year's ideas
conference and to welcome the thousands
of people online tuning in. We are
thrilled to have next generation leaders
from every part of our country, all
offering new ideas on the path forward.
But as we look to the future, we cannot
ignore the present.
The truth is we are meeting at a dark
moment in our nation's history with
rampant corruption,
division, and a sense of misery for the
middle class. Consider just the last few
weeks. Partisan justices of the Supreme
Court working to wipe out black
political power in the South.
Trump's Treasury Department settling an
$1.8
billion slush fund with their po boss
Donald Trump and his political allies. A
slush fund that you and I are paying
for.
Trump's war with Iran driving gas prices
up to $5 across the country. On top of
the pain of tariffs, inflation
outstripping wages for the first time in
years.
The good news is the American people are
waking up and realizing finally that the
Trump administration is failing and
failing them. His decisions and his
decisions alone are making life less
affordable for all Americans including
the working-class people who he got to
vote for them. These are policy
failures.
Still, to escape the cycle of
polarization,
I believe we need to address not only
Trump's current failings, but his rise.
In 2010, at the height of the Great
Recession, about 60% of Americans agreed
that they could improve their standard
of living in the future. In 2024, that
number was just 25%.
That is a high level of pessimism for
the future. And I believe pessimism
begets fear. And when people are
fearful, it is much easier to hate.
to forcefully challenge the polarization
we are living through. I believe we need
to confront that pessimism and fear. The
fact is Americans feel stuck because
they are more stuck. It is harder to
move up. Kids born in the 1940s had n a
90% chance of doing better than their
parents. Kids born in the 1980s,
it's just a coin flip. And it's less
today than even then. It's no wonder
that today only a quarter of Americans
feel like the American dream
is real, less than any point in modern
American history.
So my friends, I believe it is crucial
that we criticize Trump's policies for
the harms that he's doing, but it is not
enough.
The country is demanding a vision of how
the future will be better than the past
for all of us. Restoration is not
sufficient.
We cannot just go back to days gone by.
We cannot tinker.
It is time for transformation
with ideas that meet the scale of the
problem with an ambition that meets the
scale of people's desperation.
Forging a new social contract in the
country where hard work pays, where
striving
one of us, every single one of us can go
as far as our talents take us. Where we
believe our children will be better off
than we are. A vision that offers hope.
An agenda that tackles what is failing
and makes it work again for all of us.
My friends, I believe we can use this
dark moment as a springboard to a
better, stronger, fairer country. But we
will not do that with circular firing
squads. Although we know how to do that
well.
We will be do we will do it by building
a big resilient broad majority in the
country. A big tent where we stretch
ourselves to welcome converts just as we
celebrate stalwarts. An army big enough
to not just win the next battle, but win
the war to end the politics of hate. I
believe our country is worth fighting
for. I think this is the fight of our
lives. And I do believe that when we
offer better ideas, we will win. And I
am so thrilled that at today's CAP Ideas
Conference, we will have new leaders
discussing those very ideas to make our
world and country better. Thank you for
all Thank you all for being here.
We're excited.
Speaking of fighting, I am thrilled to
uh to have our first major speaker of
the day, Senator Ruben Ggo, who has a
fighter in so many ways. He deployed to
the Iraq war as a Marine fighting in
infantry men of a Marine a Marine
infantry men in 2005 with a unit that
took some of the heaviest casualties of
that war. He knows America must always
have a plan to win the fight and to help
our soldiers when they get home. With
troops once again in conflict that the
president can't explain to Congress or
the country, that mission could not be
more urgent. So, please give a big
welcome to Senator Ruben Ggo, who will
discuss his views on national security
and a vision for the future. Senator
Ggo.
Thank you, Ner, for the introduction and
thank you Center for American Progress
for bringing us together. I'm here today
because right now UNC our country is in
danger.
Will this president continue to drag
America into another endless Middle East
war while families struggle to pay for
groceries, gas, rent, mortgage? and
where are the voices that are standing
for them right now?
If we're serious about solving the
problems of the world and problems
facing Americans, then we have to deal
with a simple truth. We have to fight
for the country that we want.
As a Marine, I deployed to Iraq and I've
lived the idea firsthand that foreign
policy starts at home. Our standing in
the world is only as strong as the
economy and the values that we show in
this country. When we engage abroad, it
must be with a clear plan, a moral
compass, and a deep respect for working
Americans who pay the price when things
go wrong, either with their livelihoods
or with their taxes. Whether it's the
cost of gasoline or the life of a young
Marine, the stakes of our leadership are
measured in the kitchens and the living
rooms of places like Phoenix in Tucson,
not just Washington DC and Alexandria.
Right now, Americans are getting
squeezed from every direction. When you
look at the price of gas right now at $5
a gallon in Arizona alone with the
soaring cost of groceries and housing,
these just aren't abstract data points.
These are the direct consequences of a
war of choice in Iran.
This is a war that wasn't planned,
wasn't authorized, and is not making us
safer. Trump got his war, and working
families got stuck with the bill. Every
day, consumers are paying price, paying
the price at the pump. In Arizona, if
you can't afford to fill that gas tank,
that means you can't go to work. You
can't go to school. You can't truly live
the American dream. This administration
has not thought any of this through.
They left our oil reserves low and
failed to even work with our allies to
prepare for the calamity that came. They
thought this would be easy, which is
exactly what I heard before I went to
Iraq. Let me tell you, it wasn't easy.
They thought Iran won't push back. And
tragically, they're deeply wrong. This
war, this war of choice is costing us a
billion dollar a day. $1 billion a day.
And think what we could be doing with
that money right now. Not just building
ballrooms, but think how we could be
finding our schools, supporting our
veterans,
and trying to take care of those that
are just trying to make it every day.
For me, this feels like deja vu. Trump
and his lackey are more than happy to
send 18, 19-year-old boys and girls to
war, just like they did to me and my
brothers 21 years ago. And now, when the
president comes to Congress asking for
more money, he's not even asking for
support for our veterans that are still
hurting. No, he's still asking for money
for his insurrectionists buddies and to
build a stupid ballroom.
It's disgraceful. It's disgraceful that
we have veterans that are still lacking
and yet he doesn't fight for them. The
guys I serve with in Ohio and New Mexico
and Arizona and even the Arizonans back
home, they tell me right now they're
hurting. They tell me they're just not
making it and they're not making enough
and that their communities, their
families are truly suffering.
And what do we hear from this
administration? Trump the Republicans
are cutting Medicaid for the poorest of
Americans and kicking families off food
stamps when grocery prices are jumping
through the roof. And to add insult to
injury, it's not just a matter of
funding priorities. He's taxing all them
at the same time. He's raising tariffs
that cost the average American family
$1,200 a year. The average American
family cannot take more than a $700
fluctuation in a year. And where is this
president at for them? Unfortunately,
the mess in the Middle East is not the
only mess this president is about to
create. You've all seen the news. Trump
is laying the groundwork now for his
next endeavor, invading Cuba.
For what?
It's not responding to some kind of new
threat. He's manufacturing one and using
it to build a case, a case, an illegal
case with war in Cuba. Here's my
solution to all this. It's quite
complicated, so you have to really pay
attention.
Don't start stupid wars.
[applause]
End this war in Iran as fast as
possible. Stop the unauthorized strikes
off Colombia and Venezuela. And make
this administration answer for every
dollar they have miss, misallocated, and
misdirected. And then we can actually
start moving into a place where the
American family is thought of first and
not last. Yes, America first. Does that
sound familiar? We can build that
country that we want. Now, I see on
Twitter all the time, well, if you're
against the war in Iran, why do you
support the war in Ukraine? Let me be
clear. The Ukrainian people are fighting
for their independence, and it's in our
strategic interest to make sure that
they win, that Europe wins, and that we
all win and defeat Russia. I am proud to
have spent 10 years the Armed Services
Committee and I'll soon be heading
actually to the Black Sea Conference in
Odessa, Ukraine later this month. And I
want to see firsthand what is stopping
Putin on the Black Sea. What Ukraine's
fight can teach us about the future of
warfare. And my message to Ukrainians,
to Americans, and to our allies, Ukraine
can win this war, and Ukraine must win
this war. If we turn our backs on them
now, it will be a moral strain stain on
this country. Something that we will
regret for generations to come. And
perhaps more importantly, our allies
will never forget it or forgive us. It
is more than just a moral obligation. It
is a strategic masterclass if we
succeed. And the Ukrainians are showing
us the future of warfare now. Creating
better systems when they knew they could
not engage in a bullet forbullet war.
They've essentially destroyed 26% of the
Russia's Russians Black Sea fleet. And
how do they do it? Not with a$1 13
billion aircraft carrier, but with
lowcost baby Navy drones that cost less
than $20,000.
They are providing and proving what we
need to know and that we don't need to
spend tens of billions of dollars on
outdated legacy systems that are sitting
ducks in a modern conflict and only will
cost our taxpayers more and more.
Ukraine is showing us a future of
warfare and they are meeting the moment
one drone at a time. We need to learn
these lessons for our own defense if we
haven't seen what happened in Iran
already. We need to move from deterrence
by punishment, waiting for invasion,
then reacting to deterrence by denial so
that our neighbors, our enemies think
again of invading either Ukraine, the
Baltics, or Taiwan. We need to align our
industrial base with our allies to
ensure we produce cheap, scalable
missions that actually win modern
conflicts. And we can't keep building
the weapons of the last century while
adversaries are innovating and fighting
the future wars.
Coming out of the Trump summit, one
thing is not negotiable. America does
not trade away Taiwan's security for
photo op or cheap words. We must we must
uphold our long-standing commitments to
Taiwan, continue our arm sales, and
strengthens Taiwan's self-defense
capabilities. And the commitment is not
only because Taiwan produces chips that
our economy depends on. It's because if
we abandon Taiwan, the world will
abandon us. America's asymmetric
advantage in the world is that we have
friends. We have allies. We have friends
and allies that will go to war with us.
China has customers and they have
clients. They have vassal states. We
have allies that have fought with us and
will continue to fight with us. But not
if we abandon Taiwan, Ukraine, and NATO.
When this president even discusses
military action against any NATO
country, we are making China stronger.
Or when we treat our partners as
secondary partners and allies, instead
of friends, we are making China
stronger. And if we create a vacuum by
undermining our friends, China will fill
it. from Kuwait to South Korea to South
America to everywhere else in the world.
We are seeing this happen right now in
our own backyard. If our allies in the
Indoacific or Latin America stop
trusting us, they will find friends in
Beijing. And we cannot push Latin
America anywhere further towards China.
We must look at our relationship with
the Western Hemisphere through the prism
of true alliances, economic
collaboration, and friendship. We need a
prosperous Latin America and a
prosperous European Union to stand up to
China's sheer mass and capital markets.
The America first attitude is actually
going to make us America last. We cannot
meet China's sheer capital and market
alone. But if we stand with our allies
and combine our populations, our buying
power, our economies, and our moral
directions together, then we actually
have a fighting chance for that future.
But alone, we can never meet the demand.
Not now or in the future.
Principal leadership means having the
humility to admit when a war is a
mistake. If that had been if that had
occurred 20 years ago, there would have
been thousands and thousands of men and
women that would be alive right now,
including my best friend. It means that
we have to we also have the courage to
stand by our allies when the stakes are
real. And it means being honest with the
American people about the costs of our
choices.
Leadership means building an economy
that works for the person driving to
work in Phoenix as much as it is for
that person that commutes in Washington
DC. And it it means that we assure that
the American dream stays alive for
everyone, not just the elite few. It is
about building the country that we want.
And we need to be realistic about the
dangers. But we're also optimistic about
our future. And if we lead with our
values and our allies, that future is a
great future. Thank you so much. Enjoy
the conference. [applause]
[music]
The cost of living has gone crazy. It's
gotten harder for people to live. The
Center for American Progress Action
[music] Fund is lifting up voices of
everyday Americans being squeezed by the
high cost of living and holding
Republicans accountable for the pain
[music] that they cause.
>> Across the nation, CAP Action is doing
the work of finding and sharing these
stories. I'm talking about farmers,
teachers, bus drivers, and steel
workers. [music] The people who are
bearing the heaviest weight of our
society, yet are being pulled further
and further away from the American
dream. Now I'm looking at $1,500 a month
of an increase for my monthly premium
[music] if these tax credits expire.
>> Everything is expensive right now. I'm
feeling crushed by my electrical bill.
More farmers than ever in Iowa [music]
um are going bankrupt.
>> It takes one emergency and I am on the
street, you know, like all of these
things are just kind of hanging over my
head. It's one slip up and that's it.
>> And once these stories get out, they
spread [music] everywhere. That's
because the testimony of your neighbor
is much more powerful [music] than any
other secondhand source. These
storytellers are our neighbors.
>> I benefited from the ACA [music] tax
credits as you all have heard. Then as a
part of Trump's agenda, I now pay just
short of $10,000. Affordability [music]
looks very different today.
>> So, I was just wondering what your
thoughts are and plans might be.
>> Thank you. I'm not going to talk to you.
Many Americans are still struggling to
afford basic necessities, [music]
struggling to make ends meet.
>> Many of us do have to work two jobs.
>> The video shows Central [music] High
School teacher John Havchek walking
alongside Van Orton inside the capital
and asking, quote, "What are you going
to do to bring costs down for
constituents like me?" Just like its
sister organization, the Center for
American Progress is leaving no stone
unturned to expose all the ways that the
Trump administration [music]
and those who have supported its
policies have made life more expensive
for all Americans. [music]
Whether it's the war in Iran, Trump's
tariffs, congressional Republicans
[music] big, beautiful bill, SNAP cuts,
the ACA subsidies, and so much more. CAP
has kept [music] the drum beat going.
>> But we know that it's not enough to
fight back against bad ideas. We have to
offer solutions [music]
to tangibly improve people's lives,
something for people to be for,
something for people to vote for. And
that's exactly what we're doing here at
CAP, [music] authoring bold plans to
lower costs for all Americans.
>> Cities and towns [music] sign what's
called an affordability contract. We
will help them finance the building of
affordable housing if they take [music]
down the barriers to building that are
making buildings so expensive. CAP and
CAP action are driving the [music]
conversation in communities by blending
policy research, earned media, digital
engagement, [music] and storytelling.
Through this dynamic approach, we are
changing hearts and minds. [music]
[music]
Heat
>> [music]
>> up
[music]
>> [music]
>> Please welcome MS Now's Katherine Rampel
and panelists, Representative Greg Casar
of Texas, Representative Maxwell Frost
of Florida, Representative Lauren
Underwood of Illinois, Okay.
[music]
Thanks everyone. We're going to get
right into the big topic of this year's
election and of course the main topic
that Americans care about which is
affordability
and what exactly our lawmakers and other
policy makers can do about it. So, I
want to start with Congressman Khazar.
As the chair of the Congressional
Progressive Caucus, you all recently
released a uh new affordability agenda
that deals with the costs of groceries,
housing, child care, uh health care. I'm
sure there's something I'm leaving out
there. However, pardon, gas,
all sorts of goodies.
However, even if Democrats sweep the
House this midterms and maybe even take
the Senate, you will still have to
contend with a Republican in the White
House, President Donald Trump, who can
veto legislation. So, my question for
you is, what on the agenda do you think
you can actually get signed into law in
the next year? Is this mostly a
messaging bill or excuse me a messaging
agenda about what you would like to get
done or are there concrete things that
you think you could peel off either
Republican support in the legislature
and or uh the support of a president so
that people's lives and access to an
affordable lifestyle can actually change
next year.
>> Thank you for the question. Good morning
everyone. Uh so the progressive caucus
put out a list of 10 proposals to lower
the cost of everything from housing to
child care, gas, utilities, to stop
price gouging, to increase your wages
and benefits. And when we went out and
tested the support for the progressive
caucus's ideas, we found not only
overwhelming support amongst Democrats
and independents and voters in swing
districts, but amongst Republicans where
actually not a single one of the ideas
that we can talk about here in a moment
pulled at less than twothird support
amongst Republican voters. And so I when
I I believe just like leader Jeffre
believes that we will retake the House
through the work that we do over the
next few months and then there will be
um a lot of accountability work that
Democrats rightly need to do against the
Trump administration. But if all we do
is accountability, but don't also do
affordability work, show voters not only
that we're against Trump, voters already
know that, but also show people what
we're for, regain people's trust as the
party of workingclass people, then I
think we'll have failed. And so I think
that we should push forward bold ideas
like and new ideas that will interest
voters like Roana's windfall profits tax
on the gas companies that are making a
killing right now. Instead of just
providing people a small amount of
relief, we should tax the enormous
profits that the oil companies are
making by jacking up prices right now.
Send a rebate check back to Americans.
And at $100 a barrel of oil, uh, this
proposal would send everybody about a
$400 rebate. We should pass that out of
the House if we retake the Senate, push
to get that out of the Senate, and then
either win Donald Trump's signature
because it's supported just as heavily
by Republican voters as Democratic
voters. Or he can veto it. And if he
does, then it shows voters that
Democrats were fighting to lower their
costs and that Donald Trump stopped it.
And then those contenders running for
president in the next election cycle
have a foundation of ideas to say,
"Donald Trump blocked that bill that
would have lowered your utility costs by
$500 a year. Donald Trump blocked that
bill that would have lowered your
grocery prices and I would have signed
it." And I think that that is the kind
of aggressive posture that Democrats
need to take to not only be an
anti-Trump party, but a pro-workass
party. And to clarify, do you think that
the windfall profits tax piece of this
would be the one that would be most
likely to h have real real bene
>> I don't get paid enough to be a good
Donald Trump predictor.
>> Fair.
>> Um um but I think that we should not
lower our ambitions as a house majority
as whatever we can get uh the Donald
Trump world to think we can do. I think
that we actually have to make sure that
voters understand that we really care
about their pocketbooks. I hear about it
all the time when I've I've done over
half a district dozen town halls in
Republican held districts and I ask
people that voted for Vice President
Harris to lower their hands not ask me a
question for a second and for people
that voted for Trump or chose not to
vote to ask me a question. And I hear
time and time and time again that maybe
they voted for Trump, but they're
already sick of him, but they want to
know what Democrats will do so that
people don't have to check their bank
account before they go to the grocery
store. People say, "I pull 712s." That
means working over 70 hours a week, but
still can't afford my childare. We
should pass uh the bill that was Mikey
Cheryl's bill. now is AOCC's bill that
would guarantee $10 a day childare to
virtually every single family and tax
the ultra rich. To do it, we should uh
pass my bill that would update our
overtime laws for the first time in 90
years to have overtime, pay double time
so that people can make a little bit
more money and maybe work a little bit
fewer hours so they can actually spend
time with their kids. And when we talk
about ideas like that, I think we can
build the kind of big tent coalition
necessary to not just win a midterm on
anti-Trump sentiment, but actually bring
the Democratic party back in line with
the vast majority of our natural base.
Congressman Frost, the largest monthly
expense for most households is housing,
which has become a huge burden, not just
on the blue coasts, the liberal coasts,
but basically nationwide at this point.
And there's lots of evidence that since
2006, more or less, we have underbuilt
housing across this country. that as
younger people have moved out of their
parents' homes and formed their own
families, there's just not enough
housing for them to buy. What can we do?
And and and in fact, as I'm sure you
know, uh a lot of members of Gen Z think
that home ownership is out of their
reach forever. So, what can we do to
ensure that there is enough housing for
everyone?
>> This is really important. I think to
what Greg was saying, we would have
failed if we do not as a Democratic
majority move forward a comprehensive
housing package um that will address
this from A to Z. And part of the
problem with this whole discussion in
housing is everybody has one idea and
they think that idea is the thing that's
going to solve the problem. This is just
not true. Um this is a a difficult
problem for the federal government to
tackle, but I think we can tackle it. Um
and it's going to take everything. We
have to ensure that we build more
housing. Of course, there's a lot of
things that we can do as a government to
incentivize cities and towns and
municipalities to get rid of
exclusionary zoning, get rid of parking
minimums, these different things that we
need to do to make sure that we have
more inventory. But that alone is not
enough. We also have to ensure that we
pass uh good consumer protection laws to
protect tenants, which is something
that's really near and dear to me. I
live in Florida, which has some of the
worst tenant protections in the nation.
While I was running for Congress, when
the rent hike moratorum was lifted uh
during COVID, I got priced out of my
apartment. I was homeless for two
months. I literally spent all my money
in my bank account on an Airbnb for a
month and I was like, "Future Max will
figure it out." A month passed. Future
Max did not figure it out. And uh and
then I was homeless for for a while
during my campaign. Then I said, "Well,
at least if I win my race for Congress,
I will never have to deal with this
again." I get elected to Congress and as
a congressman elect I get denied to
every apartment complex I applied to
here in DC because my credit score was
poor because during my campaign I ran
ran up a ton of debt. And so I and there
was nothing to help protect me or help
me get into housing. In fact, when I
moved to DC, I took out a loan to be
able to pay the first last and deposit
um to get a place here. And even with
the money in my bank, even though my dad
would say if you had to take a loan out,
you'd have the money. But even with the
money in my bank, um I couldn't get a
place to live. I was told no. I I was
told no to having the high honor of
paying the high rent. And so I just
think there's a lot we need to do. And
then home ownership is such an important
part of this, especially for young
people, but really everybody. I've been
doing a lot of town halls across Florida
and in my district on housing
specifically, which is the number one
issue I hear about when I go knock doors
anywhere in my state.
And we have a homeowners insurance
crisis in the state of Florida and
really across the country that is
pricing out seniors and homes that
they've lived in their entire lives
pretty much, but they're on a fixed
income and they're having to put their
home up for sale. And young people who
are saying not only is it a figment or
something they feel like it can never
happen. It's just like out of the realm
of possibility. And this leads to a
bigger problem. Usually the largest
asset a working person will own is what?
Their house.
We are we have a ownership crisis in
this country that deeply impacts working
people and especially young people. Not
to put my tinfoil hat on, but it's
everything. It's it's housing and we're
moving. If current trends continue, most
people will the vast majority of people
will not own their home. They'll rent
forever and the rents can continue to go
up or down. We don't own the music we
listen to anymore. We don't own the
movies we watch anymore. If trends
continue, most people won't own the car
that they drive. And actually, if trends
continue, most people won't own the
phone that they have in their pocket.
You won't own a damn thing. And I think
the the the home ownership crisis is
indicative of something much bigger
going on where just a few people will
have the keys to everything in our
country, which means when somebody needs
to be bailed out, who gets bailed out?
The people who own everything. And that
is an existential problem for working
people in the rest of this country. It's
not that we don't want people to do
well. We want everybody to do well. But
it's kind of hard to do that in this
country when you can't even own the roof
over your head. Um, and so, um, I think
there's a lot we can do as a nation.
Something a lot of people aren't talking
about is manufactured housing. I just
released a bill on this, which
[clears throat]
right now in Florida, about a fourth of
the manufactured housing communities
have been purchased by private equity.
And in case you don't know, the way it
works, you essentially own the the house
you live in, the manufactured home, but
you don't own the land that the home is
on. And what's going on is these
communities are being bought usually
from mom and pop companies across the
country and having their rents jacked
up, their lot rents jacked up by a lot.
In fact, there's a community in my
district who saw it go up by double. And
now they're putting the taxes of the
land on the renters as well. And so, and
manufactured housing for a lot of
seniors and a lot of veterans is the
last safe haven for home ownership,
affordable home ownership in the
country. And so I put forth a bill um
that essentially will help us make it so
that way folks who live in these
communities can own the land that their
house is on top of as well. But it's
like things like this that piece
together I think can create a
comprehensive housing bill to help us
with this crisis. But the era of the
federal government saying that's a state
and local issue is over. There's a lot
that we can do to help solve the housing
crisis. I'm wondering actually if you
could talk a little bit more about
creating incentives for states and
localities to allow more building in
part because of something that you just
said that for many Americans their
single most valuable asset is in their
home. So that means when housing prices
fall or rents fall which is necessary
for people who are trying to get into a
home that also means that somebody's
nest egg gets less valuable. Right?
That's part of the reason why it is so
difficult to build in a lot of
communities in America because people
don't necessarily want their house their
home value to decrease because that's
their retirement. And so that leads to a
lot of friction against building new
homes because the supply of new homes
again will benefit people who are trying
to get into housing but may hurt the
people who already own their homes. So,
how do you change that dynamic so that
you don't have sort of that almost
natural nimiest impulse for people to
not want more housing lest it devalue
what is their retirement plan?
>> I and I've had this conversation a lot
in my roundts when we talk about housing
and it people come from different places
if they would consider themselves a
nimi, right? Um, I got to tell you, for
a lot of the more working families I
speak to who have been able to get into
home ownership, even though they've been
able to get into it, most of them, not
most of them, but a lot of them are what
you would consider house poor, right?
Where they have gotten to a situation
where mortgage, insurance, um, taxes,
everything that you have to pay. Most of
them are paying PMI because they
couldn't afford the deposit on their,
uh, on their home. um uh are in a place
where they just don't have that kind of
money. So they they do want of course
their home value to go up. Anyone wants
that, but I think people see what's
going on in their communities and they
understand the fact that the home prices
are so high and most of them are the
sticker shock is is so recent for them.
They just purchased their home maybe a
year ago or maybe they purchased it 10
years ago and they too realize that the
price of their home was way too high.
And I think there's a lot of things that
we can do to help with that. But this
notion that we have to pit homeowners
against tenants or homeowners against
potential homeowners, I think is is
false. And I don't see it in my
community and I also don't see it when I
travel the country and talk with people
about housing prices because I hear many
of the same complaints from people
regardless of what situation they're in.
>> Congressman Underwood, you've worked
throughout your career on healthcare um
including in the implementation of the
Affordable Care Act.
Historically, Democrats, I think, have
focused their firepower when it comes to
health care on expanding insurance, on
making sure more people are covered.
There are obviously a lot of
frustrations now about the cost of
health care even among those who are
insured, who have insurance plans. What
can be done to make health care
affordable? to make healthcare more
affordable for those who have coverage
as the promise of the Affordable Care
Act uh indicated.
>> Well, I think that this is by far one of
the most salient issues in this moment
uh because everyone needs health care.
You need to be able to see a provider,
fill a prescription, get a procedure
when you need one, right? And so this is
something that's top of mind for so many
folks. And yet you have Donald Trump and
the Republicans in charge passing their
big ugly bill taking a trillion dollars
out of Medicaid. So we have about six
months until we reach this point where
the American people are really going to
be feeling that acutely of folks being
kicked off of their coverage. So it's
not about at that level affordable.
That's do you have healthcare or not?
Yes or no. Um we have a real crisis
right now because they refuse to extend
the ACA tax credits. the extremely
popular ACA tax credits uh that was
based on my bill, the Healthcare
Affordability Act, which drove down the
uninsured rate to the lowest levels in
US history. But Donald Trump told the
Republicans, "Don't waste time on
extending them. And now 20% of enrolles
have been kicked off their plans because
they can't afford to see their premium
double, triple, quadruple." Right? So,
some of the stuff is just real basic,
like extend the ACA tax credits, like an
overwhelming majority of the House of
Representatives voted to do in January
of this year after we stood together and
forced a discharge petition and a floor
vote on the House. Right? We got 17
Republicans to stand with us, but the
Senate refused to take it up. Right?
This solution is right there for us in
our grasp. Um, obviously
making sure that we can take action
quickly in a Democratic majority to
block these Medicaid cuts from going
into effect, the 500 billion dollars
that's slated to come out of Medicare.
But then you have all kind of stuff that
we need to do on prescription drugs,
improving access to primary care visits,
improving access for people who uh just
need to be able to use the health care
that they have. We know that there are
tremendous barriers to people being able
to manage their chronic illnesses
uh to being able to actually improve
their health care status. And then we
have this whole issue of uh health
equity where we have these entrenched um
um disparities that we see among
communities of color, rural communities,
low-income communities, etc. Right? And
so all of that will require our
intention and our investment. I think at
the end of the day if we only focus on
cost
then we are not always improving our
health care system. If we only focus on
cost we are not always improving folks
health status. And I think that when we
have a Robert Kennedy as the secretary
of health and human services serving as
the biggest source of misinformation
and the largest threat to public health
in our country. We have to have a wide
angle lens when it comes to tackling the
multifaceted healthc care issues that we
face. Just right now today, we got an
Ebola outbreak
with an American who's been confirmed
and nothing out of HHS. Right now today,
you got the Hunter virus and folks
freaking out and nothing. We can't get
access to reliable data, right? Like I
guess my point is this. Yes, we have to
lower costs to win this election. We
have to have a plan. I think we have a
plan. People understand it. It's not
that complicated. We're the party that
believes you deserve healthare.
They're the party that believes actually
no.
Nope. Sorry. It's that simple, right? It
doesn't have to be more complicated than
that. But I think in order to actually
make improvements, we have to tackle the
wide range of issues.
>> Well, can you give a little bit of color
to that? So, what are some examples of
things that Democrats should be focusing
on, should be pitching to voters as we
head into the midterms? Uh, I take your
point about expanding or or re-upping
those uh um enhanced premium tax credits
and rolling back some of the Medicaid
cuts. Beyond those two things, which are
about undoing Trump damage, are there
other specific points that you think are
pretty salient to voters? Sure. That
could address costs, let's say.
>> Okay. Well, you know, you need to have a
place to go and so let's make sure that
our rural hospitals are in good shape. I
represent a suburban and rural community
outside of Chicago where already in the
last year since the big ugly bill has
been into effect, we've seen unit
closures, pedes closures, ICUs closures.
Um, and those facilities need a cash
infusion. They need some help staying
open. I have a bill prioritizing our
rural hospitals act. Easy. We could get
that moving in the farm bill, guys. It
doesn't even I mean, hello. Let's be
smart in how we move our bills. Um I
think that we have the the Department of
Health um Department of Education is
trying to roll back access to student
loans for our healthcare workers, right?
So, we're going to have fewer providers.
If you have if you don't have access to,
let's say, a nurse practitioner in your
community and there is no physician,
what are you supposed to do? We need to
expand our healthcare workforce so that
people can actually go in. That's how we
drive down costs. We need more workers
in every community in every zip code. We
are trying to overturn this uh really
devastating regulation coming from the
Department of Education on prescription
drugs. I mean everything from inhalers
to um insulin to you know anything to
manage uh chronic illness. I have a
bill, the Chronic Copay, chronic
condition copay elimination act.
Okay? Like there's solutions. It doesn't
have to explode the deficit or anything
like that. We just have to care to solve
the problem. Um but I think that in
terms of messaging for the election, we
keep it real tight and real simple. Fix
our broken healthcare system. It doesn't
have to be more complicated than that.
It really doesn't. And I would really
encourage us to really focus on winning
so that people can get the healthcare
that they deserve.
[applause]
Congressman Kazar,
Democrats have to this date made a
relatively compelling case that part of
the ail affordability crisis falls at
the feet of Donald Trump's economic
agenda, particularly his tariffs.
And if you look at estimates from places
like the Yale Budget Lab, they suggest
that the tariffs in the past year raised
the costs for America typical American
household by at least $700, something in
that wheelhouse. I noticed that in your
plan for an affordability for the
progressive affordability agenda, there
was nothing about tariffs. So my
question to you is given that Democrats
have isolated one of the core problems
as being about this trade policy if
Democrats retake the House and the
Senate. Do you think Trump's tariff
should be on the chopping block?
>> Yes. I mean I think that we absolutely
will and should undo the reckless tariff
policy from Trump. But if all we do, if
we get pushed to say all we're going to
do is undo his Medicaid cuts, all we do
is undo his tariffs, um then I think we
are going to wind up in a real problem
because there are forces within the
party arguing essentially Democrats stay
boring. That what we want is just for
everybody to notice how bad Trump is,
for us to not be too noticed, and then
things will go our way. that may turn
out to work in a midterm election, but
if we follow the Constitution, Trump
won't be on the ballot again. And if we
don't regain the trust of working
people, and if people don't know what
we're for, then I'm worried that Josh
Holly or JD Vance or Tucker Carlson or
whoever could beat us next. And that's
just not acceptable because it's already
been way too hard on the country to deal
with a year and a half of this. Imagine
12 years of this kind of a White House.
So if we want to re regain people's
trust, they have to know that yes, we're
going to repeal the horrible Trump
policies. We're going to hold them
accountable for their criminal and
corrupt actions, but also that we're
willing to take on villains in the AI
industry that are price gouging you. We
have a bill in the new affordability
agenda to ban surveillance pricing where
for example the other day JetBlue
basically admitted on the internet to
someone that they were having to buy a
plane ticket to get to a funeral.
JetBlue had data on the person and they
suddenly had a ticket price nearly $300
higher. We should just ban that and take
on those
>> Sorry to interrupt. JetBlue has actually
since said that they do not use any
personal data
>> that they should support the bill if
they think that nobody should be allowed
to do that. Um, of course they said
that. Um, Instacart got caught doing the
exact same thing. We should be willing
to take on the utility companies that
Democrats and Republicans alike hate
because our utility costs for these
for-profit utilities. Some people's
bills have gone up 50%. Just in the last
few years, Donald Trump became president
villainizing immigrants, saying that the
bad guys were LGBT youth. And I think
Democrats need to be willing to take on
villains ourselves, whether it's in big
oil or in big pharma or these big
utility companies, so that people notice
us, so that people know who we are. And
in my view, those ideas actually unite
the party. Whether you are moderate or
progressive, these ideas are very, very
popular across the country. They divide
the lobbyists. They might us get us
uninvited from some dinners, but I would
rather get an uninvited from some
dinners and win the damn election.
>> [applause]
>> Just before we move on from tariffs for
a second,
the constitution article one says that
congress has power over international
commerce and uh sets and lays taxes. Do
you think to your point about
future presidents may try to abuse their
power in similar ways that should
Democrats retake the Senate and the
House, they should try to curb the
limits on all presidents ability to set
tariff policy without the consent of of
Congress because over the years Congress
has essentially delegated away a lot of
its constitutional authority here. Yeah,
we need um we need definitely need
structural reform to make our policies
stick and to make sure that voters
voices are heard. And so uh of course we
should rein in uh the justices, the
Supreme Court, the folks that continue
to let Trump have this runaway power. Um
because I don't think that um we will
have succeeded in the next trifecta if
we get there. um if we pass the John
Lewis Voting Rights Act, if we pass
these bills to lower your housing costs
or increase health care and the Supreme
Court just tells us no. Um, so I think
that in this moment where a right-wing
Supreme Court is so eroding, voters
rights, so eroding the Constitution, we
have to be willing to say that we need
to take on the Supreme Court, make sure
that voters uh concerns and voices are
heard so that we actually restore
abortion rights, so that we actually
restore civil rights, and so that we
actually can show people we made their
lives cheaper uh and less expensive.
That's what FDR um had to to try to do
or at least threaten to do. And what I
hear from folks all the time is that
they would vote for the Democratic Party
of FDR and LBJ of the New Deal and the
Fair Labor Standards Act and building
unions across the country and defeating
fascism around the world and the Voting
Rights Act and the Civil Rights Act and
the creation of Medicare and Medicaid
and Head Start. That's the kind of
democratic party we need to be and that
means being willing to take on an outofc
control executive as well as the Supreme
Court.
>> Well, part of the reason
>> [applause]
>> Part of the reason I asked specifically
about the executive rather than the
Supreme Court is that Donald Trump also
abused his I would argue abused his
tariff authority in his first term.
Democrats were very critical of those
tariffs. Then when his successor,
President Biden, came into office, he
kept almost all of those tariffs in
place. Uh maybe swapped some of them out
for different kinds of trade
restrictions.
>> Yeah. Look, I believe that we need to
restore the Constitution and that's part
of why I think justices need to actually
hold the executive to the to the law.
We've seen a huge double standard here
by this Supreme Court. That's the reason
I went there. I would caution us, of
course, we should take on Donald Trump
and the crazy way he's used the tariffs.
I mean, it's just I mean, you read what
he says on this any given day, it's
nuts. But I also don't want us to as
progressives, as liberals to be so I' we
are we have of course been so shocked by
how horrible Trump has abused his
authority and for our only response to
then be we need an executive who can do
very little because what we actually
also need is the for the next Democratic
president to be able to act aggressively
to rebuild everything that Doge tore
down to be able to implement policy
quickly. It's almost unthinkable today
that when LBJ signed uh Medicare into
law, he started enrolling millions of
seniors one year later than next July.
Uh we need an executive that when we
pass transformative policy that takes on
corporate interests and makes
workingclass people believe in our
collective power again that we have a
executive that can actually execute that
quickly and doesn't have to jump through
10 million hoops.
>> [applause]
>> Congressman Frost, uh, your colleague
just now or a few minutes ago mentioned
AI and a lot of the anxiety around AI.
As I'm sure our audience knows, it's
graduation season. People are graduating
from high school, graduating from
college. There is a lot of angst out
there about the job market. And if you
look at the unemployment rate for young
workers, whether college graduate or
not, it is ticking up. It is rising. And
some of that angst has to do with the
advent of this new technology that it
may displace a lot of entrylevel type
jobs.
To what extent do you think AIdriven job
displacement is similar or different
from other kinds of mass job
displacement? we've seen in the past.
I'm thinking things like trade uh other
kinds of automation
and how does that imply policy makers
should respond to it if it is similar or
if it is different? Is it is it the same
set of tools essentially that we've used
before for these other kinds of seismic
shifts or is it something different? I
>> I I mean there's similarities and
differences. I mean, one of the big
differences is the fact that the
difference between this and automation
is that this is going to be cheaper to
implement and happen more quickly than
it did with automation. So, there's less
time for us as a government to be able
to respond to helping our constituents,
working people. And taking a step back,
I think part of the issue that we have
in Congress is number one, most people
don't know anything about tech. Okay?
And that creates a big issue because we
have to legislate common sense guard
rails now because if we don't do that,
there will be an emergency that then
pushes us to have to advocate for
something more radical essentially that
will have that much more opposition. And
this whole thing happened with social
media. I always talk to people about
social media decades ago. Congress
buries its head in the sand. in fact, in
many cases, makes the situation worse
for the average person. Now, we're
having an emergency with social media,
keeping our children safe online, our
data being used against us, this and
that. And like the big idea people come
up with is like, let's ban Tik Tok.
Like, that's going to solve the problem.
And it didn't. And in fact, in many
cases, the whole that whole thing made
it worse. I'm really worried that when
it comes down to technology, Congress
does the same thing over and over again.
And it's really important. And I like
that I see more people running on this
because we need folks who are willing to
step into it, experts themselves,
because what ends up happening is that
industry writes the bill. We want common
sense guard rails. And this is what I
hear from people across the country when
I travel. You see the college
graduations. My University of Central
Florida, UCF, where my district is, um,
was had one of those viral videos of
someone saying AI is the next industrial
revolution and every student in the
audience booed. It's because and that's
coming from a real place guys. Right now
it is you it's always been hard to be a
young person. Yes. Right now it is
uniquely difficult and the numbers prove
this to us. For college graduates, it is
the worst time ever in this country's
history after you've done everything you
were told to do. You got all the debt
you were told to acrue. You were told
that if you acrew this debt, you'll be
able to get a good paying job and pay it
off and you'll be fine. It is the worst
time to find work for college graduates
in the history of our country. It's
right now. And so they see this, they
see the rise of AI, they see everything.
And people are rightfully nervous and
concerned that they won't be able to be
an adult that's able to feed themselves
and have a roof over their head. And so
I think it's important that Congress
does something and I am concerned about
it. Of course, we know that
like every technology, there are things
where we're going to have societal
benefits from it and there's things that
are not going to be a benefit to our
society. I guess where where I'm coming
from is the things that a lot of these
companies already say they believe in,
let's hold them to it and making sure we
pass common sense guard rails to protect
workers and protect working-class people
as we go into this. We know technology
far outpaces government and Congress.
And this is another problem. We have to
modernize government because we can't
keep up ourselves. We have no in we
don't have the in-house capabilities to
be able to keep up with the private
sector. And that's part of the reason
why we're always far behind. So, let's
pass common sense guard rails to hold
everyone to what they say they believe.
Anyway, um and I think that'll that's
really important in keeping our
constituents in mind.
>> I do want to push back on one thing.
It's not the worst time in history to
have been a college graduate. I mean,
college young college graduates, I think
their unemployment rate is like 5.6% or
something like that. It was definitely
higher during financial
>> crisis. But you have to take you have to
take in the totality of circumstances
going on in our country right now. Not
just finding employment, but the wages.
Have they kept up with inflation,
housing, the cost of food, healthcare,
all the things we're talking about right
now? So, yeah, marginally the numbers
might be up or down unemployment, but
the quality of the job, how much it pays
you, and what that pay is able to get
you is very difficult for young people
right now. Um, and I see it not just in
the numbers, all my friends, people my
age, my girlfriend, my my my best
friends, the people in my life who are
struggling with this right now. But so
you said common sense reforms. I think
everybody agrees common sense is a good
thing. I don't think anybody is like
against common sense. Well,
>> you'd be surprised.
>> Yeah,
>> there's a lot of pe There's a lot of
people against common sense.
>> There's a lot of money in not following.
>> Well, but again to to my question, what
does that mean in terms of protections
for workers or or how should policy
makers be thinking about this? Is it is
it just about again the same kinds of
tools we've had in the past,
unemployment insurance, other kinds of
safety net programs? Is there something
specific?
>> Yeah. And I wonder too in the affordable
affordab we have anything on AI in that
>> we we we had an anti-pric gouging
provision, but frankly uh I think that
if you listen to the CEOs of these AI
companies, they're talking about 20%
unemployment. Sure, it would be nice if
if it turns out not that way, but when
you hear Elon Musk saying humans won't
be needed for mo most work, when you
hear what Bill Gates has to say about
this, I think we should be um planning
aggressively that this isn't just the
invention of the steam engine. You're
talking about taking away uh a
foundational part of what makes us a
society, which is people having the
dignity of work. So I think we
aggressively should be thinking about
taxing AI as a method of making sure we
have sort of a works progress
administration of the future. We should
be making sure the government ensures
that we are not going up into depression
levels of unemployment. I think we need
an expansion of collective bargaining so
that workers have the power um to
negotiate um as AI is being integrated
um into our society because it the the
idea of just a big expansive social
safety net program. But 20% of people
aren't working. I think that is uh to me
that sounds dystopic and something the
Democratic party should be strongly
against.
>> And and something else I think is
important too on the AI conversation. I
I recently went to uh Los Angeles to
speak with a bunch of songwriters about
this. There's a lot of anxiety in the
creative economy. And in many ways, I
think actually starting the conversation
where it's the hardest and talking about
um how the rise of this is hurting
creatives. Um what does it mean to
create something? What does it mean to
be compensated for something? How can we
even how do we use the technology to
figure out if the song you wrote was
used in an AI model to write this other
song, this and that? I think solving
those questions are actually important.
Even though it might not feel pertinent
to most of society, these are the
hardest questions to answer in my
opinion as it relates to AI and emerging
technology. When you're able to answer
those hard questions, it it makes it
easier to to work backwards from that if
that makes sense.
>> Um, I'm going to take a question or two
from the audience. I have more of my
own, but the first question is for
everyone. What will you do to accelerate
the pace of implementation of solutions
such as things as getting more housing
built, solving for universal health
care, removal of Citizens United, a more
progressive tax system? Basically, how
will you move fast to solve problems?
Congressman, Congresswoman Underwood,
start with you.
>> Well, as Democrats, we like to be right.
Okay. We like to debate each other all
day. We have symposiums. We have
dinners. We write we write binders full
of policy white papers to assert our
opinion on why our idea is the best. We
got to get rid of that and work with the
urgency that we have seen on display
from Donald Trump and the Republicans in
charge. We have to get rid of the ego
and be willing to just get it done and
try to fix it later. Okay? I'm not
saying we have to hurt people, but I'm
saying like we cannot spend all of our
time and screw around with our majority
fighting with each other. And when we
have an idea that can get a majority
vote, we need to put it on the floor and
move forward. That's number one. Number
two, we got to get rid of the
filibuster. I don't want to hear it. But
but but but no, it's got to go. If we
are serious about saving this country,
our democracy, and advancing an
affordability agenda, that filibuster is
standing squarely in our path. And it's
got to go. And I just think in my
opinion, in my opinion, we are not
functioning in normal times. This is a
survival moment. In survival moments,
you make different decisions than you
would ordinarily make. And um I think we
have to be cleareyed about all that is
necessary to accomplish and the limited
window of time that we will have to get
these things done to [applause] to add
on this. And this is something I've been
thinking a lot about as well. A big
problem too is the way that Congress
writes the legislation and you you'd be
I mean just look at our immigration
system, right? I mean, it is just
peacemeal ideas thrown at something
after decade after decade after decade
and not some not a group of people
sitting down and figuring out how do we
make a system that works? How do we
create something that works? And my my
one concern with moving through big
packages is that it ends up being
peacemail ideas from different members
of Congress who I've had this bill and
I've had this idea for a long time and I
want to make sure it's in the package
that you're moving forward, but it
doesn't necessarily fit into a bigger
picture. And so to what Lawrence said,
that requires us to put our egos aside
for a minute and figure out how are we
going to pass legislation that of course
accomplishes what we want to accomplish.
Make sure that the executive has what
they need to to make the implementation
happen, but also possibly punish
agencies that don't move as quickly as
we want them to move by moving
responsibility to other agencies and
different things like that. And I think
when when we put on the hat of not just
what do we want the goal to be, but how
quickly do we want it, what do we want
the timeline to be as well, that's how
Congress is going to be able to write
real legislation that doesn't just talk
about what we want to have happen, but
how fast we want it to happen and
attaching, you know, real strings to
that. Um, so that way we have real
implementation and people feel it.
Because if people feel the thing we're
passing, four to eight years later,
another president comes in and pulls a
rug from, you know, underneath the bill.
It It didn't happen, right? It didn't
happen. And we need people to feel that
government can work for them um while
we're in power.
>> Sounds like you kind of want a
Democratic version of Doge if I'm
listening. But sure.
>> No, but that's the thing. Doge didn't do
anything. Like that's the thing with
with Republicans and and Donald Trump
right now. It's it's the illusion of
doing a lot and of course they're doing
horrible things. Number one, their
agenda is easier to achieve because it's
just destroying things and we want to
build things, but number two, like Doge
just really didn't do anything. It was a
lot of showmanship and so sort of we
want to actually do things and like
actually have people feel it in their
lives.
>> All right, Congressman Kazar, last word
to you.
I uh was a labor organizer in the
construction industry before running for
office and I think that we need to be
able to follow the construction site
test which is our idea is if can we go
talk to somebody on a construction site
and it makes sense to them and it would
help them and they understand it
quickly. Our prior child care proposals
are like we're going to send block
grants to the state and you can apply
for a voucher if you hit a certain
income level. People are like screw
this. They've already you've already
lost them. We just need to implement a
child care program that makes it so you
never pay more than 7% of your income.
It's going to be for every single
working American. Vast majority of
people pay $10 a day. Somebody say,
"Sign me up for that. Let's raise the
minimum wage. Let's guarantee everybody
two weeks paid vacation." Um, like these
are the basic things that we should just
be able to tell somebody this is for
you. It's going to improve your life and
we aren't going to go into a five-year
rulemaking process so that some other
president can take credit for what we
did. We want folks to say, "I voted for
that Democrat and I saw my life get
better after my vote." It's I think that
simple.
>> Well, thanks so much for the for the
question from our audience and thank you
to our excellent panel. Look forward to
talking more with you about all of these
great ideas. [applause]
Heat.
[music]
Heat. [music]
>> [music]
>> Please welcome CAP's senior vice
president for energy.
Everyone, just a quick word. Uh,
Governor Cheryl is on her way down and
she'll be here momentarily. Uh, so
please, uh, you know, uh, keep seated
and we'll be back out soon. Thank you.
Hope you're enjoying the the
conversation so far. Thanks.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Hey,
hey, hey.
>> [music]
>> Wow.
Wow.
Wow,
[music]
bound.
>> [music]
[music]
>> feel
about you.
>> [music]
>> Please welcome CAP's senior vice
president for energy and environment,
Trevor Higgins.
>> Hi everyone,
welcome back. Good morning. My name is
Trevor Higgins. I lead the energy and
environment department here at the
Center for American Progress. We're just
delighted to have you all here with us
today.
Um today, uh our next discussion is
called Making Life Affordable in New
Jersey and Beyond. And I am delighted to
say that we'll be joined by New Jersey
Governor Mikey Cheryl, who came into
office earlier this year with a clear
mandate from New Jersey voters to tackle
affordability and deliver results. Mikey
Cheryl is a wife, a mom, a former Navy
helicopter pilot, a federal prosecutor,
a congresswoman, and now the governor of
New Jersey. and she has focused her
administration on the question many
families across the country are asking
right now. Can government still make
life better for people? Can it solve
affordability challenges when they rear
their head? On day one, the governor
declared a state of emergency on utility
affordability and directed the state to
pursue rate relief and to build clean
energy and grid infrastructure faster.
At a moment when many Americans feel
frustrated with the current leadership
here in Washington DC and worried about
rising costs, governors and state
leaders are increasingly being asked to
show that government can still deliver
real results for people. What happens in
states like New Jersey shapes the
national conversation around
affordability, climate, and clean
energy, as we all know. In fact, CAP's
own recommendations for affordability
policy at the federal level, which we
just released yesterday for electricity
uh were inspired by Governor Cheryl's
leadership. So, I would like to thank
Governor Cheryl for her leadership and
for being with us here today. Um so the
key components of this plan include rate
relief that immediately provide uh for a
whole year in New Jersey a rate relief
uh stabilization as buys time for the
reforms to the utility business models
and to make investments in clean energy
and grid infrastructure that are needed
to fix this problem in the long term.
So, uh, I think we may be ready for
Governor Cheryl. Okay. Excellent. Please
join me and welcoming Governor Mikey
Cheryl. Thank you.
[music]
Well, good morning. Um, I'm not going to
make any news with my first statement.
Americans are struggling with their
bills. Inflation just grew at its
highest pace in three years and we're
facing an affordability crisis. Now, I
talk a lot about affordability because
in New Jersey, I hear a lot about
affordability. It was the centerpiece of
my campaign and certainly my north star
in the first 119 days of my
administration. Who's counting? Rising
energy prices are a critical driver of
the cost of living challenge. And since
2021, energy prices have tripled.
Electricity and gas prices are not just
outpacing inflation. It's the fastest
driver of inflation. And our grid is
ancient. The majority of our electricity
infrastructure was built in the 60s and
70s. And the majority of transmission
lines are over 25 years old. Every day
there is a growing demand for
electricity. In New Jersey, it's been
painful for residents and businesses.
Last June, utility rates jumped up by
20%.
The Trump administration has undoubtedly
not only set us back, but actively
aggravated the situation, killing solar
tax credits, killing offshore wind,
failing to support grid modernization,
an illegal war with Iran that spiked gas
prices.
But here's the hard truth that many in
our party don't want to admit. It's not
just Republicans. Many Democrats and
leadership positions have also failed
when it comes to energy policy. In my
own state, all the focus has been on
clean energy pledges without clear road
mapaps, single sources of renewable
energy development without
diversification or investment in our
existing infrastructure.
Battery storage initiatives left on the
shelf, bowing to the grid operator and
the utility companies that favor their
shareholders over people. And residents
have been left paying the price. not on
my watch. I ran for governor last year,
promising, just like I learned at the
Naval Academy, that I was going to find
a way or make one. I committed to
putting together an actionable roadmap,
bringing the best minds into my
administration, looking at what other
states were successfully doing and
relentlessly focusing on driving down
energy costs and making New Jersey an
energy arsenal. In New Jersey, it won't
surprise you. People tell you pretty
directly and clearly exactly what they
think. But I was surprised that the
loudest naysayers to my plan were
Democrats. Too many Democrats in
positions of power love to say no. It
can't be done. That will never work. I
don't think a governor can do that. That
narrow thinking, that lack of
imagination and boldness has helped get
us where we are today. Of course, there
are other factors, but I firmly believe
that it's up to government to provide
the solutions to our toughest
challenges. I'll tell everyone here, and
I think it's especially important to say
here in DC, we cannot be the party of
strongly worded letters. We can't settle
for tenure studies.
[applause]
Our problems are solvable. We just need
to get to work in actually solving them.
First, short-term, we need to provide
relief for rateayers and be unafraid to
challenge the status quo. We can't put
growing energy demand solely on the
backs of consumers. It requires standing
up to not just naysayers, but pushing
grid operators and utilities to do
better. medium-term, we need to use our
power, build out renewables like solar,
make existing technologies like natural
gas more efficient, invest in more
flexible grids, and pursue multi-state
efforts that leverage economies of scale
and our interconnected energy grid. And
long-term, we need to build the energy
sources of the future, nuclear to start.
How are we doing this in New Jersey?
Shortterm, I didn't wait even 20
minutes. During my inaugural address, I
signed an executive order freezing
utility rate hikes. I appointed
[applause]
I appointed New Jerseys first chief
operating officer and we build a
best-in-class energy team whose entire
portfolio is New Jerseyy's energy
future. And we're pushing our grid
operator PJM and utilities to put
reliability and affordability at the
forefront for our medium-term. My second
executive order, also signed during my
inaugural address, directed Trenton to
cut through permitting delays, resulting
in six new battery storage and solar
projects in my first two months.
[applause]
These projects had been languishing for
months, if not years. I'll continue to
rapidly deploy new projects. I directed
our board of public utilities to require
utilities to report on energy requests
from data centers. New Jersey is
coordinating with other states to hold
PJM accountable and leverage our power.
And the long term, this is important and
a key area we need to address. Good
government is good politics. For 50
years, New Jerseyy's had a moratorum on
the development of new nuclear power.
That's ridiculous. It's 44% of our
in-state generation and 80% of our clean
power generation. That moratorum was
written in the 70s with outdated
requirements that don't make sense in
this century. So, we got rid of it.
Nuclear opens the door for new largecale
base load electricity that we are going
to desperately need with growing energy
demands. But when I first mentioned
nuclear, I was told, why bother? you may
be out of office before it even comes
online.
That sort of short-term thinking is what
got us into this in the first place.
That's why we need to be bold and we
need to address AI and data centers.
That's exactly where the challenges are
coming right now. And I will tell you
that if we want to innovate into the
future in New Jersey, we've seen data
centers that power all of Manhattan and
the banks there. The back offices have
been in Jersey for about 15 years. We
know that we can power supercomputers
and AI development and innovate for
those jobs for our kids. But we're not
going to be able to do that effectively
if we don't make sure that bad actors
aren't usurping all of our resources
while leaving our communities to pay the
price. So that's why strong leadership
and a vision in our state is necessary.
We have got to ensure we're leading on
the future. That's what Democrats can do
here. We can make sure that our future
looks bright, not just for our
communities, but for the children that
we want to see getting the great jobs of
the future. And that's what I'm asking
of all Democrats to do right now. To
lead in this moment, to find a way or
make one. Thank you so much. [applause]
Joining Governor Cheryl on stage, please
welcome moderator Alicia Mendez of MS
Now.
[music]
They called in a New Jerseyian to do the
interview. Thank you so much. Um, I'm
hacking my way through those questions
based on your remarks. You know, you
talked about energy costs, the state of
emergency you declared on utility bills,
first day in office. Um, also an
emphasis on supply side. You talked
about the 50-year lifting the 50-year
moratorium on nuclear. I think what has
gotten less attention and it was what is
perhaps more interesting as other states
think about how to contend with this is
the way in which you've really gone
toe-to-toe with the regional grid
operators and I wonder if you can talk
about the role they play in rising
energy costs where you have found
success and what of that success you
think is replicable elsewhere.
This has been a really interesting area
and I can tell you um I like most people
in New Jersey could not have told you
what PJM was. Somebody said I don't know
what a PJM is. Um that is our regional
grid operator. It stands for
Pennsylvania, Jersey, and Maryland. Um
which came together and now represents
uh a lot of the eastern seabboard and as
far west as at least Illinois. Um and
they have been a really bad actor in
this. They've taken six years to get
power online. and they haven't planned
strategically very well for the future
and the board uh is largely made up of
oil and fossil fuel people who want to
put that kind of power in the grid. So
we've seen a lot of the um more uh
environmentally secure programs
languishing and sort of left on the
table and they just haven't been quick
to act. And this is actually an
interesting area where a lot of our
states uh are aligned with the White
House on some of what needs to be done
here. And PJM has continued and remains
a bad actor in the space. They're not
meeting the moment. So I've worked the
the way we found the best leverage is to
work with um other states and with the
courts. So for example, I said that our
power rates went up by 20% last year.
they were said to go up by another 20%
this year. Last year kind of broke the
bank of a lot of people, especially on a
fixed income. This year was going to
double it. Um, and so, uh, Governor
Shapiro had worked to put a price collar
on some of the rate increases. That
really had a huge impact on our ability
to keep costs lower and to keep, um,
them down for consumers. But, it's
really working with the other governors
in the region that are holding that's
holding PJM accountable. they are not
moving on their own to act in a better
way.
>> You talked a little bit in your remarks
about AI data centers. Um let's talk
about the factors that contributed to
high energy prices last summer. So there
was just a really hot summer that was
part of what was going on. There were
supply shortages, higher prices from the
regional grid operator, which we just
talked about. And then this growing
demand from AI data centers. Um, this
week you had more than 60 environmental,
labor, and community organizations
calling on you to impose a moratorum on
new data centers that use at least 20
megawatts of electricity until stronger
regulations are put in place. Do you
think a moratorum is the answer?
>> We have got to make sure that we are
balancing a lot of needs here. Um, I for
example represent the most densely
populated state in the nation, one of
the most environmentally sensitive
states in the nation. The sea rise for
New Jersey will impact New Jersey more
than any state in our nation. So, um, we
have to be incredibly thoughtful about
how we're using space and resources. We
also run the most high-end workforce in
the nation. We have more scientists and
engineers per square mile than anywhere
else. And we have always um innovated.
We you know from Thomas Jefferson or um
now I'm um blanking Edison. I wanted to
say Thomas Jefferson so my friend
Abigail Spanberger could like troll me
but
>> [laughter]
>> um I uh from Thomas Edison onwards uh we
have really represented the the most one
of the most innovative states in the
nation. We have to innovate for our
workforce. Those are the jobs our kids
are going to have and that's how we're
going to manage this transition. So with
that in mind, we are going to uh put out
our data center plan next week. We're
announcing it uh getting engaged in
demanding both that we have appropriate
use of um our resources that data
centers bring their own power. We've
seen costs go up in large part because
of Virginia under the last governor
really just added unmitigated data
centers and they're part of our grid and
so they drove price energy costs up
tremendously. Um, so we have had several
data centers come to some of our utility
operators saying, "Look, we want to hook
to the grid." And the utilities have
said, "No, we we don't have that power."
They've got to start bringing their own.
And they've got to do so in a
responsible way. We've also seen some
new resources where they can use
different cooling mechanisms, so they're
not using as much water. That's
something we're going to demand. And
we're also going to ensure that the
community is not negatively impacted by
this. So there are appropriate places to
build data centers. We're we're not
going to be a state that builds these
huge data farms like they do uh out west
or in in states with a lot of land. We
will you know we have about 80 data
centers and most people don't even know
that they exist because they're smaller
there in offices and they run like I
said the back offices for banks and
stuff like that.
>> We've talked about energy. I want to
make sure that we talk about housing
especially given that New Jersey has
such an incredible history um when it
comes to creating affordable housing.
So, for the non- New Jerseyians in the
room, 1975, a lot of working-class,
Latino, and black citizens along with
the local NAACP sue the town of Mount
Laurel, saying, "You're using your
zoning laws to discriminate, and that is
why we can't find affordable housing
here. Those advocates win at the New
Jersey Supreme Court. Um, the Mount
Laurel framework goes into effect. It is
then codified by your predecessor um
Governor Murphy and now other states
California, Massachusetts, Montana,
Texas, they're all looking at what we
have done in New Jersey as a model for
what is possible when it comes to zoning
and other things that are at the state's
discretion. when you talk to your
corollaries in those states, what is it
you tell them about what you can learn
from the success and failures we've had
in New Jersey?
>> So, it's really interesting you bring up
Mount Laurel because that is put us in a
better place than mo most uh states in
the area as far as continuing to build
out our housing stock, but it's not
enough. Um, so it was sort of necessary,
but not sufficient really. And uh what I
mean by that is in some areas of my
state in the last five years housing
prices have gone up by 60%. We are
hearing from young people who can't
afford homes. And in fact I was speaking
to one police officer who was telling me
that I got he said I've got some guys on
the force who are living with their moms
and I was making fun of them until I
realized oh there's just really no way
for them to afford to move out right now
and they're making a good salary. And we
hear that story again and again and
again. And um so what we need to do is
have a a sort of reinvigoration of how
we're going to build housing across New
Jersey. And we have to do it in a really
thoughtful way because as I mentioned,
we are the most densely populated and
environmentally sensitive. We can't
build on wetlands. Um we need to make
sure we're doing this in a thoughtful
way. But we also have a lot of
underutilized property especially
stateowned property property. And this
is why I just uh passed an executive
order because this is an area where as
governor I have a great deal of
authority on stateowned property so that
we can build out about 20,000 housing
units on property that especially
stateowned property especially like the
Department of Transportation. think
things like um underutilized parking
lots or other areas where an old
warehouse that nobody uses anymore. So,
we can actually repurpose that area,
which is right now some of the most
desirable area uh for people who want to
live in in transit oriented development
spaces. So, we're really excited about
this. It's going to be a good step.
There's a lot more we're going to do. I
mean in general I in in preparing for
this interview I was reading all of the
critiques of the first few months the
lauding of the first few months and my
overall sense was this on energy on
housing she is doing everything she can
possibly do and yet a lot of it requires
a long tale and short-term relief
remains the trickiest element of all of
these affordability questions and so I
wonder for you as you communicate with
voters about the fact that relief belief
is forthcoming,
but it may not be there today the way
that people want to feel it. How do you
bridge that gap?
>> It's really tough. Um, for a couple
reasons. So, for example, I froze
utility rates, but utility costs just
went up 20% last year. People don't just
want rates frozen, they want rates to go
down. Um, we just had an incredibly cold
winter with uh two epic snowstorms. Um,
one of them came in the weekend after I
got into office. So, with this in mind,
people aren't just satisfied with me,
you know, freezing rate hikes. So,
that's why we're expanding power. At the
same time, at every turn, the
president's driving up rates. So, when
you're talk whether you're talking
interest rates, uh, grocery prices
because of illegal tariffs, the gas
prices because of his illegal war. I
mean, here we are desperately trying to
drive down costs and at the same time he
continues to drive them up up to an
including now with like our health care
system. So, we got about a billion
dollar hit to our state budget this year
from um HR1. We anticipate it'll be
about a $5 billion hit next year. And
that's not even taking into account the
extra money we've had to spend for
counties to run programs that the
federal government had run and some and
we're continuing to see attack after
attack. So I think you know it's it's
communicating non-stop about what we're
doing and at the same time um driving
those costs down where we can. So,
community solar is a really good um way
in which we can actually immediately
drive down costs while talking about
nuclear and how we're looking to do that
in the long term. I think what people in
New Jersey want to understand is
somebody's handling this problem.
>> Somebody is taking this on. That's my
job. And so maybe they can sleep at
night because they know that I'm doing
every single thing I can to chart out
this future. And we've got a great plan
and we've got a great team. We've got
two minutes, but let's try to sneak in
the Gateway Tunnel Project. Of course,
uh, stalled [laughter] by the president.
You're welcome. Um, you have called the
Gateway Tunnel Project the nation's most
urgent infrastructure project. Tell me
why.
>> So, the Gateway Tunnel Project is the
largest pro program of national
significance that u we are running. It
is the Hudson, it's a new Hudson River
tunnel. The old one is over 100red years
old. It was damaged in supertorm Sandy.
And if you ever take have the pleasure
of taking this like glassbacked train to
see the rail goes from about six rail
lines to two, one in one out. So, uh
it's a it's a really strategic choke
point. It's a point of failure in our
system and it's becoming harder and
harder for people to commute and about
uh you know it could be worth too as
we're developing this out about 100,000
good jobs in the region. So illegally,
Trump cut off the money. So he just cut
off the money. It was not his money to
cut off. So people were telling me,
"Well, just give him what he wants." You
know, just end your DEI programs and
give him DHS funding or name Penn
Station after him. Why not? What do you
care? Just get it done.
And you know the problem is he just
finds what you want and then he
leverages and he never actually gives
you the money. So playing that game is
ineffective. So I said and we had to
work uh with New York on this as well. I
said look we got to get in court
immediately. People are getting pink
slips. I was talking to one guy whose
child's severely autistic. He's like I'm
not sure where this healthc care is
going to go right now. I'm really
scared. So this was something we had to
handle immediately. And that's what we
did. We got right in court and we beat
him. Uh he appealed. We beat him again.
We're now in court for damages because
he held us up. So that's the way to
fight this. I think a strong aggressive
move and making sure you can deliver.
Ladies and gentlemen, the governor of
the great state of New Jersey, Mikey
Cheryl.
Please welcome House Democratic Leader
Hakee Jeff of New York and founder and
chairman of the board of CAP, John
Podesta.
>> [music]
>> leader. Welcome back to the CAP ideas
conference.
>> Morning. Great to be here.
>> Yeah, it's tr a real honor for us to
have you here. Um I want to get into uh
what you have to live in and day in and
day out in the current Congress. But I
want to take us to a happier place to
begin with. It's January 3rd,
2027. You've just been sworn in as
speaker of the house.
[cheering]
>> See, there are they're happy already.
[laughter]
What uh what are the two or three big
things you're going to want to get done
for the American people when that
happens?
>> Well, thank you, John, uh for your
friendship and your leadership and uh to
Nerra, so appreciate you and to everyone
here and the CAP uh family. It's great
to be back. You know, I think our focus
and we're going to continue to
relentlessly make this clear over the
next few months in advance of taking
back control of the House of
Representatives. And then when we do uh
in the next Congress, we want to focus
on cost. We want to focus on care and we
want to focus on combating corruption.
But right at the top of that list uh is
the economy, lowering the high cost of
living, dealing with the fact that far
too many everyday Americans are
struggling to live paycheck to paycheck,
can't thrive, and can barely survive.
This in the wealthiest country in the
history of the world, and it's
unacceptable.
And the American people have been crying
out uh for this administration or this
Congress to do something about lowering
the high cost of living and they failed.
And you know we define those costs in a
variety of different you know issue
areas that we have to tackle. housing,
right? Gas, groceries, goods and
utilities
in terms of what needs to happen, you
know, related to the impact uh that this
environment is having on everyday
Americans. Related to that, of course,
is care and the cost of it, but also
making sure that that care is provided
in a high quality way. So clearly,
that's health care. We have a broken
health care system that Republicans have
decimated. unprecedented attack on the
health care of the American people and
all of the things that's on Medicaid, of
course, the largest cut to Medicaid in
American history, the attacks on
hospitals and nursing homes,
community-based health clinics, the
Affordable Care Act, vaccine
availability, the National Institute of
Health, the Centers for Disease Control,
the FDA, all of the things unprecedented
attack on the health care of the
American people. We got to fix our
broken health care system and make sure
that what we put in place uh is the best
ever. And then of course related to that
uh is child care on the front end and
elder care on the back end. And then we
certainly feel a responsibility to
tackle like the just the naked
corruption that we're seeing, but also
connected to the fact uh that because
Republicans are focused on enriching
themselves, their family members, and
their big donors, uh they're not focused
on solving the problems that the
American people want us to solve on
their behalf. But there's a related
issue, excuse me, that [clears throat]
we need to deal that we need to deal
with
and that is
dramatic reform to the fact that the
system is rigged against everyday
Americans to benefit, you know, the
elites. And that's going to require
massive campaign finance reform, massive
electoral reform, and yes, massive
Supreme Court reform as well. [applause]
>> I want to I want to I want to come back
to the court and I want in particularly
the Cala decision. Uh but I I noted uh
your current circumstances um and you're
having to live with a a in a house that
really is just on bended knee to the
president. Uh but you've been actually
been successful in peeling off
Republicans uh and passing uh by uh
using uh discharge petitions, the uh the
premium tax credits, uh the release of
the Epstein files, uh the stock trading
ban, for example, speaking of of uh
corruption, we just seen the stock
trades of the president uh coming out.
Uh
uh h how's that worked? How have you
gotten Republicans to come over? Is it
just the political pressure of their
constituents or and and is there any
hope that you can actually create some
bipartisan coalitions in the future?
>> Well, you know, we began um the Congress
understanding that we had two
responsibilities. One, we had to do
everything we can to push back against
the extremism that is being unleashed on
the American people, right? with
righteous intensity
to push back against this extremism
devastating everyday Americans
while at the same period of time
do as much as we can to govern in the
minority as if we were in the majority.
And in the House, there are only limited
tools available to accomplish that
objective. in the discharge petition
where you can get to 218 signatures on a
piece of legislation and over the
objection of the president and the
speaker force an up or down vote on the
floor of the House of Representatives.
We've now done that six different times.
And [applause]
that,
as far as we can tell, those six times
plus the two times that we did it in the
last Congress, eight is more in those
two congresses than at any other point
in the last 100 years in the House of
Representatives. And so, we've had them
on the run legislatively. And these have
been on interesting issues as you
indicated, John, in the aftermath of the
43-day government shutdown where we made
the issue, right? We just said seven
consecutive words over and over and over
again, cancel the cuts, or I guess it
was eight words, cancel the cuts, lower
the cost, save healthare,
and repeating, save healthcare, over and
over and over again. That was the fight.
And in the immediate aftermath of that
fight, the Republicans felt the pressure
of extending the Affordable Care Act tax
credits in the House on our terms. A
three-year straightforward extension, we
were able to do it on Epstein. And
you'll hear from Robert, you know,
Garcia and the oversight Dems have done
a great job of standing with the Epstein
survivors and pushing for transparency
and accountability. And ultimately, we
broke them on a discharge petition with
respect to Epstein. One of the things
that hasn't gotten a lot of attention is
that in November or early December last
year, uh we actually compelled 20
Republicans to join with us to override
one of Trump's first executive orders uh
that smashed his executive order,
collective bargaining rights for over a
million federal employees. We passed
legislation through a discharge petition
in the House to override uh that
executive order. And then of course,
most recently, we extended temporary
protectance status for Haitian migrants,
which was interesting because just two
years ago, these very same Republicans
were claiming that these Haitian
migrants were eating cats and dogs in
Springfield.
And two years later, we forced them to
join with us to extend temporary
protected status uh because it's the
right thing to do. So, I think what it's
demonstrated is that on issue after
issue after issue, when we're on the
right side of it, and when we're
disciplined and when we're focused and
when we put pressure in particular on
the so-called swing seat Republicans,
they have been breaking with us to do
the right thing for the American people.
>> Yeah, it's a little bit different than
old school. You you get a little bit, I
get a little bit. It's really pressure
and focus. Uh, and that can happen on
the affirmative agenda as well. you you
have anticipation that you that will
help actually move from ideas and and
control in the House to be able to get
stuff that actually gets signed, maybe
roll back the Medicaid cuts, uh get
those premium tax increases done. Uh
>> well, that's exactly right. And you know
what, I guess part of how we as House
Democrats view this moment, either MAGA
extremists are going to break the
country or we're going to break them.
And our goal is to break them. We will
defeat them. [applause] We have to beat
them electorally and then we have to
break their spirit because of the
extremism that's being unleashed on the
American people. That's completely and
totally unacceptable. And that's the
approach that we've taken with respect
to legislating on these discharge
petitions.
>> Yeah. Let me uh let speaking of
extremism, uh let's talk a little bit
about redistricting. Uh Trump started
this off tried to urge all the uh MAGA
state legislatures, state legislative
bodies uh to redistrict in in the middle
of term. Democrats have fought back uh
in California. We lost that Supreme
Court case in Virginia. Uh try to uh
really uh push back, but I think we've
now created a cycle uh that the American
people must sit back and and wonder
about. Added to that is this Cala
decision which gutted the voting rights
act. Uh they had done a lot already to
weaken the voting rights act. Uh
endorsed extreme partisan redistricting.
Uh but uh going forward what's the
strategy uh to get a level playing field
for in the in the elections?
>> Yeah. Well, because of um you know, the
Republican gerrymandering scheme had
been a complete and total failure with
Democrats fighting back aggressively
until they were aided and embedded by
the Cala decision and an egregious
decision by the Virginia Supreme Court
4-3 decision, partisan decision,
completely unacceptable to overturn the
will of more than 3 million Virginia
voters. Now, we're still going to win
two seats minimum in Virginia, and then
we're going to work as hard as we can in
advance of 2028 to restore that 10-1 map
because that's what the voters uh
decided would be appropriate moving
forward. Now, notwithstanding, you know,
the Cala decision and what happened in
Virginia, you know, our assessment is
that the Republicans may have netted
when it's all said and done in terms of
what's happening in the South right now,
maybe three or four seats in this
environment, which means that they will
go perhaps from plus three, which is
where we started, narrowest majority
that any party has had in the Congress
since 1930, the Great Depression, uh to
maybe plus six or plus seven. Keep in
mind when we won the House back in 2018,
and we're in a 2018 type of environment
right now, as poll after poll, private
and public continue to show, if not
better, uh we needed to flip 24 seats,
John, as you recall, with the help of
many of the people in this room and
people all across the country, we
flipped 40. 31 of those seats were in
districts that Donald Trump had just
won. And so we only need to flip a
fraction of those, even given all of the
gerrymandering that they've done, aided
and embedded by these two Supreme Court
decisions, we only need to flip a
fraction of those uh in order to take
back control of the House. And I can
tell you right now, as a guarantee, we
are taking back control of the United
States House of Representatives in
November. [applause]
But then our work is not done. Um,
Republicans had a structural advantage
which is why they launched this
gerrymandering scheme because so many of
our states had commissions built into
the law or constitutional impediment to
being able to redraw districts in this
cycle that have to be unwound. And in
most state legislatures,
California was an exception. Uh it takes
two consecutively elected legislative
bodies before you can bring something
before the voters or do it uh in the
state legislature. uh which means that
in states like New York and New Jersey
and Washington and Colorado and we'll
add on top of that Oregon, Illinois,
and Maryland will have at least seven
states that we believe we need to
respond
in advance of 2028
uh to what they are doing in the deep
south to wipe out any structural
advantage that they're trying to get
themselves in advance of 2028. And we'll
have some opportunities uh in
legislative bodies across the country
where we're only one or two seats short
of a trifecta
uh to be able to explore uh what can be
done. And we still have pending um
litigation in Wisconsin where we're
waiting on the Wisconsin Supreme Court
uh to act. And so we look at this as a
two-step process, right? We'll finish
the job in 2026. will take back the
house and then we've got uh to make sure
in these states all across the country
where we'll have a renewed opportunity
to respond because you'll have two
consecutively elected legislators and in
many of these places like New York
they'll act in the first instance this
year and then come back in January early
next year they'll act again and then
we'll have new maps in these states all
across the country uh to wipe away any
advantage that they may try to gain. by
going into further states in the deep
south.
>> Uh in the past, uh Democrats, not so
much in the House, but in the White
House and in the uh and in the Senate
have been criticized for not focusing as
much on judges and the Supreme Court in
particular as the Republicans done. Uh
is there anything we can do about that
at this stage? Do you anticipate uh
trying to uh find a way to uh either
through term limits or other ways to
reform the court which has been just so
partisan lowers its standing with the
American people?
>> Yeah. In my view, listen, all options
are on the table. Uh and you know, that
effort will be led, you know, by Jamie
Rascin. No finer constitutional scholar
you'll find in this country. uh who will
be the chair of the judiciary committee
uh and the Democrats on the judiciary
committee as it relates to what needs to
be done to ensure that we don't have you
know
we don't have a Supreme Court that in
far too many instances they're operating
like partisan political hacks right
trying to advance [applause]
the interests of the Republican party
and by the way we should take a step
back and Eric Holder had an op-ed today
where he laid out several of the things
that I think need to be on the table in
terms of Supreme Court reform. Uh but
perhaps the original
most recent sin from this Supreme Court
was granting
this president blanket immunity which
has given him the ability to operate
with impunity unleashing corruption that
we've never seen in the history of the
country. I mean, Donald Trump makes
Richard Nixon look like a choir boy.
It's outrageous and it's hurting the
American people. And we're seeing it
with the billion dollar ballroom now.
We're seeing it with the multi-billion
dollar slush fund for violent
insurrectionists who brutally beat
police officers. And we're seeing it
with the more recent disclosures of the
stock trading ban. And when we talk
about cleaning up corruption, we want to
do it across the board. our own
institution, the Supreme Court, which
needs an ethical code of conduct imposed
upon them. And of course, you know, the
White House, which is a Trump cartel, an
organized crime entity that is unfolding
in 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue. There's no
other way to say it, and the American
people know it. And we can start uh by
prohibiting the ability for members of
Congress, for the president and the vice
president, and for Supreme Court
justices to trade stocks. Great. We're
we're we're out of time, but I just I
want to give you a one shot at uh Robert
Garcia is going to be here uh later. Uh
but there's kind of a free fire zone out
there on oversight going into a new
Congress. Uh what are the priorities?
And I think maybe you just laid them out
on the corruption side. There's the war
uh in Iran. There's uh the bad policy
decisions. Uh how do you organize the
House to actually tell a story of the
American people? Well, I you know, I
think our our fundamental premise is
that taxpayer dollars should be used to
make life more affordable for the
American people, to improve their
quality of life, not to unleash
masked untrained ICE agents to brutalize
or kill American citizens as we
horrifically saw. Not to fund a reckless
and costly war of choice that has
increased, you know, gas prices on the
American people. And certainly we
shouldn't see taxpayer dollars used, you
know, to subsidize the lifestyles of the
rich and shameless who are connected to
Donald Trump, right, as part of a
friends and family plan that he is
unleashed on the American people in real
time, hiding in plain sight. And so I
think in terms of our oversight
responsibilities and this corruption
piece, I think it's the American people
intrinsically believe the system is
broken, it's rigged, and it's corrupt.
What we have to do is connect that
corruption to the fact that things
aren't happening here in Washington that
they want to see happen, right?
Particularly driving down the high cost
of living. And the thing I'll say about
this, John, is in terms of listen, our
oversight effort, it's not a Democratic
playbook. It's not a partisan playbook.
It's the James Madison playbook. Like it
was Madison who said Congress at its
best should be a rival to the executive
branch. He said it and there were no
political parties. It was the American
thing to do. And of course, that's not
what this Congress, you know, has done.
They've just been a reckless rubber
stamp for Donald Trump's extreme agenda.
And I found it fascinating when King
Charles came and spoke crisp 20-minut
speech that he gave uh to the Congress.
And one perhaps the most memorable part
is when he referenced the Magna Carta
and talked about the Magna Carta as the
foundation for the principle that
executive power is subject to checks and
balances.
And every single Democrat immediately
got up and gave him a standing ovation.
And then I looked over to the other side
of the aisle and much to my surprise, I
saw Republicans standing up and giving
him an ovation. And I'm thinking to
myself, don't they know King Charles is
talking about them right now?
But checks and balances, that's an
American thing. It's not a partisan
thing. It's a Madisonian thing. It's
it's the framer's vision for what the
Article One first amongst equals branch
of government should be. And so while we
have a responsibility to drive down the
high cost of living and focus on the
affordability agenda, we also believe uh
that there's an accountability agenda
that the American people uh will expect
rightfully for a separate and co-equal
branch of government to pursue, you
know, and led by Robert Garcia, who do a
great job. The oversight Democrats have
already done a great job. If you think
about it, in the minority, in the
minority, Christy Gnome is gone. We ran
her out of town
and Pam Bondi is gone. [applause]
And if I have anything to do with it,
Pete Hexf will be next. Pete Hexf will
be next. [applause]
Um, we've got to maybe get to one or two
questions from the audience that have
been uh submitted, but uh one that's
important, which is uh and I'll just
read the question, which is that polls
show American people don't trust
government institutions anymore. I think
that's particularly true of young
people. How do you restore that sense of
of uh
support, faith that things can get
better, that government can be on your
side?
>> Yeah. No, it's incredibly important and
we have to deliver, right? We we're
going to make
a series of promises as part of our
affirmative agenda
to the American people and then we got
to work as hard as we can to bring those
promises to life in ways that tangibly,
you know, will improve their quality of
life. And young people are facing a very
uncertain environment. It was the case
prior to the rise of AI. Now with AI, it
even adds further uh to that
uncertainty. And we got to run straight
into that uncertainty and make sure that
this generation doesn't become the first
one where you can't clearly see a better
quality of life for them uh as compared
to the generations upon whose shoulders
they stand. You know, I have the honor
of serving
in a district that was once represented
by Shirley Chisum. And Shirley Chisum,
the great Shirley Chisum, she once said
to some young folks who were thinking
about running for office, if you run for
office, don't be a career politician, be
a states person. And I said, what's the
difference? And she said, well, a career
politician is only concerned with the
next election. But a states person cares
about the next generation, and we've got
to make sure that we deliver for this
generation of young people and future
generations to come.
We say it, we feel it, but we have to
mean it in terms of the actions that
actually occur to bring that to life.
Um, and I think, you know, that's the
responsibility that we all shoulder. Uh,
we know it's a heavy responsibility. Uh,
but we plan on delivering like the
Democratic Party going all the way back
to FDR
has. We've done it before. We've done it
before. You're talking about Social
Security and rural electrification and
the GI Bill and Medicare and Medicaid
and Head Start and the Civil Rights Act
and the Voting Rights Act and the Fair
Housing Act and the Children's Health
Insurance Program and the Affordable
Care Act and the Inflation Reduction Act
and all the things that were
accomplished in the last administration.
Every single one of those things brought
to you by your friendly neighborhood
Democratic party. That's a pretty good
track record of success to stand upon.
And we've got to build upon that to
continue to deliver for the future.
>> I told you I was going to ask you uh
who's your hero in politics or in life
and then we're going to get out of here.
>> You could pick which one.
>> Yeah. Well, I I thought you were going
to actually ask me. Am I picking the
Knicks in five or in six?
>> Oh, I want to say one of
>> But um
>> is there a is there a question there?
>> Yes. But [laughter]
but I will you know I will say
>> I figured the answer to that was
obvious. Well, they that's right. Um I I
I think you know there's so many legends
that I've had the opportunity to serve
with in this Congress. Of course, Nancy
Pelosi and Stenny and you know Jim
Klyurn, but we all feel like a
particular sense of pride and honor to
have served with John Lewis. And he was
a real American hero.
[applause]
And you know, I'll never forget that
when I was on the floor as a as a new
member of Congress, my first or second
day,
saw John Lewis called me over and he
asked me a question. He said, "Are you
the new guy?"
And I said, "Yes, sir, Mr. Lewis, that's
me."
He said, "Haim, you're a colleague of
mine right now. You don't have to call
me Mr. Lewis. You can call me John.
I said, "Yes, sir. Mr. Lewis, I
understand."
Then he asked whether I was from
Brooklyn. He thought I said, "Yes." Um,
he said, "Well, you know, I I hear some
good things about your class, yourself,
and I came in, there was 52 other 51 52
other Democrats, some great Democrats,
but Washington DC can be a a tough
place.
So, young man, I don't want you to get
into any trouble
unless it's good trouble.
And he lived a life of good trouble. And
he showed such character and courage and
conviction and belief in America, the
good of America, even when confronting
the ugly underbelly of America. And we
certainly are called upon to summon that
that type of courage and character and
conviction to get us through the storm
which we will get through this storm and
make sure that we come out stronger as a
country on the other side of it. John
Lewis.
>> Thank you, Mr. Jeff.
>> Thank you all.
>> Thank you, leader. [applause]
[music]
Heat.
Heat. [music]
[music]
Please welcome Representative Robert
Garcia of California, Minneapolis Mayor
Jacob Fry, and MS Now's Ari Melbour as
moderator.
>> [music]
>> Hello. Good day, everyone. How's
everybody doing?
>> Good. We got a great panel. We got a lot
of energy. Uh we have two leaders, both
uh state and federal. Um and we're going
to talk about what we're up against as a
country from a civic perspective, from a
nonpartisan perspective, uh and thinking
about what works because we have got a
lot of experience up here. So,
gentlemen, thanks for being here. Uh,
I'm going to dispense with a long
introduction. We got a very informed
audience uh and and go right to you,
Congressman. We have these reports now
of a giant billion dollar plus fund uh
that the the president wants to take
from the American taxpayer and give to
allies, partisan warriors, political
criminals, and convicts potentially. Um,
so your view of this thug fund, is it
corrupt? Is it legal? What would you do
about it?
>> Well, a couple things. I mean, one, I
think just to set the stage, we should
be very clear that this is the most
corrupt president and the most corrupt
administration in the history of our
country. Period. And not only not only
is he enriching himself, he's enriching
his family, he's enriching his allies,
he's enriching those that he believes
will be beneficial to him. And so this
this one fund, it also may end up being
the single most corrupt thing he has
actually done up until this point. This
is on top of all of the real estate
deals, the grift, selling access to the
White House, the crypto schemes, the way
that uh he's doing foreign policy, but
also enriching the Trump Organization,
the billion dollar slush funds to Jared
Kushner, and the list goes on and on.
And the idea, what I've told folks, and
we're just chatting about this, is he is
literally
stealing the hard-earned labor and funds
of the American people and directly
funneling it back to himself and to his
allies. And so when we get, of course,
our work is to get into the Congress
with the majority in November.
But right now and in the future, we've
got to focus as we think about what
happens next. It can't just be a
forward-looking agenda, which we have to
have. There also has to be
accountability. We also have to be able
to tell people that what's happening
right now is wrong and our kids and
grandkids and future students cannot
just pass this moment by and think that
this was okay. And so prior from a
priority perspective, the oversight
committee, judiciary, others are
absolutely on this. We're going to we're
going to demand hearings, demand
accountability, and push back whenever
we can.
>> Yeah. I'm curious how that fits into the
upcoming election. And so when we look
at a country that lived through the
effort to steal and overthrow an
election with violence, it's the biggest
stain on our modern history. And there
was the accountability. You mentioned
the probe into January 6th by the DOJ
was actually the largest federal probe
in American history, but then wiped away
on the first day of this term with all
of the pardons and now a fund for it.
And so before we turn to the local uh
push back that's been so effective
there, I did want to ask you, how do you
look at the future elections when you
have people who credibly say, "Well, if
you're pardoned, you could probably get
pardoned again. Now you're going to be
funded if this isn't stopped in court."
Why should people have confidence in
these future elections, midterms, but
especially the presidential if there is
a legal and now financial mechanism to
support what could be another
insurrection?
I I think that is why the accountability
piece and leaders and all of us and
Congress and whoever the nominee is on
our side have to be very cleareyed about
what is happening right now is corrupt,
is wrong, and there has to actually be
accountability, criminal prosecutions
and hearings that happen in DC and
across this country because we cannot
just allow the moment to go on and
somehow normalize what's happening. And
I think one of the issues that we're
going to have as a party is this idea
that yes, we have to focus on
affordability. That's what the American
public want. We have to focus on fixing
healthcare. That's a critical concern.
But a key part of our agenda has to be
the party of fighting corruption of
taking on corporate and power of the
executive and in DC and ensure that
people understand that what's happening
now cannot is not acceptable and can't
happen again. Uh, Mayor Fry, what
happened in Minnesota and what worked
from your perspective?
>> Well, Ari, I'm going to give the segue
for you because to the extent there's
this thug fund, uh, a whole lot of thugs
came to Minneapolis in the form of ICE
and Border Patrol. They terrorized our
communities. It resulted in $23 million
worth of damage in January alone. So, if
there's a billion dollar fund, ISha
could come back to the people of
Minneapolis.
[applause]
We're gathered here at a time where
what's been in the news now is the war,
the economy for folks following
politics, primaries today, but for a
period, the nation's eyes were on
Minnesota. You were thrust in that
position not because you got on a
committee or wanted to to fight that
fight, but because of what came to your
to your town. and then your citizens uh
stood up so bravely. What did you learn
from that? What are the lessons there
for other places when this comes up?
>> The goal here was not just to have ICE
and Border Patrol leave Minneapolis and
go to terrorize some other city. The
goal, and every single person felt it
deeply, to stop ICE and Border Patrol in
their tracks, to stand up for the
endurance of our republic, to be
patriots. And we saw that by the tens of
thousands of people that were peacefully
protesting in the street and dropping
off groceries to those that were
terrified to go outside. Uh and look, we
have learned lessons not just through
Operation Metro Surge, but you know,
we've been through other crises in the
aftermath following the murder of George
Floyd. Uh and during these crisis, it's
not like we just sat on our hands. It's
not like we didn't think of ways that we
can improve. We did. Uh there was
organic organization that happened in
our communities. Neighborhood
associations were already stood up, but
people also set up mutual aid funds that
were able to go out to people that
needed them most. Our city had a task
force where we could quickly disseminate
communication to people on the street
and we were able to get information back
from them again with the goal of just
keeping people safe in the city. Uh, and
then finally, you know, I think that
people need to have the guts to stand up
against a federal administration that is
doing everything possible to bring down
this republic as we know it. Uh, this
again was not about immigration. It sure
as hell was not about safety. uh this
was about going after a
democraticallyrun city in a
democraticallyrun state and trying to
show that we're about chaos when it was
exactly the opposite. They created that
chaos. They created that danger on our
street and we were doing everything
possible to prevent that from happening.
>> I think that's right. And let me just
first say and I I was telling the mayor,
I don't know that there's been a mayor
in the country that has been tested more
uh than this mayor and what happened in
Minneapolis. Not just what happened with
this last with the ICE with what
happened with ICE and DHS, but what
happened with George Floyd and so much
and so I think that cities and mayors as
a former as a former mayor myself are
are leading the way that will forever be
your most distinguished title by the
way.
>> Absolutely.
>> Absolutely. Um, and I think look, I
think what happened in Minneapolis when
we're why it's so important is the
response from the community and the
American people is actually what began
in motion why Christian Noom is no
longer the secretary at DHS. And so even
when you have complete control of
government by a party and MAGA and
what's happening right now, when there
is public backlash, when there is a push
back from from the people, you can
actually get change. And I think what
what the what what the former secretary
I think doesn't understand is she may be
out of office, but back to the point of
accountability,
>> right? if she was doing paytoplay with
Cory Luendowski or if they were selling
contracts or if they were uh involved in
corruption, just because she's out of
office doesn't mean she still does not
to be h held accountable for whatever
she may have done while she was in
office.
>> And so we can't we can't allow just
because a Pam Bondi or a Christian are
now gone as they should be. There has to
be the push from the public and the
accountability on on the other side.
>> That's right. There has to be
accountability at the top. There also
has to be accountability for the people
that
killed Renee Good, killed Alex Prey, uh,
shot Julio Serelis. Um, I mean, just a
couple of days ago, there was an
announcement by our local Henipin County
attorney uh that there were in fact
going to be charges of this really
horrific shooting that does not get as
much attention as that of Renee Good and
Alex Prey, but was arguably one of the
worst. Um, we have people,
United States citizens or residents that
were doing nothing wrong.
Uh, it looks like that they were shot
from behind. A bullet almost hit a
little kid. They were then torn apart
from their families while you had this
federal administration and ICE agents
that were lying about what took place.
They were trying to create this
narrative that they were attacked, that
both Julio Sosa was trying to kill them,
that the local residents were beating
them up with shovels. All of it was a
flatout lie. And I think one of the most
important things that we also learned
here, uh, and mayor, you learned this
very directly as well, serving a
municipality, is that you also got to
focus on the how. Far too often at the
national level, we're focused on these
policy items, these these, you know, the
this this really kind of geeky stuff
that your average American doesn't pay
attention to. You know what your average
American hates, though, whether they're
Democrat or Republican? They hate seeing
a pregnant woman get dragged through the
snow. They hate seeing a six-year-old
get separated from their family. Why do
they hate that? Because they imagine
their mom or their wife or themselves
being pregnant, getting dragged. What is
that like? Well, I'll tell you that
sucks. Whether you're a Democrat or
Republican, it doesn't matter. This is
not an ideological thing. This is a
human being thing. And to the extent we
all can explain what took place in
Minneapolis, by the way, it was way
worse than what you saw on the news. It
was a full-on invasion. We need to be
spreading that message, stop it in its
tracks. And we all need to be, you know,
I've heard from some mayors and some uh
uh
business people, whatever that, hey, we
got to keep our head down. Otherwise,
we'll attract, you know, the eye of
Sauron. Um, no man, you can't keep your
head down. You got to speak up. You
speak out. Otherwise, you're going to be
the one that's next. [applause]
And Congressman,
when you hear that and you look at the
changes, you mentioned the changes in
leadership, but we've also seen um
Steven Miller, according to reporting,
taking more of a backseat in the White
House. Donald Trump uh is nothing if not
a PR reality show communicator. Well,
he's communicated a lot less about
immigration in the last several months.
How do you view what what started in in
Minnesota and what the Congress is doing
as affecting that in real time? Because
to the mayor's point, sometimes
Democrats are the party of the 10-year
plan and they're saying, "Well, when
they get elected and then they do this
and then the budget's going to be there
and then they're going to offset it over
here." And that's cool, but the mayor's
referring to re to direct action and
movements that may have actually changed
some of immigration policy now, even
before an election. Your your thoughts
on that? Look, I I think that we have to
look and this is also speaking as like
uh a progressive uh an immigrant myself.
I came to this country when I was a
young kid. I would not become a US
citizen to my early 20s. I know what
it's like to be in a college classroom.
Look around and not know if you're going
to be actually want end up getting a job
or not. And so the experience that
immigrants go through is real. We have
to understand those. But at the same
time, we've we lost the plot over the
last 10 years. immigrants,
progressives, the average person,
they also want a strong and secure
border. We we can have immigration
reform, a pathway to citizenship, common
sense, law enforcement relationships,
and also humanity to teach people that
the that folks are coming here because
they are scared, they're starving, and
they're desperate because their family,
they want to take care of their family.
And those same people when you give them
a chance and opportunity to work, they
also they're we're all reasonable. They
understand that you know what, we should
have a secure border with a safe asylum
system and making sure that folks have
access to good immigration attorney that
entire we can have that conversation and
center and humanize the people that are
suffering that are coming across to this
country because we should be a beacon
and such a great place that we should
want the world to look at us as a place
where they want to be. I think that's a
that's a good thing. And I think as as
Democrats and progressive, we've got to
reenter this immigration debate and use
the example of what's happening in our
cities who are actually putting in place
common sense solutions to actually put
together a good a good policy. Look,
Donald Trump right now is underwater on
immigration.
His his top issue the American public
has turned on. He has turned ICE into
his own essentially federal police
force. He couldn't get police chiefs to
do it. So he turns to ICE, increases our
budget 10fold, makes them larger than
most militaries in the world. And if we
think if we think he's has stopped using
them, get we got to get our head out of
the sand. There are there are real
opportunities for him to try to use ICE
and his power over ICE
at election centers come come November.
And so we've got to be very smart that
the public right now is with us. And at
the right opportunity, we got to retake
this idea that somehow immigrants are
some other thing and are not patriotic.
Immigrants are some of the most
patriotic people in this country. And
and if we want to talk about what
patriotism means, real patriotism is
actually not screaming and yelling, uh,
just think about me and America first.
Real patriotism is actually taking care
of the people in our country.
Compassion, kindness, being neighborly.
And I think that's as as Democrats,
we've got to take that argument back.
>> Mayor.
>> Yeah. And ICE is not just the federal
police force that he's developed. It is
his. And there's a historical analog
here, which is the SS. Uh the SS was
unaccountable to the parliament. They
answered only to Hitler. uh ICE also
once they get the funding and have these
massive increases to the extent that
it's larger than the FBI
uh they largely don't need approvals
from the congressional body. It is very
much Donald Trump's force. Uh and
similar to the SS, it is used in our
streets to terrorize people extensively.
They use the Department of Justice and
weaponize it against local elected
officials. And my great concern of
course is in this coming election how
that same ICE force is going to be used
to try to prevent people
congressmen that look like you candidly
from voting.
How they're going to prevent United
States citizens from voting by for
instance placing ICE agents at or very
near to a polling location.
Uh and that kind of action is not just
terrifying.
uh it could upset this very American
experiment that we all hold dear. Uh and
so it is important that we continue this
political drum beat because again
they left Minneapolis not because you
know job well done they accomplished
some sort of safety mechanism. They left
Minneapolis because it was a disaster
for them politically.
They left Minneapolis because the
narrative that was created was such an
epic failure.
uh that they had to change gears and we
need to make sure that the American
people understand that failure so it
can't be replicated again and we have
free and fair elections especially this
one coming up in November.
>> I'm going to I want to just cuz we have
such limited time I want to ask you if
if the Democrats take back the midterms
which a lot of estimates say if it were
held today they probably would uh your
colleague and leader Jeffrey spoke about
that moments ago.
When you look at accountability, does it
include a multi-pronged impeachment to
have a line in the sand? Because the
president was first impeached for asking
another country to investigate a
political opponent. It seems like such a
long time ago, but that was the Ukraine
plot. Would another country announce a
Biden investigation? Now he's abusing
government powers to do that against
multiple Democrats, including potential
rivals to the Republican party in 28 in
this country. So by any legal measure
that's worse. The other impeachment of
course was about the insurrection we
discussed at the time. The president
said publicly violence was bad. He
didn't see that coming and that it just
and they said look at the speech. It was
peaceful. Since that time he's used his
powers, many say abused his powers to
free the violent convicts, the
seditionists. And we discussed that
earlier. So by those two precedents
which are from your Congress, you would
have two grounds of impeachment there
plus the corruption plus other
questions. So as the oversight leader,
you know, key oversight leader, should
people be looking at their midterm vote
as one for potential impeachment or you
don't go that far? I I think first
obviously everything's got to be on the
table. You can't take it off the table.
The the reality is we have be have to be
honest that Trump does an impeachable
offense every week. And so we could
spend an enormous amount of time going
through that process or we can try to do
everything we can to stop and slow the
Trump agenda. And so while you cannot
take impeachment off the table, I think
we've got to give people a stronger
reason to vote for in November. And it's
got to be motivated off the fact that
we're going to hold we're going to have
accountability, bring the truth out, but
also try to make their lives better by
focus you on that. We have a politically
sophisticated room here. Is that because
you've come, your party has come to the
view that messaging impeachment just
doesn't help you get votes?
>> I think that spending all of our time on
impeaching a president that is not going
to get impeached. It's happened already
two other times is not the best use of
to consume all the energy that Democrats
are.
>> And Mr. Mayor, do you agree given where
you're at? Do you agree with that or you
would put it differently?
>> No, I think the congressman is
understanding this accurately. as he
said, they're compete they're making
these impeach impeach impeachable
offenses virtually every week. And the
other point here is
>> and I I'll let you finish, but
>> that's not the greatest legal argument
because if somebody's gang banging every
week or stealing every week and you go,
"Well, this gang keeps stealing."
>> It's not it's not. But the
>> you know, so go ahead. But but but how
do you speak to that logically?
>> I mean, I here's how I speak to it. The
opposite of Donald Trump extremism is
not the opposite extreme. The opposite
of Donald Trump extremism is good,
thoughtful governance where you're
loving your country more than your
ideology and you're not just taking
whatever it is that Donald Trump does
and you know having a leftist tint on
it. We have a greater obligation to than
to that exclusively of our party. We
have an obligation to maintain and
uphold this great democracy. We have an
obligation, as the congressman
mentioned, to actually do things that
help people. And if you're spending all
your time spinning your wheels trying to
counter Donald Trump, you're not
actually helping anyone. We got to we
got to not just counter Donald Trump,
it's going on offense. And of course,
it's also not off the table to be very
clear. I mean, we we should be clear.
It's not off the table, but we have to
have a broader agenda and message, I
think. And right now, just putting all
of our energy on impeachment, we should
be impeaching the guy every single week.
>> Was it Was it a pretty good answer for
you guys? It
>> is. [applause]
>> We don't go full Jeet Bush and say,
"Please clap." I was just curious how
you felt if you remember. Does anyone
remember? Please clap. Never a good
sign. Um,
we have a submitted question. So, I want
to read this out and then we're going to
end. I want to end with a lightning
round, which is the fast answers. But,
uh, this is for the mayor. What do you
think Congress should do to prevent what
happened in Minneapolis and other
cities? What should the next president
do? Obviously that would depend on
policy but you specifically already said
today you don't you don't look at it as
oh nimi hey hey stop leaving you know
stop with my city and who cares about
the rest and a lot of democratic local
leaders have sort of linked arms. So
what can other cities do either to
prevent it from happening or if they're
greeted with it? The first part of the
answer is going to be really boring
which is make sure you do an emergency
management training. Uh we ran extensive
national incident manage system
training. Uh we had a full understanding
of uh we ran simulations, practices all
culminating in a trip out to Emittsburg,
Maryland, not too far from here to make
sure that we were prepared no matter
what went down. To the mayors out there,
strongly recommend uh doing so. uh and
to the people uh of America. Um I
mentioned focusing on the how as opposed
to sanctuary city policy or separation
ordinance. Uh you want to focus on what
you are not okay with not just as
Democrats but as American people. What
are the values that we hold dear that
we're not going to abandon? Uh and again
standing up for your neighbor. One of
the most important pieces I thought was
this sentiment that we weren't just
standing up for immigrants. These were
like our neighbors. You know, you don't
look at these people as immigrants in
Minneapolis. They're like your banker.
You know, they're your insurance agent.
They're my babysitter, my security
detail. You know, people that you meet
when you're walking down the street.
These are the people of our city that
have made our Minneapolis a better
place. And not just Minneapolis, Long
Beach, New York City, you name it. Uh,
and I think that we have a great
opportunity to take this narrative,
which is the truth that came out of
Minneapolis and this great neighboring,
which can in fact be a verb, take it
nationwide.
Uh I want to get in another another
topic while we're here and I don't know
that it's been hit a lot today which is
Congressman the work that uh has
happened in Congress on accountability
for Epstein survivors and victims and
transparency across multiple
administrations. As someone who covers
Congress and the news
strangely
it has become one of the most bipartisan
exceptions of any topic in this era. It
didn't start that way. And that doesn't
include Donald Trump, but I said
Congress,
you found with your colleagues and with
Connor, with Massie, who's up for an
election today that uh involves taking a
risk for this issue, you found
bipartisan veto proof supermajorities.
So given that I think everyone here
knows a lot about the history of the
epic, I wanted to actually have you tell
us about that part in addition to
whatever else you want to share that
something that Roana started and others
that's looked like a long shot became
veto proof. I'm not aware of any other
major domestic issue that's overridden
Donald Trump's opposition to this
Republican Congress saying don't do it
then they don't do it. So can you walk
us through that? And then to sound
naive, could you fashion that coalition
for anything else?
>> Yeah. So I I agree with uh um as far as
it being bipartisan in the Congress and
also bipartisan in the country. So I go
out and talk to folks Republican,
Democrat, not affiliated. The the
average person knows what's going on.
The Epstein investigation has broken
through in a way that other issues have
not. And so the folks at the barber
shop, folks at the supermarket, when
they stop me, they're asking me about
the Jeffrey Epson investigation. And
people have watched are following this
uh on late night TV, on Saturday Night
Live, on their favorite podcast. So it
has broken through. Look, what what
happened and I think it all and it
started in a bipartisan way in in the
committee in in oversight. If we all
remember, you go back six months ago,
seven months ago, you started seeing all
these emails coming out the Yeah.
between maybe the president Galain, you
saw the photos coming out from Mara Lago
and other places, the videos of Epstein
Island. All of that information that
started coming out before the release of
the DOJ files was because Democrats on
the oversight committee forced
Republicans to vote on a bunch of
subpoenas. The Epstein estate, different
documents, getting folks to come in and
testify. We were able, by the way, to
peel off one or two Republicans on all
of those votes. Nancy Mace, uh, Anna
Paulina Luna, uh, Lauren Boowberg, and
by peeling those votes, Margie Taylor
Green, we were able to then build this
kind of, I think, uh, pathway to getting
the the law passed, which eventually we
got done in the Congress, the super in
its way with the supermajority. But even
getting all of those initial documents
and videos was bipartisan. And so I
absolutely think that there's a
bipartisan effort and interest to get to
the truth on the Epstein investigation.
It's not a majority of Republicans, but
there are some, especially some of the
more independent women, uh, that
continue to fight for the survivors. And
look, on Epstein, I'll say this, he ran
the single largest modern sex
trafficking ring. It impacts all levels
of government. We shouldn't care who is
implicated, whether they're Republicans
or Democrats. These are powerful people.
They're deser the survivors deserve
justice and oversight is going to
continue to stay on this until we get
justice because the American public want
the survivors to be able to have their
their justice and that's I think what's
going to launch us into the next phase.
>> Appreciate that and wanted wanted to get
your update on that. As we wrap up this
panel, a lot more fun stuff to come. We
do a lightning round which is very hard
for politicians. Doesn't matter what
party. This is finish the sentence in a
sentence, not two sentences. and you
both get a shot. We'll do a couple and
then we're out. Um, mayor, starting with
you. If Democrats underperform in the
midterms, it will be because
>> one sentence.
>> If Democrats underperform in the
midterms, it it will be because we did
not do the proper organization ahead of
time.
If Democrats underperform in the
midterms really because we're not
focused on affordability and
accountability.
>> If Democrats win, it will be because
Democrats will win, it'll be because
we're absolutely right. And what is
taking place in this country because of
the Donald Trump administration is
horrific. And we've got real affirmative
answers that we can give that'll provide
people with a better life.
If if if Democrats win, it'll be because
the American public has finally seen
Donald Trump and this movement for what
it is and believe that a better America
is possible.
>> In this Trump era, one problem we've
discovered with the Constitution is
>> one
>> one and then we're out of here.
>> It's not a guarantee.
uh from the moment when I had an
understanding of politics and I grew up
not too far from here uh I believed in
the United States. I believed that there
were these foundational ideals that we
hold true and that those foundational
ideals were not dependent on ideology.
What we saw in Minneapolis and we have
are now seeing coming out of the halls
of government and specifically the White
House is that it's not guaranteed that
this republic lasts 10 and 20 and 30
years from now. And it is on all of us
not just to bend the arc of justice, but
to hold true for a country and this
experiment and to have that mean more
than partisan bickering or ideology or
anything else. Which also means that
Republicans have to have the guts to
tell MAGA people what they don't want to
hear.
It means that we have to have the guts
to stand up when something is wrong at
the threat of getting prosecuted by the
Department of Justice. It means we have
to have also the guts at times to tell
our own side what they don't want to
hear. That was more than a sentence.
>> It was more than a sentence. And
finally, in one sentence, Congressman
Garcia, we're leaving the stage. One
thing that works about the Constitution.
>> Oh, that works.
>> First Amendment.
>> Yeah, that's right. Look, look, I think
um I think just recognizing that the
press plays and must always play a
critical part of our of our government
and our democracy um and is there to
protect the people.
>> Please join me in thanking our guest
today. Thank you all.
Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Please welcome counselor to CAP and
president of CAP Action Caresia Graham.
>> [music]
>> Hello, hello, hello. Uh, thank you all
for being here again today and also for
all the work you're doing individually
to move big ideas forward. As we
celebrate the nation's 250th
anniversary, it's not just about
honoring our history. It's also about
laying the foundation for where we're
going. Virginia has a special place in
that story and today it is also testing
a uh test is it also a testing ground
excuse me for a fundamental question of
can government still deliver for the
working class. Our next speaker is
answering that question by placing
affordability at the center of her
agenda. Just within the first few months
of her administration, she's already
signed nearly a thousand bills, most of
which are measures aimed at lowering the
cost of living. She also helped turn the
nation's eyes toward the Commonwealth as
voters stood up to Trump and said, "No,
you will not wreak the rules of
democracy without a fight.
But her leadership has also not been
without some difficult decisions, some
in which draw real disagreement. We at
the Center for American Progress and
most of you are big, strong advocates
for workers rights. So we can be honest
and acknowledge that her recent veto of
the collective bargaining bill has
sparked some serious concerns about
workers right in an incredible important
moment. Even so, a big tip movement is
not one where we all agree on all the
things all the time. It is one where we
are honest about those differences,
where we keep showing up at the table,
and where we fight relentlessly to find
common ground and improve life for
working families. That is the work that
is before us today and that is the work
I know our next speaker believes in.
Here to share her vision for Virginia
and for the United States is Governor
Abigail Spanberger in conversation with
Jonathan Kart, co-host of MS Now's The
Weekend. Please welcome them to the
stage.
[music]
[applause]
Governor Spanberger, thank you very much
for being here and for your time. Um,
okay, let's just get it out of the way.
was mentioned in in the intro. Union
leaders in the Commonwealth are not
happy with your veto of collective
bargaining legislation that would allow
public workers to form unions and do all
the things that unions do for workers.
Why did you do that after expressing
support for such legislation during your
campaign?
>> So, I continue to support public sector
collective bargaining. Um, and I
continue to look forward to a place
where we'll have a bill that I'll sign
into law. Um, you know, importantly, I
sent back valuable amendments and that's
our process in Virginia. The governor
can sign, veto, or uh suggest
amendments. I suggested amendments uh
towards that legislation. They were
summarily rejected. Those amendments
were incredibly vital from an
implementation standpoint um and took
the feedback of localities and um
community members about what it would
look like to implement collective
bargaining in the public sector in
Virginia. Just as an example, you know,
standing up an entirely new system as
the chief executive who would be
implementing it um is is a big and
substantial shift. And so one of the
things that I propose in the amendment
is as we are creating uh we call it the
PERB in Virginia, our public sector
employee uh relations board that state
employees who are currently the class of
employees within the Commonwealth of
Virginia that have absolutely no right
to collectively bargain at the local
level. Uh that right exists. It's a
optin by localities. Um where state
employees, the ones I'm most responsible
for, uh would go first. So any hurdles,
challenges, kind of getting any of the
uh kind of practice and reps in for the
PERB would be tested on the employees
that I oversee. So by the point in time
when our localities across the
Commonwealth of Virginia would be
implementing an entirely new system, we
would have gotten through some of the
hurdles. 18 months later was the delay.
Um and I think that's a really
straightforward example of the types of
amendments that I put in place. Now,
notably, um, unfortunately in the
conversation related to my one veto is,
uh, lack of recognition of the fact that
we are, uh, the first state in the south
that has now implemented or not
implemented yet, but I signed into law
paid family and medical leave. Uh, I
[applause]
giving access to paid family and medical
leave um, as we build out the program to
millions of Virginiaians. Um we I signed
a bill to raise the minimum wage for all
workers. I signed another uh farm
workforce uh minimum wage bill which
importantly we built such a broad
coalition that we had support from uh
labor and union leadership to the farm
bureau uh heat protections for workers,
wage theft provisions. The number of
pro- labor, proworker, pro- Virginiaian
bills that I have signed into law um is
substantial, consequential, and I am
deeply proud of my record. And I look
forward to having conversations with my
counterparts in the legislature about
how we can continue to move forward um
and get to a place where we can also
create an implementable and durable
program as it relates to public sector
collective bargaining. Governor, given
everything that you just said, paid
family medical leave, raise the minimum
wage, um, laws on wage um, wage theft,
what why do you think there are folks in
the in the labor movement who say that
your veto was a quote betrayal as I saw
in one of the stories?
>> I would defer to them to answer that
question.
>> Okay. Um,
affordability is the catchphrase, the
watch word, whether the president wants
to believe it's a real thing or not.
What are you doing for Virginiaians for
whom affordability is more than rising
gas prices? It's jobs. It's health care,
particularly because of Doge. You're a
little more than a 100 days into your
administration. what are you doing to
uh nip away or chip away at the
affordability issue in your in the
Commonwealth?
>> Well, so it's a it's a all uh avenues
approach. And so importantly, before I
was even uh sworn in, I released my
affordable Virginia agenda in
partnership with members of the general
assembly. All of those bills, the bills
focused on lowering costs of housing,
healthcare, and energy passed through
the general assembly. 75% of them in
fact with bipartisan support. those
bills. I have signed all of them into
law, you know, and just as sort of an
sampling an example um on the housing
side, allowing localities to keep
affordable housing in affordable
housing. Um protecting renter rights. So
that part of the challenge of course is
that once you face the potential of
eviction, getting back into the housing
market can be so much of a bigger hurdle
than really overcoming potentially one
uh missed rent payment. uh giving
localities, we're a Dylan rule state, so
giving localities the opportunity and
the options to be a bit more expansive
with how they uh choose to build um and
and ensuring that we also at the state
level are contending with some of the
the um call it restrictions or
regulations that can sometimes impede
housing growth. on the health care side.
Um, changing the way that a a patient
might have to deal with prior
authorizations that can overall increase
costs and deplete care and and take away
from that patient doctor uh experience.
We've capped the cost of insulin out of
pocket costs $35 a month. Uh we've also
kept out-ofpocket expenses um in in
terms of the types of plans that that
people can pay into. They would have to
have limits on what's out of pocket. um
and we're cracking down on the middlemen
uh in prescription drugs, principally
PBMs. Um so that's on the legislative
side, but then importantly within my
administration, I via executive order
test all of my uh secretariates to do a
full review of the work within their
agencies, places where they can have a
focus on affordability and and look at
even the the not obvious priorities that
they might be pursuing through the lens
of affordability. And so every
conversation we are having whether it's
uh education related or transportation
and investment related um our state
agencies and
uh our my cabinet secretaries are
consistently and clearly focused on
issues of affordability whether it's
affordability to the taxpayer which
ultimately does um you know impact every
individual household or uh affordability
in the way that whatever it is we are
implementing from a state perspective
might impact their paycheck. What's the
the the best idea um that you and your
administration has come up with so far
that you think is something that should
that your fellow governors should take a
look at and replicate when it comes to
affordability?
>> That's a good question. You know,
there's a a couple different pieces
where, you know, I'll give a very simple
example, and this does not solve the
affordability question at all, but I
think it's an issue of giving a little
bit of consumer choice. Um, we're the
second state in in the nation to uh sign
into law a a balcony solar bill. And so
it's Utah was first, we were second, and
that's allowing individual homeowners,
renters uh to be able to do the plug-in
solar generation in Virginia. It'll be
legal as of July 1st. Um and and so
that's not going to meaningfully kind of
upend everything within the Commonwealth
of Virginia, but it allows for the
individual consumer to lower their costs
a bit. um from an overall agency
perspective and kind of across the state
government perspective, a lot of the
work that we are doing um within
commerce and trade which oversees our uh
multiple departments including including
focusing on housing. Um we are really
trying to get aggressive in how we bring
housing into the conversation of
commerce and trade and economic
development. Um, and so I think some of
what the work that we're doing there, we
have had really innovative ideas come
from some of the investments that have
come to and continue to come to
Virginia. but also setting up I'll give
one more um a a fund to be able to have
um uh you know
varied housing and allow for localities
um and to attract the public private
partnerships with some capital available
to them in order to be able to um uh to
build housing um in communities that
otherwise may not be able to sort of
fully bring an anchor of both capital
and interest enough on their
One of the things about the Virginia
governorship is that by by law it is
only one term, which means um you've got
one term to do lots of things. Um I've
talked to some of your predecessors, for
them it's a bit of a a a liberating
thing to not have to run for reelection.
So given that, what's the best idea that
another governor has done or is doing
that you would like to bring to
Virginia?
So, because of this one-term
governorship, it means that the things
that you are planning for have to be
durable. Um, and so I I think that among
the best things that some of my
predecessors have done and what I'm
looking to do is some of the best ideas
that I'm trying to bring to Virginia and
principally these are sort of longer
term investments whether it is in
um transportation is kind of chief among
them. you have to set up the
investments, the priorities that you are
making in a way where they are teed up
for someone else's success. And so a
conversation I'm consistently having
with our Secretary of Transportation
because, you know, if you want to drive
economic investment, if we want to
continue to attract businesses, and I
think the same can be true also in our
investments in education, right? We're
we are the number one state for talent.
We want to continue to supercharge that
and drive on that. But whether it's
investments in our schools and in
recruiting educators to Virginia and
keeping them in the classrooms or
whether it is um investments in roads
and bridges and infrastructure, uh those
are successes that you have to kind of
tee up that you know someone else will
take uh credit for responsibility for
and making sure that it is teed up for
success and not for someone else's
headache um is is a principal
requirement. And so I I think of many of
the things that I'm doing through that
lens of how do I make this so durable
that nobody else will want to sort of
pull back or depprioritize something
that I believe to be so important to the
future of the Commonwealth and and
Virginiaians. So, um, Virginia is seems
to be always in the news, but I believe
it was last week when, um, the United
States Supreme Court stepped in and
sided with the Virginia the Virginia
Supreme Court in overturning the
redistricting um, effort that was passed
by the people of the Commonwealth. Um,
first your reaction to that and what
does that say about the state of our
democracy when the people have had their
say and the United States Supreme Court
stepped forward and said no.
So just and and you you touched on it in
your question, but just to reiterate the
point, what was different about what
Virginia was doing from some of the
other states that we've seen on the
Republican side of the aisle who have
done redistricting is we could not take
action without the vote of the people, a
referendum, so similar to what
California had to go through. Only ours
is a multi-step process. The last
process being a ballot referendum, which
we did in April, which is an unusual
time frame for a ballot referendum, but
yet we still had extraordinary voter
turnout. Of course, the people voted yes
in that referendum. More than 3 million
Virginiaians voted. And I say that
because my disappointment with the
Supreme Court of Virginia falls
principally on the fact that we executed
this election, which is a multi-ter
process, goes through the general
assembly, goes through the general
assembly, again, goes before the people,
and millions of Virginiaians in favor or
opposed cast their ballot demonstrating
their view, my our shared view, that
that election is legitimate. and the
Supreme Court of Virginia determined
that indeed it wasn't legitimate um and
nullified the results of that election.
Um and so it uh I find it
extraordinarily frustrating. Um but my
response to it has to be that now we
have to prove the point by winning. You
know, notably, we have 11 congressional
districts. Of the uh we have six that
are currently held um by Democrats, five
that are currently held by Republicans.
Of those remaining five that are held by
Republicans, I won two of them on the
ballot in November when I ran for
governor. And just, you know, on the
details of the politics, in a statewide
race, you're not necessarily trying to
win the contours of a congressional
district. So, two of those races are
imminently winnable. Um, and then
arguably when I won my first
congressional race, my predecessor had
won in 2016 by 15 points. I won in 2018
by two points. That's a 17 point swing
by those numbers. And with a president
who is even more unpopular than he was
in the last time we faced a midterm for
him, we can win three to four seats in
Virginia. And so,
[applause]
so while I have lots of feelings about
the results uh of the Supreme Court
decision, I am channeling all of that
towards trying to encourage people to
not feel depleted or to channel their
their worry, their anguish, their
disappointment, their anger into
volunteering for a candidate, supporting
a candidate, and making sure that we win
two to four of those races. is um on the
current lines it will be rough but you
know things worth doing are not always
easy and we have to do it.
>> How concerned are you that the president
on election day or even before how
concerned are you that he
will send either the military or the
national guard or even ICE to polling
places and what can you do what what can
you do if anything to stop him?
um
very concerned. I'm also my background
is national security, so I think you
should always sort of plan for every
contingency that might cause a worry.
Virginia, we have certain advantages. We
have 45 days of early voting. Um and so
enabling voters to be able to go to the
polls over a period of time is an
important step for us. um and does
create a slightly different experience
than some of you know other states where
you will see just lines around the
blocks and blocks and blocks of people
waiting to get into poll the polling
places. Um
uh you heard it first here. Tomorrow
I'll be um issuing an executive order.
>> So uh surprise sorry to my comm's team
on this one.
>> Let it out governor. Let it out. um
in ensuring that we are putting out from
the state level some guidance um across
public spaces including um polling
places of how uh Virginia state
employees or people who are working in
support of Virginia's state-run
elections um can react to in in this
particular case, you know, federal
agents who might be appearing at a
location um and where or the worry is
that they're principally there to
intimidate or scare people. Um but but
the reality is that that there are um
there's a lot of you know throughout
history we have seen efforts at
intimidating voters um and my worry is
that we will continue to see those
heightened. Um, and while I will
continue to encourage people to vote by
mail or to vote orally, the reality is
that the the challenges and the fear
that people might have when going to the
polling place is real. Um, and we have
been here before um in a totally
different way in a totally different
context. But people have bravely gone to
polling paces decades in the past. It's
what created change. It is what made
Virginia, you know, a place where
progress was ultimately achieved and
calling upon that history of brave
people doing the thing that they know is
impactful, which is using their voice at
the ballot box. Um that despite the
concerns will be the encouragement that
I continue uh to put in place, but also
making sure that people know um and
where possible um and appropriate people
have the ability to kind of push back
and know what their rights are. All
right, I have a question from the
audience. Um, you can see it there,
Governor, but I'll read it for everyone.
How do you think about data centers?
Lowden County gets almost half of its
tax revenue from data centers, but they
are broadly unpopular with voters. How
do you balance what voters want with
what's good for Virginia's economy and
budget and do that in less than 5
minutes and 5 seconds?
>> Sure. You know, and this is an
interesting thing because um it also
becomes a question of what voters want.
voters may not necessarily want a data
center, but they certainly want the
iPhone with the data on it in their
pocket. Um, which I I say not to be kind
of sassy and disrespectful, but because
it's actually true. And so sometimes the
conversation has to be if you like
ordering things online or watching
movies or, you know, storing your photos
in the cloud, like that's data centers
are behind that and it are essential to
it. Data centers are are a driver in in
many ways of Virginia's economy. Um, and
this example certainly gives Louden, but
the example doesn't stop with Louden.
Across the Commonwealth of Virginia, um,
the the taxes that data centers pay into
local economies are substantial and
essential uh to the ability to provide
basic local services, funding schools
and first responders. Um and so I
continue to make the case that certainly
Virginia is a place that many data
centers want to come has a lot of uh
ability to say what we expect in terms
of uh you know their the requirement
that they pay their own share when it
comes to energy utilization or um
everything from the setbacks to the
types of greenery that they put around
their locations. and from a
gubernatorial standpoint being able to
provide support to localities that
really might not know what to ask for in
those types of negotiations. But what I
have incoming to my office so
significantly is a lot of localities
because yes, many of them went to
Ladowden first. Um, but it is a lot of
smaller, more rural localities that
really want to bring the investment and
the support that they bring. Um, and so
it is I I balance it by saying yes,
there's real challenges, but in fact
there's significant benefits and it's
about what local economies need. Now, I
think locality should always have the
final say. So I'm as governor would
never force any particular type of
industry or investment into a locality
that doesn't want it, but I think that
it is wrong for the state to preclude uh
localities that do want to welcome data
centers from being able to do so.
Governor, in the time that we have left,
let's talk about the 250th anniversary
of the United States, which is this
July. Um, Virginia's role in that
anniversary is um vital. How how will
the Commonwealth celebrate America's
250th uh anniversary? What are you going
to do?
>> So, our slogan is America made in
Virginia. [laughter]
Uh, Governor Mikey Cheryl has some
feelings about that.
Um, but we have events and have had
events occurring all across Virginia on
July 4th in particular. Um, we have
phenomenal events happening all across
the Commonwealth, fireworks and
communities that are all sort of
registered with Virginia 250. If you
want to go to uh the Virginia 250
website, there is a lot of information
about what might be available, different
tourist attractions, sites, locations
that um we welcome you all to visit. On
July 4th, some of the the um landmark or
kind of capstone events that will be
occurring is at Montichello. Um there
will be a mass swearing in event for new
citizens. And so what better way
[applause]
what better way to celebrate the
founding of the United States um or the
our declaration of independence by
welcoming uh Virginiaians to Montichello
Thomas Jefferson's home and having those
those Virginiaians uh become new
Americans on July 4th. Uh there's also
going to be an event in Williamsburg
which of course uh is kind of essential
to Virginia and US history uh the site
of the original House of Burgesses. Um
and there will be extraordinary
fireworks there and in cities and towns
all across the Commonwealth of Virginia.
>> Um Governor, luckily for you, we've got
a minute, so I'm going to luckily for
me, you might not like this question,
but um final question. I just want you
to keep your CIA hat on because you're a
former CI CIA officer. Um, were you
surprised that Iran closed the Straight
of Hormuz?
[laughter]
>> No.
>> [applause]
>> And so, Governor,
if you were in a position to
get it reopened, what's the one thing
you would do to get that done?
Not threaten to obliterate an entire
civilization.
[applause]
I mean, not not to make light of a very
serious circumstance, but it is I mean,
it's an outrage the way the Trump
administration started a war, then says
they're going to end a war, then
continues bombing a country. Um, and
sort of it is, it is, I think, meant to
be disorienting and confusing, but it is
absolute chaos. And, you know, gas
prices are
continue to creep up. like $45 a gallon
is crazy in Virginia and it's hurting
people. Um, and it is a direct result of
the bad choices from this
administration.
>> Abigail Spamberger, 75th governor of
Virginia, thank you very much for the
conversation. [applause]
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hope you all have had a great great
morning and enjoyed the discussion. Uh
we're going to have our 30 minute lunch
break. Um for those here in the
ballroom, you uh can grab your lunch out
in the foyer. And for those who are
joining us virtually, uh Trevor Higgins
will be discussing energy costs and Chad
Masel will be discussing housing costs.
Enjoy lunch. See you all in 30 minutes.
>> Hello folks. Thanks so much for tuning
in to the 2026 CAP Ideas Conference. My
name is Colin Seaberger, senior adviser
at the Center for American Progress. I'm
excited to chat a bit more about
affordability. It's something that we
talked a lot about this morning with my
colleague Chad Mazelle uh who is senior
fellow uh and one of the authors behind
CAP's housing plan we released last
year. Chad, thanks so much for joining
us.
>> Thanks for having me. I feel like this
is the closest I'll ever get to like a
Super Bowl halftime.
>> Oh yeah. Well, uh uh we'll see if
there's some fireworks at the end. Um
well, Chad, uh housing, we heard a lot
about it, particularly among uh you
know, on the panel with several
different kind of next generation
leaders. Um we know that housing costs
are crushing families. Prices have gone
up over 50% since the pandemic. Rent has
shot up over 30%.
Why has this become such a big challenge
in this country?
>> Well, yeah, it's it's you know, you you
name the stats and anyone following
along knows this to be true that the,
you know, housing affordability
challenges that we're seeing today is
really at the center of our broader
affordability crisis that we're seeing
nationwide. And so, you know, and it
used to really be an issue primarily
confined to big cities on the coast, you
know, where you'd see the $3,000 studios
and the million-dollar starter homes and
so on. But really what we've seen over
the last decade, decade plus, is this is
increasingly a national issue where
you're seeing 20, 30, 40, 50, 60%
increases in the last 5 years alone in
rental costs. Over the last decade, home
values have nearly doubled. And so it's
just everyone is is feeling the pain.
The existing renters and then of course
the folks who want to buy their first
home, want a home that better fits their
needs and that feels increasingly out of
reach. There's a there's a data point
that I often think about because it's
illustrative of the broader challenge
around housing affordability and it
looks at the metro area of Phoenix.
About a decade ago in 2006 200 2005 2015
2016 about 80 to 85% of all rental units
in the Phoenix metro area were $1,500 or
less.
>> Today a decade later it's like 5 to 10%
are available. So, of course, wages have
gone up in that period, but if you are a
young person, someone on a fixed income,
uh someone, you know, low income, that
you're not seeing any inventory that
that meets your needs. And of course,
the pain, you know, goes up up all the
way up the income ladder. And so, you
know, you ask why it's happening.
There's a number of reasons, but at its
core is we're not building enough
housing.
>> Since the great financial crisis,
housing construction, housing production
fell off a cliff, and we just haven't
recovered since. Year after year, we're
at a deficit in terms of where we need
to be in housing construction. Now,
we're looking at a gap of at least 2
million units, probably quite a bit
more, and that's manifesting with much
higher rental costs, much higher home
values, higher homeless rates rates, and
everything that that follows.
>> Well, you talked about the need to build
more housing. Uh that's something that
takes a long time to do.
How does CAP's plan help you know get
rid of some of that red tape so we can
you know make a difference in people's
lives quickly? Uh and you know how do
you balance providing help to people in
the short term while making some of the
more long-term structural investments
that are needed to build the housing
supply out?
>> Right. Yeah. It's it's interesting
because you know housing policy is is
such a challenge in this way because we
know what the solution is. We need to
build more housing. But if you are a
renter and you've seen your rent go up
$1,000 a month in the last 5 years,
which it has for many people, you're not
really interested in a 10-year plan to
to build more housing. You need help
now.
>> And so that doesn't mean that we abandon
the work that needs to be done over over
many years. We need that. But we need to
pair that with this second imperative,
which is provide relief now. And so
that's what we try to do with with the
housing plan that you mentioned that CAP
just released called Bill Baby Build
aptly aptly named
>> Build Baby Build.
>> And it is and it and it really seeks to
address these two things. One, we need
to close the housing supply gap that 2
million plus unit gap in 5 years. We
need to do it quickly. And two, we need
to deliver short-term relief for
renters.
>> And you know, I can talk about a couple
of the Yeah. What does that look like?
So, so we the the the policy platform
puts forward a number of proposals, but
I'll I'll highlight a couple of them
that I think are illustrative of how
we're thinking about this and how we're
really pairing this need to build, need
to build fast, and need to deliver
short-term relief. So, the first is a
program that we call rent relief for
reform. And it's a new program that
would effectively put cash in the
pockets of renters if their local
leaders, their town actually builds the
housing that they need uh to close their
housing supply gap. Sounds popular.
>> It is. It is. And uh you know because it
it recognizes that housing supply. We
need communities to be held account.
They need to take whatever steps they
need to do to whether it's through
zoning changes, land use changes,
expanded access to financing, speeding
up permitting times. They can choose
their own venture. We don't care how you
get there, but you need to you need to
build more. You need to get more of
those permits done.
>> Sure.
>> Approved. And if you do, then your
renter households will benefit in the
form of a cash payment that will
effectively freeze their rent for that
short period of time. And so it's kind
of serving as as like a bridge. We know
that housing costs if you build more
will moderate in the long run, but we
need to get our renters there. We need
to provide that relief right away, and
that's what the the rent relief payments
serve to do.
>> Well, you talked about uh you know, home
values moderating over the course of the
long term as the you know, buildout
takes place.
It came up in one of the questions but
you know that can also be politically
tricky right um housing policy can be of
a delicate dance uh there's different
stakeholders who have uh you know
different interests
how do you see CAP's plan as helping
overcome some of those political
obstacles
>> well well two things I'll note you know
one and I I think it's really important
to note that no community is the same
and so we should be we need to be firm
in terms of pushing communities to build
more housing. I think that overarching
goal needs to be the policy of our
federal government. And for a very long
time, that was not the policy of
Congress, of the executive branch. It
was very hands-off. States and
localities should do whatever they want
within their within their borders. But
and governors and mayors and others
increasingly recognize that the status
quo is is not possible. We need to do
more. But I think it's also important
that the federal government doesn't
dictate what steps each locality has to
do has to take in order to um in order
to build more housing. In some places,
it could be allowing accessory dwelling
units. These are like granny flats or
you know basement apartments which are
illegal in many places. In more rural
communities, it might involve allowing
residential on Main Street on top of
storefronts. Some cities there are
height restrictions that are meaningful
barriers. So again, choose your own
adventure. communities have an
opportunity to go whatever direction
they want in order to um you know build
the housing they need but they need to
take they need to take action and and
then the second thing I'll say is right
now we have a status quo where if you're
a local decision maker you're deciding
on the on zoning changes for example you
are hearing from a very very very small
subset of people in your community
>> and those people are homeowners
>> they sure are
>> who for reasons good and had do not want
more housing in their community. They're
overwhelmingly opposed to new
development.
And we we think that local leaders
should be hearing more democratically
from their constituents. Right now,
renters are not in those meetings. And
I'll tell you who's definitely not in
those meetings is people who have yet to
even move to that community because
they're priced out. And so we think that
by
something like the rent relief or reform
program where we're really giving
renters some skin in the game and a
stake in the housing production that's
yet to come that we can really shake up
the local politics and really create a,
you know, a housing market locally that
works for each community but that
recognizes that there's lots of
constituents out there and not just the
incumbent homeowners. Well, Chuck, can
you tell me a little bit about what the
re response has been to the release of
this plan? Um, what kind of feedback are
you getting from policy makers? So, it's
been really extraordinary actually
because I think
>> leaders in Congress in particular are so
desperate for for new ideas in this
space and it's just as I said for a very
long time there's been a hands-off
approach when it comes to federal
housing policies especially as it
relates to what localities are doing on
zoning and land use. Um pretty stale set
of financing tools that we've had for a
very long time and haven't really
revisited. And so
>> those days are over, folks.
>> Those days are over. And we and we've
and we've put forward, you know, a
number of proposals that are that have
been or will imminently turn into bills
in Congress. Um, as you know, leader
Schumer, head of the Democratic caucus,
came to CAP to announce the Senate
Democrats housing plan, which, you know,
used quite a bit of, you know, and built
on quite a bit the proposals that we put
in our bill baby bill proposal. And so
the the response has been has [snorts]
been terrific because I think folks
recognize
when they go to their town halls, they
need they need new answers. And it can't
just be little dials to the existing
programs, you know, funding this a
little bit more, tweaking this
regulation. We need sweeping changes if
we're going to build the housing that we
need to protect renters, to advance fair
housing, to solve homelessness. This
these are not tweaks around the edges.
This is wholesale structural changes in
how we do business.
>> Well, uh, Chad, I'm curious. You know,
housing is something that affects
everybody, whether you rent, you're a
homeowner, uh, whether you're homeless
and you want to be, uh, you know, in an
apartment. um
you know, do you see this issue being
one that there could be uh bipartisan
traction for uh you know, doing some of
these kind of big, you know, bold
visionary ideas
>> 100%. And and I think we're seeing some
promising signs on the Hill. There's
some there's a couple bills that are
moving their way through through
Congress. There's a Senate version and a
House version um which is which proposes
some meaningful changes to a number of
programs and creates some new ones in
terms of boosting housing supply. It's
very consistent with the many of the
proposals that we put forward in the
Build Baby Build report and plan. We
think we need to go further and that's
what this is this is about. But again,
you talk to governors, Republican,
Democrat, you talk to mayors,
Republican, Democrat, members of
Congress, everyone recognizes that
no one cares who's what letter is next
to their name if it's an RNL. They they
they're desperate for change. They need
to be able to afford their rent. And and
people deserve to not spend 50% of their
income on rent. They deserve to be able
to buy a home at some point in their
lives. they deserve to not be forced to
live on the street uh because of an
unexpected rent hike. And so these are
the kinds of
solutions that that we think can drive
towards bipartisan change and also the
kind of structural
big big changes that we think we need.
You know, and you can't talk about
housing policy and uh in this moment and
not talk about the fact that the Trump
administration has been taking an act to
um make housing less affordable,
particularly for the most vulnerable
people in our our country right now. Um
we've seen a real backslide uh over the
course of the past two years on
homelessness. Uh we've seen um you know
cuts to uh affordable housing programs
uh from this administration. We've seen
the president's budget lays out uh you
know even more cuts to uh making sure
that people can have access to
affordable housing. Um you know how do
you square that with uh the needs of the
country where we are in this moment?
Yeah, it's honestly it's it's puzzling,
right? Because like President Trump of
course came into office talking about
high high costs, high housing costs,
>> but then since coming in, he's pretty
much done everything possible to go in
the opposite direction, making housing
costs more expensive um for builders,
you know, with things like tariffs. um
as you noted trying to take an axe
through the budget fortunately wasn't
successful on a lot of really critical
housing production programs affordable
housing production programs um voucher
the voucher program which helps
low-income people middle- inome people
cover cover rent and then the
dismantling the CFPB the consumer
financial protection bureau which is
this absolutely critical watchdog to
ensure that folks have access to credit
and um that we install basic
protections for home buyers, homeowners,
and and again uh dismantling that agency
and all the protections that it provides
for people. And so, and that's to say
nothing of, you know, the immigration
crackdown, which has had a
disproportionate impact on um workforce
site on construction sites, most of whom
are here legally.
>> Makes home building a lot more
expensive, doesn't it? So when they when
you're seeing, you know, huge
percentages of your workforce not show
up to work because they're scared of
getting illegally detained, that has a
huge impact on on the speed at which you
can actually build these homes.
>> Well, Chad, I appreciate uh you coming
and chatting with our audience. This is
I know uh you know, an issue that's top
of mind for so many Americans in this
moment. I'm sure it is one that we're
going to hear a lot from uh presidential
candidates as we go into uh you know
having a big national conversation about
what our priorities should be for the
future. Um so I appreciate you coming
and uh sharing more about it and uh
thanks so much.
>> You you got it. One thing I'll I'll plug
if I may is we um you know at the
beginning I talked about how this
housing affordability challenge is
really a a national one and so we have a
a resource on our website in addition to
checking out our report build baby
build. When you go to that report you
can click on an interactive map that
allows you to see in your county how you
stack up what the affordability
challenges are what they look like and
how they've changed over time.
>> Great. Well, thanks so much Chad.
>> Thanks Colin.
>> Yep.
All right, folks. We've talked a lot
about affordability challenges in this
country uh all throughout the
programming this morning. We're excited
this afternoon, though, to also turn to
uh real threats that we're seeing to our
democracy in this country. uh whether it
is uh efforts to crack down on voting
rights, uh purge black representation
from our government or uh you know
really the uh you know wholesale
takeover of uh our our government uh uh
in its elections uh or rampant
corruption that we see coming out of the
White House. So here to chat more with
me about it is democracy uh policy
director Greta Bakovich. Uh, Greta, it's
great to chat with you.
>> It's great to be here in this beautiful
ballroom on this great day.
>> Uh, we love a ballroom, but maybe not
one at the White House.
>> That's the only one.
>> Um, well, uh, Greta, I did want to chat
with you because one of the things that
we've been seeing from the Trump
administration as its approval rating
has really tanked over the course of the
past 6 to9 months is that the president
is getting desperate. he uh launched a
mid decade redistricting uh initiative
to try to uh you know pick up some
Republican seats in hopes that his party
can hold on to power in Congress. uh he
has pushed for um uh you know uh bills
to um really trample on voting rights in
this country uh through the Save Act
which he called for making the number
one priority of the Republican
majorities in Congress. Um and we also
know that he is taking steps to try to
undermine people's access to the ballot
box to do things like cast a mail-in
ballot. What does each of those things
what do they tell you about this
administration's approach to uh
democracy into respecting the rights of
people in this country?
>> Yeah. I I think it's just absolutely
clear that this president, his
administration don't believe in the
values of democracy and they're scared
of the power of the people. I mean
that's why they're doing this whole
laundry list of ways to undermine the
vote and really escape accountability.
And I think we are seeing him get more
and more desperate as his approval rate
is plummeting. But I think it's also
really important to keep in mind that
he's been on this mission pretty much
since Dave went in office. I mean, two
months into this administration, they
issued an executive order essentially
trying to implement SAVE in an
unconstitutional way on his own. And
that was just two months in when, you
know, he hadn't delivered any of his
policies. So, I think it's both clear
that they're ramping up their efforts as
they get more and more desperate. But
this has always been their plan for
democracy and how they're going to stay
in power and continue the MCA agenda. Uh
yeah, I think Americans are not uh you
know it is not lost on them that
President Trump is no uh you know fan of
democracy. He made that quite clear uh
when he incited an insurrection in the
capital.
That said, you know, we talked about the
save act. Um,
you know, you have really been at the
forefront of experts in this country
exposing
just the extent of the harm that the
Save Act could pose to Americans ability
to be able to, you know, register to um
or to cast a ballot entirely. Can you
talk to me a bit about how the Save Act
um would make it harder for Americans to
be able to register, to be able to cast
their ballots? Yeah, this is a battle
that we've been fighting now for
basically a year and a half again since
Trump took office. It's been a really
uphill battle because they've really
pitched the Save Act as an election
integrity measure as a way to prevent
non-citizens are voting on our
elections. And it's quite clear that we
all agree that non-citizens should not
be voting in our federal elections. That
is a right reserved for US citizens. And
so what we really were trying to do is
show citizens how this bill would really
impact them and make it hard for them to
vote, which is the end goal of this
bill. So right now, citizens, you and I
could go online, register to vote just
by providing our driver's license number
or our social security number, but if
the SAVE act passed, we would have to go
in person and show our passport or birth
certificate at an election office and
essentially convince election officials
that we are citizens and we say who we
are. And so we know from data that we've
shown, the Center for American Progress
is that half of Americans don't have a
passport. They're already facing so many
things with affordability. They're not
traveling internationally. They're not
paying $165 for a passport. So right off
the bat, we know that there are about
150 million people that don't have a
passport they could vote with. I mean,
that's basically a turnout in a
presidential election. So on top of
that, then we're looking at people who'd
have to use their birth ticket likely if
they're going to be voting and
registering to vote or updating
registration. And that's a huge issue
for married women because they've
married and taken their spouse's name
and don't have a birth certificate that
matches their current legal name and
would face additional hurdles. I mean,
so many married women were facing
hurdles going to the DMV just to get a
real ID. Now, they're going to do that
to register to vote. And so, let's say
you have all of those documents already.
You have everything in order. You're
going to your election office. Now, how
long is that drive going to be for you?
Because if you're in a city, maybe it's
a 20-minute commute. But if you're in an
incredibly rural area, that could be
seven or eight hours, which is driving
distances that we found in our reporting
in states like Arizona, in Wyoming, and
Idaho. And Senator Lisa Marowsky also
gave a fantastic speech on the Senate
floor basically walking people through
the different burrows in Alaska,
obviously incredibly rural,
>> having to fly in order to be able to
register to vote.
>> A 20-hour fairy in a $1,000 roundfare
trip just register to vote or update
your registration because let's say you
moved or got married and changed your
name. So, it's really not a bill that
affects you once throughout the course
of your life. Even as hard as that would
be, I mean, it's throughout the entire
course of your life. You're moving into
a dorm, you're moving apartments, moving
into a nursing home. All of these things
would require you to go back down to
your election office and convince the
government that you are a citizen.
>> And you know, we also know that uh you
know, some of these uh policies have
actually been taken up by uh several
states across the country recently and
that the result of those new laws um has
actually made it significantly harder
for people to be able to exercise their
right to vote. um there's been, you
know, real proof points. Uh can you tell
me a little bit about those?
>> Yeah, that's exactly right. I mean, the
biggest thing about the Save Act is we
don't have to draw on these
hypotheticals for how this might play
out because we've seen how it plays out
in states. So, you know, Kansas
experiments with the law similar to this
a decade ago. It's not on the books
anymore because 32,000 eligible American
citizens were blocked from registering
to vote. And yet, we see the Save Act as
a federal proposal proposals across many
different states. New Hampshire as well
just last year implemented a law really
similar to the Save Act. It was only in
effect for small local town elections.
So things like municipalities for
mayoral races and things like that. And
we saw hundreds of people blocked from
registering to vote and unable to cast
their ballot because of the new state
law. Many of whom were married women
which we've been warning about over and
over again. I mean two things really
stuck with me. There was an elderly
woman who was just moved back to New
Hampshire. She had been a longtime
resident before but moved back to the
state. had to update her registration
and she said she had everything with her
but her blood type in the kitchen sink
and she was still told she was not able
to register to vote after coming back
three times to the polls with new
documentation. And then one election
official too testified that you know
these are local towns. They people all
know each other. She saw a recently
divorced couple come into the polling
location to cast their vote. And the
woman, the ex-wife, had not the
documentation to prove her name change,
which she reverted back to, and she was
not able to cast her ballot, but her
ex-husband was able to cast his ballot
just fine. So, these are, you know, real
life scenarios that we're seeing play
out. And at the same time, we're seeing
uh officials in DC ready to charge ahead
with this terrible idea. And then state
capitals across the country are doing it
on their own as we see more of a
deadlock in DC right now.
>> That's just outrageous. Uh and you know
I'm curious uh because you have been
able to expose so many of the harms that
this policy uh you know if it were to
become law uh could cause
and yet at the same time we know that
this is what President Trump says has to
be you know the number one priority.
What do you see as the likelihood that
this ends up making it to the
president's desk? Yeah, I mean I think
it's incredibly concerning that with any
mustpass bill essentially now Trump is
calling for it to be included. I mean
that with budget reconciliation. We see
it with housing. We see it with
potential FISA reauthorization. I mean
anyone that's moving in DC, he wants
this in there. But at the same time,
we've seen some resistance in Congress
because I think Republicans honestly
kind of smartly know that this bill
would be really bad for their base. I
mean from our data that we've shown, you
know, when we look at passport
ownership, it's in rural states where
that's the lowest. So we see that a lot
of conservative voters would be hurt.
Same thing with birth tickets. It's
married women, especially conservative
married women, who take their husband's
name at higher rates and so they would
be disproportionately impacted. So I
think that is a reality that a lot of
these legislators have to face and
essentially how their elections will
also be impacted if this bill passes. Um
so I think that's how we've seen a lot
of resistance even from Senator Marowski
who really spoke up for Alaskans and
eventually did not vote um to advance
the bill. And so I think as you know
they're battling with the president on
this. There's only so many times they
can continue to tell him like, "Oh, not
this bill, the next bill, and keep him
hanging on for longer." And at some
point, he's going to set his foot down.
And he's tried to do executive orders
that the courts have struck down for
being unconstitutionally illegal. Um, so
I think the future of this bill is
really up in the air right now.
>> Well, we talked about uh the SAVE Act. I
I mentioned earlier and we heard uh
minority House Minority Leader Hakee
Jeff reference the mid-deing push.
you know, where do you see uh you know,
this fight going in uh the years ahead
federally? Obviously, you know, leader
Jeff talked about the need to keep
fighting at the state level to make sure
that there's a level playing field and
that Republicans aren't able to tilt the
scales uh all in their direction. But do
you think that there's any opportunity
to um you know pass a ban on uh uh you
know partisan gerrymandering, mid-deing
uh at the federal level?
>> Yeah, I mean this has been a problem
that's been essentially plaguing
American elections since America has
existed. So I think 250 years sounds
like a good time to do something about
it. We've seen federal proposals before,
but I think especially now with the
Kelly decision and really, you know,
greenlighting racial gerrymandering. I
think we're going to see that previous
federal proposals, which would have been
in some ways a band-aid are just not
going to solve this problem. And we're
going to need much more large scale
change in a way that Americans, you
know, that if you have an election and
your candidate loses, you don't
automatically lose representation. So,
these are things that we're exploring
now and seeing where, you know, CAP's
ideas, for lack of a better word, are
going to go on this to make sure that we
don't just have a band-aid fix
redistricting, but really reimagining
what representation looks like in
America.
>> Well, stay tuned, folks. Uh, I know
you're going to be excited to hear what
we have up our sleeve. Greta, thanks so
much for joining us. It was great to
chat with you.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> Yeah. Well, folks, we are going to get
the program uh back up and running
momentarily. We're excited to bring you
uh some you know really exciting panels
this afternoon, some great speeches. Uh
I know we're going to talk about uh you
know some of the other really pressing
challenges that are facing uh both the
United States and the world. Uh so
thanks again for tuning in to the 2026
Cap Ideas Conference. Uh we'll get
started again soon. Thank you.
Hope you all enjoyed lunch and uh we're
ready to get started again. Please take
your seats. Thank you. Have a great
afternoon.
Please welcome back to the stage CAP
president and CEO Nerra Tanden.
[music]
Good afternoon everyone. How you doing?
I am very excited for our next speaker
and I I have a little story to tell
about it which is uh about a year ago
almost a year ago at the center for
American progress we hosted Betto Aor
from Texas and the governor uh then
senator then better was talking about
what's happening in Texas he actually
previewed in Washington that he thought
the Texas legislature would do a mid
decade redistrict. A lot of people at
the time thought it wouldn't happen. Um
but it did happen and the Center for
American Progress and Center for
American Progress Action Fund decided to
go into the fight to really encourage
blue states to respond with
redistricting efforts. We thought that
was important because when you have mid
decade redistricting,
it could mean that the president would
not be President Trump would not be held
accountable for his actions. So, we
thought it was really crucial. We called
leaders we knew in California, uh, a lot
of people in power and a lot of people
raised concerns about doing a ballot
initiative because here's the thing
about a ballot initiative, it could
lose. So, a lot of people were like,"Wh
take the risk? Why take the risk?" And
we said, "Because we believe democracy
is so important."
Well, Governor Nuome decided to go to
the public with a ballot initiative to
respond to Texas.
And because he did that and campaigned
for it, convinced the convinced the
state and actually delivered
California's redistricting could mean
the difference between accountability
and no accountability for this
administration.
>> [applause]
>> You know, a lot of people talk about
democracy, but it's important to take
risks for democracy and it's important
to fight for democracy. And that is
exactly what Governor Nuome did. So, we
are honored to have Governor Nuomo from
the great state of California to talk to
us about what's happening in the country
and how we can solve it. Governor Nuome.
by one member of the family. How are
you?
>> Good. Good. [applause]
>> Good to be with you.
>> Great to be with you. Well, maybe we
should just
>> start fresh here.
>> Start fresh. [laughter] Unbelievable.
Redistricting. Still fresh on my mind.
>> Great.
>> Fresh on everybody's mind. It is
remarkable. Uh what the Supreme Court
just did. I mean, it no other way to
describe it except Jim Crow 2.0. What
Governor Landry did was even more
alarming in this respect. He declared an
emergency and suspended an election that
already had been conducted at least for
42,000 people overseas in the military.
Literally suspended a the election so he
can redistrict out African-American
representation. That happened in 2020
six in the United States of America.
What happened in Tennessee? What's going
on in all of these other southern
states? So, you know, my state of mind
is very much on this unfinished work
that we have in front of us as it
relates to redistricting and waking
people up uh from this somber, this sort
of, you know, shock and awe, this
overwhelm every day being overwhelmed by
another headline, another distraction.
Uh but what lies underneath in terms of
what's holding up our democracy is in
real peril right now. Mhm. Speaking of
peril, uh we hear you we just have the
news just uh just in the last day or so
that the Trump administration settled
with itself
>> essentially
>> nothing.
>> Trump's Treasury Department made it
negotiated with Trump himself.
>> Yeah.
>> Over a10 billion frivolous lawsuit.
>> To give a $1.8 $8 billion
taxpayerf funed slush fund. I would just
call it a slush fund that will pay out
to his allies who were involved in the
insurrection. So just penny for your
thoughts on that topic. [laughter]
>> Well, it's exactly why the our founding
fathers lived and died.
>> I mean, it's a hell of a thing. the
250th anniversary where literally this
declaration was conceived to stop this
kind of corruption, this waste and this
fraud. Uh this is I mean it it's it's
it's so alarming. 17 by the way, not
1.8. Uh it's
1776.
Uh jokes's on you, I guess, or on all of
us. This is a corruption story. Plain
and simple. Trump administration's a
corruption story. It's the great grift
and it's taking shape on an daily basis
in every way, shape or form. You didn't
even mention the $230 million at the DOJ
that he's also trying to extract. Not
just that $10 billion now $1.8 billion
settlement. We've talked a lot about the
$400 million plan which is not $400
million. It was over $900 million in the
Pentagon budget to retrofit the plan. We
talked about the eight largecale
projects he has in the Gulf and around
the rest of the globe. uh the fact that
he quite literally used the tariff
regime in order to get those deals done,
particularly the one in Vietnam. We're
talking about the kind of corruption at
scale we've never seen in our lifetime,
including what Wickoff family is doing,
what the Kushner family is doing, uh the
Board of Peace, which is really about
getting a piece of the Middle East.
>> All of this happening plain open sight.
You saw last week in, you know, the fact
that finally he's delivering on the cell
phones. Another part of the griff, the
good old days when it was just about
watches, $100,000, sneakers, $60, uh,
and cell phones. This is happening at a
scale we've never experienced in our
lifetime. And he's just winding up. And
where is Congress? Where's Johnson?
Where is Thoon? Supine completely
complicit in all of this graph and all
this corruption. There are institutions
also rolling over, also selling out with
respect, as you know. And I know I
offend people. I've got a Patriot site,
which in and of itself should be
reasonably offendive because it mirrors
and mocks a little bit of what Trump's
doing, but we sell knee pads.
[laughter]
And and and by the way, the last ones
sold out. New ones just got in. But you
know, they sold out because our
universities, remember that, were
selling out. Our law firms were selling
out. media is selling out all those
settlements you got and the corruption
is you know what Brendan Carr is doing
>> what he's doing with the Tangga deal
next $6.2 2 billion going to get 80%
penetration in our household markets.
The cap was 39%. Brennan Carr saying he
didn't like the war coverage and is
considering now investigating certain
media outlets. This is all happening on
our watch. Society becomes how we
behave.
We have agency. We have a
responsibility. It's just like the issue
of redistricting. We could have decided
it to write an op-ed.
We could have decided, you know, you
know, hold hands, have a candle light
visual, win the argument.
These guys are ruthless on the other
side. Trump's not screwing around and
nor can we. Yeah, it's uncomfortable
fighting fire with fire. Yes, we all
want the better angels. Yes, we want the
Sorcin sound and music, little West
Wing. I do.
But we'll lose our country. We will lose
our country. You saw today. What is the
president of the United States spending
all his time on? He had a big press
conference about the new design for the
ballroom. The ballroom that he promised
would be private in terms of its
contribution. Now he's asking a billion
dollars of your taxpayers money. You saw
what happened yesterday with Hexa.
This is this is the middle of a war. 80
days in the middle of a war. So what
does the head of the Pentagon do? He
goes out there and campaigns in a
partisan campaign for someone that
didn't do the bidding of the president.
This is happening in real time. And it's
happening on our watch again. Society
becomes how we behave for things to
change. We need to change. You need to
change. We all need to change and call
this stuff out. [applause]
No. And none of this normal. Don't allow
it to be normalized. Do not allow this
to be normalized. It's a corruption
story. That's the Trump administration.
Period. full stop.
>> Uh one of the differences we see in our
country uh versus other countries, you
know, if you look at Orban's Hungary or
Putin's Russia, um you know, we are
seeing a public opposition. So when you
when you talk about what people should
do in this moment, what are you what do
you recommend to us?
>> Well, you don't give into the fear of
cynicism, anxiety, and fear. You realize
that you're the antidote to all of that.
Again, it's not conditions. It's
decisions that shape our fate and
future. You've seen that with the no
kings rallies. People are showing up.
They're not falling prey to the system.
You've seen them showing up in state
house races. Over 30 have flipped from
red to blue. Not one blue to red. We're
winning. People are showing up. They're
not giving up. They showed up for
Proposition 50. It was a nine 90day
campaign. We raised $118 million. We
also raised the consciousness from that
was when you did the introduction was
you were I was thinking the fact the
reason people were reticent about that
is it pulled at 48%.
When people were talking about it we had
to shape shift things
again decisions not conditions. So we
got to turn it up. They're trying to rig
the election. Donald Trump knows he's
going to get crushed this November.
That's why he made the phone call to
Abbott saying he's quote unquote
entitled to five seats. That should put
Chill up his mind alone, that he's
entitled to the five seats. He didn't
expect how we'd respond. Didn't expect
how Virginia responded.
>> But again, we saw how their court
responded. This is hard work. And we're
seeing how they're responding. Not just
Landry, but we saw within hours how
Abbott or not Abbott, but Dantis uh
responded with an exclusive on Fox News
where the new maps were shown. Not the
democratic process, with the
transparency of the people in Virginia,
but an exclusive with Sean Henry on Fox
News. These guys are not screwing
around. Ask folks down in Falton County.
Is Trump screwing around? Trying to go
after our voting roles in California.
He's not screwing around. Do you think a
fair free election? You think that's
realistic with Trump this November after
all he did on January 6 and now the 1.8
billion dollars take care of all but
this is like what more heaven is we're
dumb as we want to be to think that you
saw what happened just on prop forgive
me going back to Prop 50 but the day of
the campaign in Los Angeles Donald Trump
of course sent out on True Social the
election was rigged. He sent out the
Department of Justice to oversee all of
the corruption.
That morning, he sent out the Borac
teams. These are the Border Patrol
tactical unit teams. These are the
Apache helicopter guys. All dressed up
in front of Dodger Stadium for the
morning news so that our diverse
communities wouldn't show up for vote.
You think he's not going to do that
again all across this country? Come on.
And what evidence honestly is there
of what we're about to face? We've got
to wake up to this new reality. So, we
have to be, dare I say it, I'm sorry,
Democrats, we have to be as ruthless
as our opposition. We do.
We have to win. It's all on the line.
You just got to win. I I'm done winning
arguments. With all due respect to the
nicities, it feels good, but we're going
to lose our republic. Again,
honey fathers do not live and die for
this moment. I can't celebrate July 4th,
the best of Roman Republic and Greek
democracy, co-equal branches, co-equal
branches of government, you know,
popular sovereignty, the rule of law,
not at the time where it's the rule of
dawn.
And if it hasn't dawned on you, I I
remember was spending 90 minutes with
Trump in the Oval Office and I I think
he honestly thought everything was his.
He was showing me the declaration, his
declaration.
It's a prize.
White House. A corruption story
happening on our watch.
>> So, speaking of fighting, uh President
Trump fights with you a lot as as you
might notice. Uh he's also like
basically waged a 10-year war on blue
states and blue cities. Now, here at the
Center for American Progress, we do care
about facts and figures and we know that
California has grown to have the fourth
largest economy in the world. Um that it
is an engine of economic growth. But
what do you say to people who worry
about blue state governing?
>> Well, I don't No, I mean they were the
economic engine of the United States.
Blue metros.
During the Biden administration, about
71% of the GDP in the United States of
America emanated in blue metros. 71%.
[laughter]
You I mean,
we're the tentpole of the American
economy. Blue states,
they're the many of these red states are
donor states.
I mean, and again, speaking of state of
mind, they're also states with lower
productivity, lower wages, higher death
rates, higher deaths of despair. Um, the
innovation index not even interesting
compared other states. And they're some
of the highest tax states. And I really
want to make this point.
>> The most regressive taxes in the United
States of America are red states. They
tax poor people more than they do the
very rich. Think about that. Who's the
high tax state? Florida or California?
Texas or California?
We tax. We have the highest tax rate. We
don't have the highest taxes. But you
fall prey to that. Many of you, the
punditry, lazy punditry. We
>> We're very happy with all the reporters
that are here. However, [laughter]
>> you do. You got to update your facts. By
the way, we we we did update ours. You
know, the Bloomberg just came out with a
piece that should just disabuse everyone
of this California derangement
syndrome.
The top performing economy of all the 49
others. The top performing economy of
all developed nations since 2019. 40%
GDP growth. We have no peers. We
dominate in every category. Dominate.
You talk about manufacturing, you're
talking about my home state. You talk to
me about forestry jobs and hunting jobs,
you're talking about my home state.
You talk about venture capital. Come on.
$106 billion record-breaking venture
capital. You talk about every category.
There's not a single single category
largecale economic category where
California isn't the dominant state. We
have more engineers, more researchers,
more Nobel laureates than any other
state in the nation. And we are the
center of the universe. We're writing
the rules of the future. And this is why
the right hates us.
It's insecurity. It's not our
trajectory.
You talk about fusion, you talk about
quantum, talk about AI, you're talking
about California, 32 of the 50 top
market cap AI companies in our backyard,
the state of California. So all of these
areas uh promise peril you know all of
that is represented in all of what I
just said that mosaic that is California
the future happening in California often
first America's coming attraction
including the challenges of
affordability housing crisis that
appeared in our state decades before
it's now become not just a trend line
but a headline across the United States
the issues of homelessness poverty
relationship to the cost of housing ing
the original sin in my state. So much of
that now dominant in the consciousness
and focus uh as we relate to the
American system today.
>> I will get to AI but uh homeless
homelessness and particularly housing
costs have been high. Um you've taken
some actions on housing. Uh we at CAP uh
been very focused on how to lower
housing costs. Looked at a lot of your
ideas, a lot of synergies there. Do you
want to talk about what you've been
doing on housing? Well, we we've seen a
59% increase in the number of new
housing constructions since 2019 and a
56% reduction in the time uh for
permitting and it's still a low bar bar.
It's a crisis. Um that said, we were
aided and emedded by he's here Ezra
Klein this abundance mindset which is
California. It's not a scarcity mindset.
It's always at our best nation as well.
An abundance mindset and we recognize we
need the party that builds. Period. Full
stop. The Democratic brand should be the
party build building. I there's one word
to define us. Uh there's destruction on
the other side of institutions and
allies and trust truth on the other
side. Ours building liberalism that
builds. And so that's our mindset and we
were able to carry through with much
more aggressive actions. Again, for
things to change, you have to change.
And so rather than the usual pace of
reform that took shape in my state,
including my first six years on housing
where we made progress,
we weren't making a difference. And
that's when we decided to move these
historic housing bills into the budget,
which you don't do. And I threatened to
veto the budget unless we got the
housing bills done. And we were
successful in doing so. It's the mindset
we need to take into the future because
at the end of the day, when you and I
were briefly talking about this a moment
ago, uh this system's broken.
>> It's broken, folks. 10% of people own
twothirds of the wealth. Same 10% own
93% of the value of the stock market.
30-year-old is not doing better than is
her father for the first time in
history. That is a five alarm fire.
Doesn't work anymore. We can't tinker
anymore. You can't play in the margins
anymore. There's a reason Donald Trump's
in office. A reason Bernie fills
stadiums. They're both right on the
diagnosis.
And we can't with respect, you know, you
know, fail more efficiently by managing
more effectively. The decline
>> doesn't work anymore. System has to be
reimagined. It does. Can't play in the
margins. Tax code is broken. I'm sorry.
No, it offends many of you. It is
inheritance codes doesn't work anymore.
It's why we're having billionaire tax,
wealth tax debates in my home state and
all across the United States. The
pitchforks, yeah, they're here. They're
not just coming, you know, and we saw
with all the populism and
authoritarianism that came from that
because of our lousy trade deals and
that you when looking back, we're all
geniuses, but the last 30 years and the
rise of these authoritarian tendencies
in terms of governance, you know, we
ain't seen nothing yet because now it's
the bluecollar worker that sounds a lot
like 25year-old white collar workers
that I see in San Francisco that are
wondering why they're not getting a call
back
>> on a job interview, they're sounding the
same. That's a different kind of
coalition, the white collar and blueco
collar coalition.
A lot of people are a little frustrated
on the stepped up basis where you can
just borrow, die, no tax.
I This is, you know, enough. This is not
working. That's why I raised the minimum
wage to $25 for healthcare workers, 20
for fast food workers. you still have 20
states at 725 an hour and you're
subsidizing that. That's madness. And
now with these trend lines and we've
seen AI is going to detonate all of this
and it's happening in real time and
we're not talking about that. I know
we're talking about hypers scale data
centers and the utility that's that's
interesting but we're missing sorry a
memo from the west coast the world I'm
living in absorbed by consumed by
something big is happening in the
plumbing of the world and we still have
systems that were designed in 1935
that are no longer viable in 193 you
know 25
unemployment insurance you think that's
going to work and hold up that doesn't
work for clerical workers anymore. You
need employment insurance, universal
basic income. You don't need charity. We
need ownership. It's universal basic
capital. By the way, those are the
creators telling you that, not just me.
That's what Sam Alman, Dario, and others
are saying. They're the ones making that
point. And the voters are demanding it.
Got to have an ownership stake. You
cannot save democracy unless we
democratize the economy.
Period. It's just simply not going to
hold up. It's the exact same fight. And
so when I hear people saying, "Well, you
know that Newsome guy, he's all about
resistance. We need to focus on
renewal." Sure, but I think it's the
same damn fight.
And so it's not just about populism,
about realism. I don't begrudge other
people's success. I admire it. Can't be
pro- job and anti- business, but
businesses can't thrive in a world
that's failing. And it's failing. I
mean, you need GoFundMe page now if you
have a major medical issue. Literally I
have a friend God is my win at Sulamine
yesterday literally sent me a GoFundMe
guy has two or three jobs and now
gofundme the hell is that you have a
health care system that's simply not
viable you know that you may not like
singlepayer I don't even know how the
hell to do it in terms of how I get rid
all your private health insurance but it
seems something's got to give
just doesn't add up debt and entitlement
seriously energy and climate change come
on in democracy and this economy me. So,
there's these tectonic plates and we've
been slow to respond. Old bargain no
longer applies. My mom talked about 52
paychecks and it required her 104. I
feel like those are the good old days.
104 paychecks.
So, this is this is my mindset as I try
to close out the last seven months of my
administration. I'm going to now run the
90 yard dash and u and I'm thinking
about universal base of capital. I'm
thinking about public equity funds and
dividends. I'm thinking about ownership.
I'm thinking about what, you know,
you're seeing in places like Denmark
that do 90% wage replacement over a
two-year period and scale it down. I I'm
thinking differently about the War Act
and doing early warning systems for
displacement. I'm thinking about the
fact that we're entitled to a
transition. It's not just a severance uh
in a LinkedIn post.
I I'm thinking very differently about
all these things. And so we've got an
executive [clears throat] order in this
space. We've got a very aggressive
effort, a series of efforts to pilot at
scale some of these approaches to start
to deal uh with some of this anxiety,
deal with the inevitable displacement.
>> So just to zero in on AI, uh as you
noted, uh California is the home base of
AI. uh a lot of the AI companies um in
the United States right now we have an
administration that essentially for the
most part is people are on their own
then in some corners people are
basically saying we should try to stop
AI which is impossible to do as a as a
technology
so we're also seeing that attitudes
towards AI are becoming much more
negative in part because I think people
think they're just going to be off on
their
you have a as I as I understand a new uh
EO uh on impacts on the workforce.
>> Yeah. Well, we look we were the first to
regulate large language model frontier
models, the first safety efforts in the
United States. When people say no one's
regulating, they're wrong.
They haven't focused on what California
did a few years ago. But Kathy Hokll, to
her credit, just modeled a version of
what we did in the state. But you're
right. Uh Trump has just let it rip. He
has David Sachs no longer there. But I
think by the way they may have a little
regret. My sense is best and others are
like okay hold on here when mythos came
out.
>> Yeah.
>> Cyber security issues.
This is we're in a different space here.
It's not just about the clerical workers
which are geographically diffuse. So
it's really hard to look at white collar
displacement at the moment.
But now there's a growing I think
consciousness that we need to yes
accelerate visav China. I get all that
but you've got to steer the technology
particularly large language models on
the safety side transparency and that's
what California is trying to lead on has
been leading on just as we're dealing
across the board with you know digital
contracts around your likeness your
voice your writing uh and ownership in
that space. uh and we'll be very shortly
doing 16 and younger on social media, a
separate uh but connected issue. Um but
on the workforce side, we're just not
look if Daario is wrong at Anthropic who
says that within the next four and a
half years
50% of the entrylevel white collar
workers will be just think about if he's
wrong by half.
Just consider the consequences of that.
You saw Sam. These are the guys writing
the script and they're seeing into the
future. There's a reason why Peter Teal
struggled for 17 seconds on a simple
question around humanity surviving.
I mean, I don't want to be pessimist
here. I think there'll be a lot of
abundance, a lot of job creation. I
think there'll be a lot of classes of
jobs will be augmented. Nurses and
others and designers uh will be profound
and consequential. Uh, and I think
businesses are going to make a fortune
and that's why you cannot continue to
have a payroll tax system that taxes
jobs
and then subsidizes automation.
Um, and and so part of the EO is on that
side. We have tax credits for automation
and then we burden everyone every time
you hire someone with the damn payroll
tax. Again, the whole system has to be
reimagined and we're not I don't think
we're having those accelerated or
advanced conversations right now. We're
still discussing who's going to pay for
my increased electricity because of the
data center, which is a legit issue, but
it's not the issue. And you're right,
the tech genie is not going to go back
in the bottle. Just saying that you
should not or cannot build the data
center is not going to slow this
technology down. what can be will be
nature of technology.
And so we just have to steer it and not
make the mistakes we made with social
media. But we have to do a scale and
scope that we are not prepared for in
our national politics. And that's why
states matter. States are on the front
lines of the rights battle. States are
the front lines of these tectonic
changes. And that's why governors
matter, legislators matter. Uh that's
why our party needs to be bottom up, not
just top down. That's why we got to get
away from the guy or gal and the white
horse to come save the day in 2028
and focus on 2026 and getting speaker
Jeff the gavl and focus on
accountability and trust and then turn
the page on a compelling vision a
journey that we can go together American
people where everybody feels heard and
included some respects that's the easier
part of it as we continue to fight the
situation ational battles of the
corruption and the rot of our
institutions and the decay uh that
Donald Trump continues to promote on an
hourly and daily basis.
>> We're going to go to audience questions.
So, just type in your questions. We have
some already. I'll just ask one last
question. Um you you're right that
states are leading in many many
directions. Uh one way states are
leading are is in fiscal responsibility.
uh you just had a budget that uh
actually uh balances your budget um and
uh addresses structural deficits,
something we could do in the United
States. Um I wonder what you'd say, just
talk to us about the kind of invest
investments you've been able to make
while balancing your budget,
>> but also, you know, perhaps share some
thoughts on the deficit at the federal
level under Trump. Well, that's Look, I
I don't know. Maybe I'm a 80s kid or
something, but I was a little alarmed
when I saw the debt larger than GDP. Uh
well, maybe I'm a little oldfashioned.
You start to do the math. I do math all
the time. I spent two and a half hours
in my budget presentation. We balanced
not just for this year, but next year,
the year I'm gone. I believe you don't
have to be proflegate to be progressive.
And I'm incredibly proud. No other
state's done more in childare. Almost
half a million uh subsidized slots. Um,
I mentioned the work we have done in
terms of wages, not just the issues of
cost, the work we did with $11 insulin,
not subsidizing it, just lowering the
cost, using our market power to be more
competitive in the market place, which
is a mindset we have, universal
healthcare. We expanded it. I know it's,
you know, you don't have to support
this, but I campaign on it and I believe
in universal healthcare. And so, we
delivered it not just on the basis of
pre-existing condition, ability to pay,
but also on your immigration status.
Otherwise, we pay for it in the back end
in the emergency room. We were able to
broadly deliver on that. We were able
also create a brand new grade prek for
all. We created a hundred. This is I'm
really proud of this. Now it's 5.5
million child baby bonds. By the way, we
didn't name them accounts. I was an
idiot [laughter]
there. Yeah. Everyone's like, "Wow,
Trump accounts. What a great idea." I'm
like, "Jesus Christ." We 5.5 million of
these up to $1,500. By the way, that's
the these things. And by the way, Cory
Booker, hats off and even Ted Cruz for
being out there promoting. This is those
bonds will be I think incredibly
critical terms of the UBC framework and
the universe basic capital and looking
at compounding, looking at ownership. I
believe there is a structure there that
should be celebrated despite the name
which needs to change. Um, but we should
make sure we institutionalize that. But
my my whole point is we're forced to
balance budgets.
uh table stakes, but I'm also proud
we're able to do it. We have a
progressive tax system which I embrace.
I don't defend. I support. I promote it.
And I think that's the approach this
country needs to face. You and I were
talking about these four or five major
tax cuts
>> in the Bush and Trump. I mean, come on.
You talk about debt, look in the mirror,
CBO, is it 3.4 trillion 10 years or 4.7?
Depends on which CBO report I read. I
mean, it's madness. It's madness. We're
spending more on interest than we are
national defense. So this is not
sustainable entitlement issues and again
you talk about displacement white collar
workers and then start to look the
entitlement question. So debt and
entitlement energy climate change I'm
sorry I know it pulls at 2%. I'll keep
talking about it. You can have a debate
with a thermometer. I'm not going to.
And uh you know it's just it's a fi it's
financial risk climate risk. It's
uninsurable. You talk about housing, you
need to talk about climate. They're
connected. So, as we build all this
back, build that scaffolding. You're
right. States are on the front lines.
And uh you know, I I I think it's why
I'm very proud of CAP and the work
you're doing. And I'm proud that you
continue to remind us um that uh
governing matters.
>> Delivering results matter. Visual
results.
>> Our biggest failure in California was
the encampments. We weren't producing
visible results.
Unsheltered homelessness is down 9%, but
you don't feel that. First time in two
decades. Visible results. Results people
can see and feel. Increase wages, lower
costs, focus on mobility, housing, not
just wages, and radically alter our
system of taxation that simply is not
sustainable. our first trillionaires.
They're coming soon to a headline near
you, likely in a few months with SpaceX.
Trillionaires.
I mean, Plutarch reminded folks,
was it 2,000 years ago? 50 AD, longer
than that. The imbalance between the
rich and the poor is the oldest and most
fatal ailment of all republics.
businesses can't thrive in a world
that's failing.
>> And so we have to fundamentally address
that structure problem.
[applause]
>> Uh so we have a question. You've been
talking about the corruption story of
this administration, but how can we stop
corruption in future administrations?
How can you get polit politicians to tie
their own hands once they've seen what
this administration can
>> Yeah. There's the old adage once a mind
is stretched it never goes back to its
original form. Um so I understand that.
I mean seeing this corruption at scale
that creates a permission structure and
slip. Um but we we we we just simply
can't demand that our institutions need
to function again.
>> Um we need a functioning department of
justice, a functioning IRS, a
functioning FBI, not allow them to
become power ministries for the dear
leader which they've become. we need to
call all of this out. We need to hold
ourselves to a higher level of
accountability and expectation as well.
And so uh all of these things um will be
at play as we move forward. And uh and
so it's it's about action, it's also
about passion.
>> I think it was Oliver Wendel Holmes said
as life is action and passion. It's
required all us to share the action and
passion of our time at peril of being
judged not to have lived. I think the
fight matters.
A year ago,
my sense was in this country that our
path back as Democrats, weak and
ineffective are the two bubble words,
was through the center. I think there
may be some truth to that, but I think
increasingly I'd argue it's through the
fight.
And people want fighters. People want
people with conviction and clarity, not
ideologues. Open argument interested in
evidence. I don't think We are well
served by tearing other people down.
But calling out the the villains on a
tax code,
calling out the villains as it relates
to monopolization of capital, and I'm
sorry, that's a real issue. I I think we
would do very well talking as FDR talked
in 1944
about a new social combat. Talking about
a floor where no one falls below.
Talking to that blue collar and white
collar worker that are both asking the
same question. What happens when I do
fall? Will you be there to hold me up? I
think those fundamental truths and
values will be part of the comeback for
the Democratic party. But that comeback
starts with Speaker Jeff this November.
>> You're here [applause]
time for just one more question. In
light of America's worsening global
reputation, how should the United States
work to rebuild trust with our allies
and restore confidence in American
leadership? I saw you at the Munich
Security Conference where a lot of
leaders were asking you, leaders from
other countries were asking you those
questions as well as I know your remarks
at Davos.
>> Yeah, I was there because of that.
America is not. It's, you know, just
situational leader. Trump's temporary.
Trump's temporary. He is,
you know, I went there a little
selfishly saying California is
permanent.
Uh but we'll get through this and we'll
be repair in the spirit of father cause
my you great Jesuit priest that I
revered you know we'll Isaiah we have to
be repairs of the breach build truth and
trust back by showing up open hand not a
closed fist I I think the bar is pretty
damn low for the next president uh next
secretary of state uh as relates to
restoring uh our alliances I I know that
back to once a mind is stretched and
never goes back to original form. But I
Trump's an invasive species.
I don't see Trump Trumpism lasting
beyond Trump. Period. Full stop. It's a
cult of personality. With all due
respect, JD, you don't have it.
And um so I I I just am a little more
damn optimistic. As long as
we own up to our own complicity,
we've been too timid. It's not about
tinkering anymore. It's not about I
doubled the earned income tax credit. If
I given that speech, you're in trouble.
>> It's not about retraining and comm
This is something different. I'm sorry.
I don't know. I'm not going all or
Bernie on you or you see maybe I am a
little bit
you know in terms of understanding that
we're all Trump and Trumpism
understanding that you know it's it's
it's just it is remarkable
and it's you know and I'll end on this I
know we got to go
this the the anxiety is manifesting in
real despair for people. I mean, their
pessimism is pretty profound and that's,
you know, an AI, as I say, is going to
detonate that. And so, we have to
fundamentally understand that. And uh
and that's why as Democrats I uh this is
not, you know, I'm not here uh for
forgiveness, but
I I get why I was out there stomping for
Biden and I rever that man and uh will
have his back till my last breath. I do.
Um and I'll never regret a day out
there. But I was, you know, I was
defending the economyy's booming,
inflation's cooling, you know, best jobs
market since 1960s, lowest unemployment
for black women and Hispanics and
talking about industrial policy that's
worker centered and the four big, you
know, the but people weren't feeling it
and you know, Trump's making the same
damn mistake
and and it's because they weren't
experiencing it. We don't live in the
aggregate.
>> We don't. And so I'm out there
trumpeting 40% GDP growth, the fourth
largest economy in the world. It's like
>> I mean, we just said it was really good.
>> Yeah. No, thank [laughter] you. I I
appreciate that. Uh so I I think we we
started to buy our own story. We started
taking the wrong lessons from Biden's
first victory.
We didn't learn it. And so I just I feel
like we talk about forces of
transformation
>> versus the forces of restoration. Thank
you um Brownstein for that coining that
phrase. And that's really the dialectic.
Trump wanting to bring us back to a
pre-1960s world. That's what's happening
in real time. We saw with LGBTQ rights,
saw women's rights. Now we're seeing it
with civil rights and voting rights.
They want to bring us back to a
pre-1960s world. Censoring historical
facts rewriting history.
We need to be the party of
transformation. And we have to talk in
those terms but in a way that doesn't
alarm people.
>> And that that's the balance because
change is hard. Change not only has its
enemies but change
people
right now too much change. And so that's
going to be I think the dance and that's
the dance that I am here to celebrate
with you because CAP is one holding that
dance party and bringing the best and
brightest together so we can figure out
exactly what new ideas will animate a
new and fresh conversation in this
country. Thank you.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Please welcome CAP's senior vice
president for national security and
international policy Damian Murphy.
[music] Good afternoon folks. We're
going to reconvene for the next panel
here. Uh my name is Damian Murphy and I
lead CAP's national security team.
We've been inspired all morning
listening to visionary leaders outline
plans for a brighter future. In the
foreign policy community as well,
there's a growing consensus that we need
new solutions for a host of new
international challenges. Around the
world, tectonic plates are shifting in
historic ways. A new era of great power
competition is in full swing. and AI
could change everything from the job
market to how countries relate to each
other. In response to these challenges,
we need a bold foreign policy vision for
a safer, more prosperous, and healthier
world, guided by a core set of
principles and values. At CAP, we are
working to advance a new agenda, one
that responsibly uses American power
abroad to deliver real solutions for
people here at home.
With deep experience across our
government, our next panel is well
placed to help us think through some of
those solutions. We are honored and
excited to be joined by first, New
Jersey Senator Andy Kim, a strong voice
representing a new generation of
national security leaders in the United
States Senate. We're also joined by two
leaders with deep experience across
administrations.
former Secretary of State Anthony
Blinkin, who has navigated an array of
challenging international issues for
President Clinton, President Obama, and
President Biden. And finally, former
ambassador to the United Nations, Linda
Thomas Greenfield, a revered diplomat
who dedicated her career to protecting
the American people. Moderating our
panel will have MS Now's Jen Saki. Jen
served as White House press secretary
for President Biden, but for the
purposes of this panel, we applaud her
service as the State Department
spokesperson
um and during her time under the uh
under the Obama administration. So,
please join me in welcoming our panel to
the stage. Thank you. [applause]
[music]
Hi everyone. First of all, it we all
recognize it is difficult to follow
Governor Gavin Newsome in a conversation
about slush funds that included the
reference to knee pads. So, but we are
going to do our best because these are
very important topics too and obviously
there is so much going on in the world
right now. We're going to try to cover a
lot of it. Uh but we also the whole
purpose of this forum is to talk about
ideas and what to do in the future and
how we move forward. So we're going to
have a conversation about that too. But
I wanted to start with China because I
think this is a topic that is on a lot
of people's minds. It is always on a lot
of people's minds, but certainly after
the president just got back from a trip
to China last week. I wanted to start
with you, Secretary Blinken. Um you said
um you've done a lot of speeches. We
looked at a lot of your speeches. You
said if the United States is competing
with China alone, we may well wind up on
the losing side of the equation. Where
do you think the relationship stands
now? What is your go from here?
>> Well, thanks very much, Jen. It's great
to be with everyone, be with my friends
and colleagues as well. Look, I think we
have a president who divides the world
up into what he sees as spheres of
influence. And the big countries get to
do what they want in their part of the
world, and the smaller countries have to
suffer what they will. and that includes
China. And so other than some trade
issues that may affect us, uh his
inclination is to give them free reign
uh over their region uh and maybe even
uh a little bit beyond and I think we
saw that play out. Uh the challenge is
what happens within one sphere of
influence almost never stays there and
countries are always looking for more.
Uh and China is an example of that as
well. This is the one country that has
the capacity as well as the intent to
reshape the international system in a
way that advances its interests and
values and probably undermines ours. I
think Jen, as we're looking at it, we we
we have to resist putting it on a trying
to put it on a bumper sticker. There's
no neat way of summing up what is
probably the most complex and
consequential relationship. Uh we um we
compete for sure. We can test where we
really disagree and we have to find ways
to cooperate on issues that really uh
are in the interests of both of our
peoples. But from that perspective,
you've got to approach it from a
position of strength. And that means
making ourselves as strong as possible
at home with the right investments. But
it also means making ourselves as strong
as possible around the world, aligning
other countries, building convergence.
Because to the point you made, if we're
competing with China one-on-one, that's
a game that we may lose. Um, their
market's much bigger, their
manufacturing is three times our
manufacturing, purchasing power parody
greater than ours, more papers, more
patents, a bigger navy. You can go down
the list. But when we're aligned with
Europe, with Japan, with Korea, with
India, with Australia, with Canada, we
go from about 25% of world GDP to 50 or
60%. A lot harder for China to ignore.
Unfortunately, where we are now is just
as the president seems to be underwater
on a lot of issues within the United
States, we're underwater around the
world. There was a poll out a couple of
weeks ago, 130 countries, and what it
found was that China was seen as a more
credible actor than the United States.
Germany, 70% of people in one poll saw
the United States as an adversary. So
this means that our ability to align to
uh to build convergence in ways that can
deal with the challenges that China
poses has been vastly diminished. And
that's a real challenge going forward.
And that's sort of a perfect setup for
UN ambassador. I mean, everybody knows
who the ambassador is, but she spent not
just time um living up in the apartment
in New York engaging with other UN
ambassadors, but also decades uh serving
around the world in the foreign service.
And one of the things about these trips
is these countries, to your point,
countries around the world are
evaluating not just the United States,
but also the strength of the leader that
you're meeting with. I wonder if you're
thinking about how President Xi and
others other other um potential partners
and and some current allies that Tony
referenced look at this trip. How do
they look at this trip? And how do you
kind of repair these relationships and
try to rebuild that type of coalition
that he was referencing? Secretary
Blinken, I'm sorry. I worked with him
before. I'll keep calling him the
secretary. Go ahead.
>> I think Am I on? I think the entire
world was watching Trump's trip uh to
China and they were watching holding
their breaths because they knew that
whatever came out of this trip would not
be good for them.
And so they were waiting to see I mean
imagine the people of Taiwan
and what they are thinking. all of our
friends in Russ uh in in in Europe what
they were thinking. And I think even
more than anybody, the Russians were
watching this very closely because when
we were in New York, Russia and China
were friends without limits. They were
the bros. They kept very close uh
connections with each other. Now, China
has played a very interesting game and
and and and Trump where now we we are
talking to the Chinese about things that
the Russians might feel uncomfortable
about. So, we're seeing the uh pieces of
the chessboard moving around in ways
that has all the pawns uh feeling
uncomfortable. You know, what is Africa?
We're telling Africa, you need to make
some choices
uh about what you want to see in your
future. And they're being forced into
making choices related to China because
again, I think they find China much more
trustworthy as a partner than uh the
United States. How this will boil down
or what it will boil down to in in the
UN remains to be seen. But I think
China's uh prowess, its power, its
leadership uh at in on the multilateral
stage is increasing.
>> Senator, part of our objective today is
to certainly talk about the path forward
and you know in in terms of building
strength here at home and building these
relationships, it requires tough choices
at home at times. There has been
bipartisan support, for example, of
something that the ambassador
referenced, which is supporting Taiwan.
Uh we don't know where that stands
exactly right now. What are the tough
choices you think Congress and other
leaders need to make over the next
couple of years in order to position
this relationship in a more constructive
way?
>> Well, one thing that I think was
absolutely spoton is talking about
strength, talking about credibility that
the ambassador and secretary talked
about. But I want to throw one more word
into the mix here that I hear a lot from
foreign leaders. I had this one leader
of an Asian country call me and talk
about just the the challenges that they
see when it comes to USChina and just at
large with foreign policy. And they said
I they said to me, they just said, "I
want you to know that when we talk about
America, we ask this question. Is
America a reliable country?" And we know
the answer to what that is. And and I I
so I want to just really throw out that
sense of reliability that how important
that is and how much we are struggling
with it and why we will continue to
struggle as a country even after Trump
is gone. And this is something that
we're going to have to rebuild. So when
we're thinking through in Congress, how
are we making these tradeoffs? We also
have to be thinking about the importance
of credibility of reliability uh in
terms of what we're actually able to put
forward even when we're talking about
some of our strategic advantages. For
instance, all of us agree that we need
to be thinking closely about how our
chip manufacturing and other types of AI
tools are so critical to the economy of
the future. But how are we able to tell
other countries what we think they
should be doing when it comes to chips
or manufacturing equipment if we don't
even know what the White House is going
to do when it comes to chips to China
and elsewhere? You know, when we're
talking about, you know, all these
different tools at our disposal, you
know, the problem is really whether or
not we will be consistent with that. and
seeing over the course of my time in
Congress how Republicans had one tune on
China for the past few years and then
all of a sudden are absolutely silent
right now. I mean, not a single one
talking to me about anything that they
were concerned about over the past few
years. It really just shows how much
Trump has captured the Republican party
on China. and we're no longer able to
talk about this with the strategy that
is necessary for what is the most
defining competition of our generation.
>> Another area where there seems to have
been some capturing, shall we say, is on
the war with Iran where there still has
not been a war powers vote that has
passed. It's come close. You've killed
off some people. But let me ask you,
Secretary Blinken, right now I think
everybody would like to see this war
come to a close. Um you can certainly
tell us how that's going to happen if
you know. But what do you see as the the
impact of of what we're looking at right
now? Um both not just with Iran but in
the region um and just kind of US's role
in the world 3 years, 5 years, 10 years
from now.
>> Well, I I think Jen, we we have an
example here with Iran uh of a war of
choice that never should have happened
and a war that really sends a almost a
split screen. You can have tactical
success in individual areas and yet have
a real strategic failure. And that's
where we are because at the end of the
day when the dust settles it's likely
that Iran will retain some vestigages of
its nuclear program. Uh it will
certainly retain a lot of uh missiles.
Apparently they haven't in fact been
destroyed. It will retain its regime and
it will have gained this incredible
leverage that it didn't have before in
the straight of Hormuz where it will one
way or another more or less control what
happens there because it will retain the
ability to mess with shipping that's
going through. And that means even even
in a small way, if one guy with a
shoulder fired missile can damage a
ship, all of a sudden the ships get
scared, the insurers get scared, and
you've got a real problem, which means
they're going to be in on the deal going
forward. That radically changes the
region, and it's going to take time to
work out from that. It's you're going to
have to find ways over time to work
around the hold that Iran will have on
the straight by building more pipelines.
not the the best thing, but it's
probably the necessary thing to do,
especially by focusing on renewables uh
and other ways so that people are not uh
under the the thumb of the Iranians, and
it really doesn't take much. But it's
reshaped it in other ways, too. Uh we've
alienated pretty much everyone in doing
this. We've alienated the Europeans
because we were kicking dirt in their
face for two years over NATO, over
Greenland, over Denmark, you name it.
Didn't tell them about this. And then
when the going got tough, we said, "Hey,
we need you." and all of a sudden they
weren't so eager to do it. Our partners
in Asia, uh, they're the ones who've
been on the receiving end of the the
real brunt of this in terms of the
immediate impacts of prices and
availability. And in a different way,
our partners in the Gulf who, to Andy's
point, have seen how unreliable we are.
Unlike the Europeans, unlike our
Asia-Pacific partners, some of them
would like the United States to quote
unquote finish the job. That's not
happening. So, they're frustrated.
Others feel like they've now been
subjected to Iran's wrath. Iran has
fired more missiles and projectiles at
the UAE than it's fired at Israel in
this conflict. It's radically changed
the equation. I think there is an
off-ramp. Um but the president's going
to have to decide whether he wants to
take it. And the offramp involves guess
what? Diplomacy and a compromise. The
only two times the Iranians have made a
deal in the past were to end the war
with Iraq that went on for eight years
with 200,000 Iranian dead. the UN came
in, offered them a way forward, got the
Iraqi troops out of uh out of Iran. The
only other time, the JCPOA, the Iran
nuclear deal that President Obama
negotiated, it took two and a half years
to get it. They were given some things.
We got a lot and we're in a much better
place as a result. I think right now, if
the president's looking at this, you're
going to have to have some kind of
arrangement that maybe down blends some
of their highlyenriched uranium. um
probably has a moratorum on enrichment
for some period of time. That would be a
good thing. Um and on the straight of
Hormuz, there'll probably be some kind
of tolling system, which no one will
want to call by its name, where the
proceeds are used for reconstruction of
countries in the area that have been
damaged. That's a lot to swallow because
so much damage done for so little gain.
Is there a scenario, ambassador, where
this war ends and the Iranians don't
have some control over the straight of
Hormuz, some financial control? Do you
think that's possible?
Honestly, I don't. It'll be difficult to
get to. And part of the reason it will
be difficult is again, we're not
negotiating with them. Why are we not
negotiating with him? We don't have
people to do it.
uh we don't have confirmed Senate uh
Senate confirmed ambassadors in over a
100 countries. So, who is going to
negotiate with the Iranians? And I've
heard over and over again, Tony, you've
dealt with them that they are
extraordinary negotiators. Uh we had
extraordinary negotiators. We don't
anymore. uh in in Africa where maybe we
want to get some support uh 37 countries
do not have ambassadors.
Uh so the administration is taking the
power that it has and dumping it and so
it's in a position where it is not able
to negotiate an agreement that would
quickly end this uh uh end this war. I
think the only thing that will do it,
the president will declare victory uh
which means he has accepted defeat uh
and uh move uh and move out of uh the
areas saying we've accomplished
everything we've accomplished when we
know that he has not.
Senator Kim, when when you just follow
some of the headlines, you see kind of
war powers vote, war powers vote, war
powers vote failing week after week.
There have been some individuals peeled
off I I should say who have voted um
with a with Democrats um for a war
powers act which hasn't happened I
should say in quite a long time. What
give us a sense of where you see things
right now in that regard? Are there
other ways that you think there is a
bipartisan opportunity to hold um people
in this administration to account over
this war? Well, first of all, I want to
say that even the war powers approach,
this is the wrong approach that we
should have been going down. This is not
a situation where we should normalize
the idea that a president can start a
war on their own and then it's
>> very important point and then it's up to
Congress later to to disapprove of it.
Right? So, just from the outset, this is
wrong. This is an illegal
unconstitutional war. Now, we are
unfortunately in a situation where we do
not have three functioning branches of
government right now. We have one branch
of government that is simply trying to
dominate the other two branches of
government. I often call Speaker Johnson
Secretary Johnson because he acts more
like a cabinet secretary than he does as
a leader of a separate branch of
government. So, that's the world that
we're in right now. So, yes, we're
trying to operate with the tools that we
can to shine light and draw attention to
the American people, who by the way
fully see this for what it is. You know,
when I'm back home in in Jersey, I mean,
across the political spectrum, nobody
likes this war. A and they understand
just the cost that they are bearing.
Over 42 billion dollars more that
Americans have spent on gas and diesel
since the beginning of this war. you
know that's what we are trying to draw
attention to that drum beat. So we have
to make sure that we're not getting
caught up on just the process of you
know the between the different branches
of government. this is ultimately about
the people and this is ultimately about
the impacts that is having on them and
that this is a choice that this
president made not just to start a war
or not but whether to help American
people or not and that he has clearly
made a decision to enrich himself and
his uh family and his friends at the
expense of the American people and they
see that so clearly when it comes to
Iran.
>> I'm so glad you took the question in
that direction. It was spicy and good.
um ambassador um you have spent so much
time working in so many parts of the
world where there are high levels of
corruption where human rights and and
and you and that is a key talking point
when you sit down with these leaders
when you when people let's say in the
future when future ambassadors future
secretaries are going into meetings and
they are looking at a past
administration that financially
benefited to the tune of $1.4 4 billion.
Not my numbers, numbers that have been
widely reported. Uh, and more. What
impact does that have on the
conversations?
>> Uh, it makes us look like hypocrites.
Uh, it is a very hard conversation uh to
have with a foreign government where you
know you're talking to them about
corruption in their country and they're
going to talk back to you about what's
happening in your country. I think the
only thing that will get us through this
when there's an a change of
administration that we hold those uh
people accountable. If we hold them
accountable then we can go to other
countries and say yes [applause] we had
this problem but accountability is
important and this is what we're doing
to hold them accountable. Now will that
happen? I I don't know. But I would have
a hard time having that conversation now
with any uh country uh because I would
feel like a hypocrite even though I feel
strongly that corruption in government
is is bad. Uh but to try to tell a
country that from this side of the
Atlantic would be hard.
I want to turn, this is going to seem
like a sharp turn, but I don't feel like
there's nearly enough attention always
on the war in Ukraine because of the war
with Iran, because of corruption,
because of all the other issues. And
Secretary Blinken spent so much time as
Secretary of State helping build
coalitions, as did as did the
ambassador, of course. Um, if you were
to strip away the headlines about
Russia, about Ukraine, about military
battles, what should people in this room
or people watching really understand
about the state of things? We're we're
now four years into this war.
>> So, Jen, I think two things. First, it's
always good to remember why we got into
this in the first place, why we were so
determined in our support for Ukraine,
because of course it was an aggression
against a country and one big country
aggressing a smaller country. No one
likes to see that and that tugs on the
heartstrings. But there was something
else going on. It was an aggression
against the very principles at the heart
of an international system, no matter
how challenged. Uh that really mattered
and mattered in working to keep the
peace, working to help countries advance
and develop and principles like
sovereignty, like independence, like
territorial integrity. That was the goal
of the Russian uh aggression as much as
it was to erase Ukraine and subsume it
into Russia. And that's why we were so
invested in it. Um but right now what
we've seen is something quite remarkable
which is a country of amazing
resilience. A country that now even with
the United States receding in the role
that it was playing is still holding its
own. Now Europe has stepped up in ways
that uh are really really important
including with funding that uh is so
necessary. But you see the Ukrainians on
the battlefield holding their own at
horrific cost. Horrific cost to them to
their civilians and citizens. also at
horrific costs to the people that Putin
continues to throw into this meat
grinder of his own making. But they are
holding on and more than holding on.
They're actually taking the fight to
Russia. So I don't think that line is
likely to move very much. Um they're
holding their own economically and
they're building a new economy again
with help from Europe and from others.
And the interesting thing is with their
defense industry and what they're doing
with drones, they may well wind up at
the heart of Europe's future defense
industry, they have technology and they
have techniques that we don't have. Uh,
and we see that being spread uh around
the world and then step by step they
continue to build their democracy
getting closer to Europe um
strengthening the tools. You've seen
many people who were in high positions
now being challenged on what we were
just talking about corruption. So I
think right now my hope is that the
pressure on Putin is such it's finally
catching up with him. He had a reprieve
with Iran and being able to sell some
oil and the higher prices, but
everything else across the board in
Russia is really turning. And he's built
a war economy that worked for a while
but now is feeding on itself because
basically everything that economy is
producing with everything going into the
defense sector is being eaten up and
it's not productive. It's one thing if
you build a weapon system that gets
destroyed a few weeks later. It's
another thing if you're investing in
roads and bridges and technology. So, I
think we're in a place where if we can
help in some fashion the Ukrainians to
hang on, it'll get to a place where the
line is more or less frozen. And the
real measure of success is can Ukraine
stand on its own feet militarily,
economically, democratically. They're
demonstrating that they can do that.
>> Let me ask you, Senator, to one of uh
the secretary's points he just made. I
mean, Ukraine, it's become sort of a
laboratory for intelligence and drones
and kind of a different way of warfare.
Once we get to a point of past the
Secretary of Maximum Lethality, as I'll
just call him, and we're in kind of a
future point, what lessons do you think
can be taken away from this war? And
what do you hope that Congress is
applying?
>> Well, I I'll take it in two directions.
First and foremost, yes, absolutely.
This is showing this new era of warfare
that we're in right now. You know, I I'm
somebody that grew up in the era where
we were concerned about weapons of mass
destruction. Now we are finding
ourselves in a place where we are trying
to navigate these weapons of mass
production. you know this idea of what
it is when you're able to produce such
quantity whether drones ballistic
missiles uh when we have the
proliferation of AI what we see with
mythos and other things like that that
are going to completely transform that
is the future and we do have to be
thinking about it both in terms of the
war fighter on our side but also how do
you defend against this and this is why
I was also going over you know some of
our efforts to make sure that we as a
nation are ensuring that we are able to
do our best to ensure that our
adversaries and our competitors like
China and Russia are not able to gain
some of these tools whether through AI
chips or the means of production to be
able to produce those chips. You know,
those are the types of things that are
going to really determine the
stratification of uh warfare in that
way. The last thing I'll just say on
this front is I I've been very much
pushing that we we can't just be saying
that we're opposed to this might makes
right approach of foreign policy of
Trump but trying to devise what is our
way forward and I for one believe that
that revolves around a singular word
which is resilience. I think we need to
focus on an era of resilience in this
age of crisis and to be able to mobilize
ourselves to shore up our own
vulnerabilities, whether that's critical
minerals or pharmaceuticals or energy
production or any number of other issues
while we are also trying to make sure
that we are performing and and fighting
on the battlefields of our choosing and
be able to advance on our strengths. So
that's what I think we need to be
pushing forward on when we see this
incredibly rapidly changing ecosystem
that we're in. You know, there's no
going back. We need that forward-looking
vision and to be able to give a sense of
what American credibility and
reliability going forward will be based
off of.
>> Okay, we only have five minutes left,
but we've covered a scope of issues I
hope all of you cared a lot about. Let
me go to you, Ambassador. I one of the
things I I would say broadly is if I
were to give unofficial broad advice to
anybody running for office or president,
I would say sit down with really smart
people and decide what you think about
the really tough issues. So let me pose
this question to you. What do you hope
that people who are aspiring to be
sitting in the Oval Office are sitting
down and spending time mapping out plans
and ideas and thoughts with very smart
people with right now? Uh, I hope that
they are doing that and I actually know
I expect that they're sitting down with
smart people. But what they really need
to do is sit down with the people. They
need to get into communities, go into
towns, go into capitals and talk to the
people because these it's ordinary
people in places like Louisiana who will
be voting for them. And if those people
are not hearing from them, nothing that
smart people say to them will get them
elected.
>> What do you wish they would be talking
about?
talking about real issues, talking about
uh pocketbook issues, talking about the
price of gasoline,
uh talking about their futures, uh
whether their children will have jobs,
whether their children will be educated,
whether their school boards will be able
to pull books like Roots out of the
library uh and and stick with it. you
know, they want to hear those issues
that touch them every day. They don't
want to hear the esoteric issues about
war and peace, even though those issues
have an impact on them. Uh they expect
their leaders to know what to do on
those issues, but they want their
leaders to know what to do to make their
lives better.
Secretary Blinken, let me ask you the a
question in a different way because you
have you have helped um past people
running for president think about issues
and and kind of red team with them what
they think, how to talk about it. What
would be top of list for you if you were
doing that with a some candidates right
now?
>> You know, there's so much to uh to think
about uh to to focus on. I guess I'd say
a few things. one is, and it it it
echoes what uh Andyy's saying and I
think what Linda is saying, um there's a
lot of understandable nostalgia for the
past because we had an American century.
We had 80 years where as a result of the
work that previous generations did, we
were at the the front of the parade and
shaping things. And those 80 years, with
all of their imperfections, profound as
they were, um we passed that. And the
reality is you can't put the genie back
in the bottle. You've got to shape a new
bottle. And that's what these
conversations have to all be about. We
have a pace and scope of change that is
moving at speeds unlike anything I ever
experienced before in my 30 years in
government. Uh and just by way of one
example, to get to 50 million users of
the telephone back in the day, it took
about 75 years. For radio, it took about
45 years. For TV, it took about 20
years. For Instagram, four years. for
chat GTP four months. The the challenge
that anyone in governance uh has in
dealing with that is acute. We have
inequalities among countries that have
actually decreased but within them
they've increased and that has all sorts
of repercussions. But finally, and this
is what I want to get to, we have a new
world order that is that's being shaped
and grappling with that is going to be
the biggest test internationally for the
for future presidents. We have all sorts
of emerging actors who are powered,
super empowered by technology and by
information and as a result can either
advance or disrupt things in ways that
they weren't able to before. And that
means if you don't have them on the
takeoff, you're probably going to have a
crash landing. So, as I'm looking
forward and I'm thinking about how do
you how do you advise a a president on
how to engage the world? Of course, it
starts with our democratic uh base and
you want strong democracies. I believe
that one principle is enduring and that
is enlightened self-interest. The
strength and success of others actually
redounds to us and that continues to be
important. American engagement and
leadership continues to be important.
But as we're looking at the way the
world is going to be designed, I think
increasingly we're going to see
alignments of not just countries but
companies and other actors that have a
stake in a given issue coming together
around that issue. And it's what I used
to call variable geometry. different
coalitions of different shapes and sizes
who are all brought together by a shared
interest in a particular issue. Maybe
it's dealing with opioids. Maybe it's
dealing with food security. Maybe it's
dealing with climate. Maybe it's dealing
with AI governance. And it won't be a
neat autocracy democracy breakdown or
east west or north south. It'll be
like-minded on a given issue willing to
play by the same set of rules. I think a
president has to look at that and think
about how he or she organizes the
country to engage in that. But it starts
with as we've all been discussing uh
regaining our credibility and that's
going to be the first task.
>> It's a perfect place to end. I'm very
grateful that they are all thinking
about these big difficult issues that I
know are on the minds of lots of people
here and people watching. Thank you all
so much uh for this panel. Really
enjoyed it.
Heat up
>> [music]
>> here.
[music]
>> [music]
>> And I want to give a heartfelt thanks to
Prime Minister Carney [music] for
joining this year's summit. Our age of
anxiety, it can only be answered by
positive action.
>> Many of us gathered in Barcelona a few
weeks ago
>> and before that last year we gathered in
London.
>> The truth is we won't solve our problems
if we don't also take on the root causes
>> to discuss not only our shared
challenges but our shared opportunities.
[music] a new path forward.
>> International rules-based order that we
helped build together no longer works as
it once claimed. We have to take the
sign down and build a new
The prime minister of Hungary is no
longer called Victor Orban. That's for
the first time in 16 years.
>> In times like these progressives do not
retreat. We show [music] here the
progressive forces of this world stand
together and united.
Progressives should make the reform of
our democracy our number one priority.
I'm just trying to purge our vocabulary
of pretty much anything that starts with
the prefix [music] re like restore,
rebuild, most of all return because it's
not going to be like that and it
shouldn't.
>> We have to [music] deliver for our
public. Our foreign policies have to
serve the economic well-being of our
countries. [music]
>> We're responsible for our own futures as
center-left advocates. If we are
delivering or not delivering, that is
what matters. We met today for the first
time. But you see that we are fighting
for the same vision.
>> No country can go it alone. And we know
that when progressives are in power,
multilateralism thrives and we can get
big things done.
>> The future is bright when you have
leaders who are focused on delivering.
So thank you
[music]
>> [snorts]
>> Please welcome the New York Times Ezra
Klene and MS Now's Chris Hayes.
[music]
Hello everyone. Um I'm Chris. This is
Ezra. Um, we're going to be speaking
about an incredibly overlooked
bespoke topic today. It's called uh
artificial intelligence,
often abbreviated as AI. Um, it is
strange how ubiquitous the topic has
become and how quickly ubiquitous it's
become. And the dynamics right now, I
think from the perspective political
economy and politics are both incredibly
fascinating and incredibly fraught. The
polling suggests that people are there
is a genuine backlash that's brewing.
You're seeing it both in quantitative
data in polling but also in individual
fights over data centers particularly
where this has been channeled. At the
same time, a shocking percentage of US
uh capital expenditure, business
investment, and the driver of GDP growth
is located in a relatively small few
hands that are controlling what is the
largest at this point um percentage of
GDP investment the country's probably
ever seen, even surpassing the numbers
of the railroad buildout in the late
19th century, which was the previous
record holder. And amidst this, a real
question about what the two parties,
what the political coalitions and what
the political positions, both from a
political standpoint in campaigning and
from a governing standpoint uh are
calling for. And so we thought we would
try to just solve all that in the next
28 minutes and 34 seconds. Um I guess my
first question to you is like what's
your I do think there's a real jump ball
now. Um, I saw Ron DeSantis today posted
on X a poll that showed people
overwhelmingly opposed to data centers
and he has been clearly kind of making
some noises around being a sort of AI
skeptic. How do you read the politics of
it broadly?
>> So, I think the politics of it are bad
um on a bunch of different levels for
everybody. I I'm gonna pull Dantis to
the side as I often try to do in life
and just like start with one big
principle like the main thing that I
wanted to come here today and say which
is that what AI is and whether it is
good or bad is not an intrinsic
structure of the technology but is a set
of political decisions. it is up to us.
And one of the things I mean by that is
right now I think particularly on the
Democratic side but also on the
Republican side there's a tremendous
amount of correct concern about what I
would call AI harm and a set of
questions about how to create an agenda
around AI harm. What about job
displacement? What about algorithmic
bias? And the way AI has not just been
sold, but genuinely I think one of the
possible futures it could represent, but
the one that the heads of the labs
talked about for a very long time and
that people listened to them was AI as a
technology for taking away your job and
maybe eventually displacing human
sovereignty over our own future. And now
you started to hear people in the AB say
AI has a marketing problem, a branding
problem. [laughter]
But if it does that, it's an actual
problem. That's a bad, terrible vision.
The there needs to be a set of policies
and people are thinking hard about these
that are around preventing harms. There
also need to be a set of policies that
are around creating and harnessing
goods.
the things that are promised to us from
AI that actually seem genuinely
plausible to me like for instance a
radical acceleration in the rate of
useful molecules to test in drug
discovery are not going to lead to new
drugs if we don't change how the drug
discovery process works and change how
the financing of it works so it can
happen much much much faster right this
is true in energy it is true in how the
government uses AI it would be trivial
now for for the IRS to have a large
language model that does your taxes for
you and in a way direct file wasn't
capable of doing goes back and forth
even on complex taxes but then you have
to actually make that happen and so
there needs to be I think both like
agenda to prevent AI harm but an agenda
to force and make possible AI goods and
the technology what it means for society
back and forth whether it is good or bad
it has been treated as if it is out of
our hands a non-political question, but
it is a political question. And if the
only thing you do is try to prevent
harms from these labs racing for profit
as fast as it can, of course, you're not
going to get a great outcome out of that
for it to have the for AI to actually
work for the public good. The there will
have to be an agenda in which the public
decides what it wants and then shapes
the market and shapes the the rules and
shapes the reality around that. Yeah, I
I 100% agree on that. Although I would
say that I do think I don't think the
technology has an inherent veilance
necessarily, but I also think it's not
neutral in this sense. Like one of the
things I think a lot in comparing it to
the internet, which you know, we're
always searching for analoges for it.
But there's a few things about the
internet that I think shaped
particularly the first few decades of
it, even if that's now vestigial. One is
that it was architecturally it was
distributed. The whole point of it was
to be distributed and the whole point of
that distribution of a distributed
network um which comes out of ARPANET
and sort of resilience in the face of a
nuclear attack or something like that
meant that the sort of distributed
nature of it as a set of open source
protocols as a set of ways that
different people can interact with it um
gave a kind of generative space for lots
of different people to kind of plug into
it. One of the things that really
strikes me about AI right now from a
sort of political economy perspective is
that inherent in the technology in the
current way it's being developed is you
need just an enormous raw amount of
power and GPUs that that necessarily
right now and that it may change right
because we might get different models
that don't work this way that that
necessarily depends on concentrated
power and very deep pockets with a few
firms and so I do worry a little bit
about like the degree just from a like
from the sort of political economy of
this new technology where it feels
whatever it benefits might be for people
the concentration feels kind of baked
into me like it feels like a very
nondistributed kind of thing it feels
ultimately also not that competit even
though it's competitive among these
three or four models right this sense
that there's going to be a few winners
that it'll be you know that it's going
to be dominated maybe by winner take all
and that's the thing that I keep coming
back to about the regulatory question is
like how to think about the market
structure in terms of what the
government's doing if that's the
inherent nature of the tech.
>> Let me poke maybe or push on that in two
ways. So one again I think that's a
choice and sometimes reflects the
way that even on the democratic side
there has been a real limitation in
imagination of what the public can do.
If you could have a public option for
health insurance run by the government,
there's no particular reason the
government couldn't have GPU clusters
>> 100%.
>> And in other countries, they will.
>> It is a reflection, I think, of the way
we have severed correct ourselves off
from having
>> powerful public options in this country
that we almost don't even like think
about it. It's like, well, it turns out
we can run libraries. Bookstores don't
just have to be private. like why
couldn't we do that and I bet you in
some cases a military will I mean the
one part of the government that is
thinking more like this is a national
security state the other thing here is
that
what you're saying about concentration
of power might be true and it is
definitely the story the leading AI labs
want us to believe because they want the
investors to believe that too. So the
the sort of implicit story sometimes
explicit told by anthropic told by open
AI told by um Google Alphabet is that we
are in a limited period race to
recursive recursively self-improving
super intelligence and whoever wins that
race is going to win everything. And
maybe I don't totally push that out as a
kind of, you know, in my view sort of
low probability event. But there's
another view which is that there's
actually not much moat on this stuff at
all. like how did Grock, whatever else
you think about Elon Musk, come
functionally out of nowhere to have not
not be the leading model on the market,
but be a couple of months behind the
leading models on the market when it
didn't start anywhere near as early as
OpenAI as Google where the foundational
research was done as meta which had you
know Yan Lun who was one of the founders
it there are a lot of people I know in
the VC world who think there's actually
no moat on this stuff at all
>> that in fact we're getting really really
good at it and the reason China is so
close to us is you can distill the
models pretty easily which is only to
say that I don't think it is baked in
like a lot of what is going to create
concentrations of power if they happen
or one I do take your point about GPUs
and the amount of money you need to
train but we could approach that with
public options and other things but the
other thing is the ability to switch
between things and go to new players if
we make entrance easier is is pretty
real there. So again, I I keep wanting
us to I don't mean to say the technology
is neutral. I don't believe any
technology is truly neutral. They all
have embedded ideas in them and embedded
pathways in them, but I do think that
there's been a tendency to treat the
technology as almost self-directed
>> as opposed to being genuinely
uh amenable or shaped by political
choices and public choices which give us
the public agency over it. So there's
let's let's talk about two different
ways of conceiving. I mean there's a
bunch of different layers at which you
could imagine policy here. Um one is in
this question about market structure,
right? Whether that's competition policy
or whether that's some sort of public
option. The other way that you could
conceive of it is regulatory oversight,
right? Like to the point that you were
saying before about the way our
imagination about the possibilities of
public the public sector and also public
public regulation have kind of been
cramped. You know, when you take a step
back and think about the enormous amount
of technical capacity necessary for a
central bank and the or the FDA or the
FTC or the SEC and we can go down the
line, right? Or the Nuclear Regulatory
Commission. In all these cases, you've
got you've got something that's very
technically complex and sophisticated.
It's possibly very dangerous, whether
it's nuclear weapons or uh depressions,
and you don't want to basically have a
vote of Congress on interest rates and
where to store the nukes, right? So
you've got some kind of question where
you want some level of democratic
oversight and democratic accountability
and also technical expertise and the
creation of this enormous
sort of ecology of the administrative
state that grows up to deal with
precisely this problem. And there's like
more of these than most people who've
never worked in government even know.
Like there's all sorts there's like
three different railroad commissions
that are appointed and when you come
into a new administration you get a you
know there's a spreadsheet that has all
these positions you have to fill and
most people have never heard of a lot of
these bodies. It's not I mean that seems
to me like an obvious model for AI right
like there's there's some sort of way
that we could conceive of some balance
between democratic accountability
technical expertise that says like
whether a model is safe or not right
whether it could be released or not.
We're so far from that conversation now,
but that seems like one obvious place,
again, this is at the highest level that
you could at least conceptually think of
what some approach would look like. I
>> I want to drop a lower beneath that, a
layer beneath that.
What do we want this technology to do?
How do we want the future to be
different than the present?
That until we have some set of views on
that, right? If you want, if what you
hope AI does, there are people in my
life who have currently incurable
chronic diseases.
One way artificial intelligence could
make my life much better is accelerate
cures for those diseases. What would
need to happen, not just in the
development of it, but in the financial
incentives it has, and then in the way
we we test and accelerate drugs to make
that happen and happen quickly for as
many diseases as possible. that there
are a lot of different things that
technology because it is a general
purpose technology can do or not do. You
were asking earlier about analogies. The
internet is maybe one. I think energy is
probably a better one. That
energy is not like a railroad. We know
we want there to be a railroad
infrastructure. What the railroad is
meant to do is like pretty
straightforward energy. We are sort of
trying to wire energy into everything.
But in order to make that useful, you
have to wire things for energy, right?
It's classic, you know, economic history
now that it took a long time for the
gains of electricity to actually show up
in the economy because people didn't
know how to use it. And so the very fact
of it being in some way available
doesn't matter if your factory is not
built for electricity. One of the things
that I see happening right now when I go
out to San Francisco and do this
reporting and and Chris has been doing a
great podcast um series focused on AI as
well is I am watching companies that are
building themselves from the ground up
to use this well. Their code bases are
internally unified. Their Slack messages
like work in a very different way
because they're making their entire
organization legible to artificial
intelligence. So then the artificial
intelligence can be more useful to the
organization. If you want to go a step
further than what they're attempting to
do, which is accelerate their coding, if
you want to make it more possible to do
what Governor Nome was saying on the
stage a bit ago and build more things
more effectively, more rapidly, and new
kinds of things in the real world, then
you have to begin to wire the world. You
have to begin to reconstruct how we
build. Right now, we have trouble in a
lot of places building homes. Homes are
a solved technology. We're not lacking
capacity. We're not lacking innovation
here. If we want to create new things,
that's even harder. And so I I really
want to hold on this question because I
think there's a a tendency in the the
the Democratic, the progressive, the
liberal, the leftist mind to fit it into
the fights we've been having, to fit it
into competition policy. That's fine. I
want competition and AI. At the moment,
I broadly think we have it to fit it
into regulatory policy because I think
we still think we failed on social media
by not regulating the harms quickly
enough.
That's good. It we I want to do all of
that. I am genuinely worried about AI
harms. I've been covering them for years
now. But if we do not actually create
like a set of ideas about what we want
to achieve, we're just not going to
achieve them because all of the energy
and all the investment to your point
about these companies who are having to
pay back investors over time is going to
go into what there's already a business
model to do. And so the public has no
view. what the public wants done is
never going to happen,
>> right? But part of that is if we sort of
go back to the experience people have
had of the economy like I always I love
the Kane's essay about the economic
prospects of our grandchildren and
returned to a lot and wrote about in my
last book. Um and you know it's fun
because there's a certain kind of
utopian thinking. It's not utopian
because he actually thinks there's going
to be a lot of challenges. But, you
know, and you go back to the Markx uh
portion where he talks about how you can
be like a fisher in the morning and a
critic in the evening and a hunter in
the afternoon and you're none of those
things because in this era of plenty,
right? When you've gotten rid of
fundamentally when you've gotten rid of
limitations, which is the problem that
he thought he was solving for and that
Kanes thinks that 20th century
capitalism will solve for, right? That
no one has to work anymore. And I think
if you were to articulate a kind of pie
in the sky vision, well, okay, what
happens if you can if the computers can
do all if the if they can do all the
thinking and they could push out the
productivity frontier big enough and we
can get rocket growth, right? That money
is going to flow somewhere and maybe we
all get to be who who's the guy who says
we all get to be lords, right? like we
all become essentially the kind of
lordly class that used to exist in
feudal systems when a very very small
percentage of people didn't have to do
any work at all because all the work was
being done for them. I think the problem
is and maybe that's not the vision that
you would articulate but that's one
vision right like the sort of
>> I'm not going for for indolent lords
[laughter]
>> like maybe if there's some universe of
sort of boundless abundance and
boundless plenty and people don't have
to like work jobs they hate anymore
which an enormous percentage of people
in our society do.
I just think it it just seems so
impossible to conceive that that even if
you gave like a slightly less utopian,
you know, curing diseases or things like
that, it's hard to get your arms around
like what the bounty looks like because
people just don't trust it will be
allocated to them. This is why I really
think that it is time for the AI
discussion to get off of far future
thought experiments.
And look, I have participated in a lot
of them in my time and I've talked about
paperclip maximizing and boundless
abundance and the whole and the whole
lot of it. And when AI was a speculative
technology, it was worth talking about
to at least as a way to to discipline
your own intuitions about it.
We are here. The technology is here. Its
pace of improvement is unknown. I am not
really of a belief that we're going to
be in super intelligence in two years.
We are not coming to boundless uh
abundance anytime soon in my view. We
are not going to be at mass job
displacement anytime soon if ever in my
view. I mean I think it's not going to
happen for the same reason Kanes was
wrong and that we will endlessly create
new wants, new desires, new forms of
social status competition which doesn't
mean we will not have some job
displacement. One of my views about AI
which is like a little bit weirder to be
to to be honest is that in a way society
we would be better at dealing with 80
million people losing their jobs than 8
million because if it's 80 million like
co we would do a societywide response.
We would not blame people. But if it's 8
million we're going to blame them. We're
going to say you communications major.
Well look most people the communications
major is still getting a job. It's just
that unemployment in that major has gone
up 3x. You should figure it out. And
that's when we I mean we did this in the
China shock. We've done this in a lot of
cases and it actually worries me a lot
more. I think we have been so caught on
these big thought experiments. 50% of
all entry-level white collar jobs gone
in two to three years that we're gonna
actually be caught unprepared by being
faced again as we so often are with the
same problems we always run into which
is bottlenecks for doing real things in
the real world which is some people
getting richer and not us having and us
not having an effective way to tax that
capital. the buy, borrow, die dimension
that Newsome and others, Ray Matto on my
show have talked about so well. The uh
difficulty of setting a public agenda as
companies become very powerful. Right
now, Andre Horowitz is the biggest
spender in the 2026 midterms. They
spent, according to reporting I just saw
the times, over $115 million. They have
a very radically deregulatory
accelerationist agenda for AI, crypto,
and other things. Right? it AI is not
putting us in a place where none of the
old constraints bite. It is putting us
in a place where the bottlenecks of the
real world and the questions of power in
some ways bite more. And so I think in
order to know how to solve or answer the
questions that are coming immediately,
we actually have to discipline more
tightly what those questions are. If we
want I keep using drug development
because I think it's a at least a very
concrete example. If we want AI to get
us more drug discovery, then we have to
ask what the next bottleneck is going to
be if we get a much more rapid
acceleration of molecules worth testing
on human beings. Right now, it is very
very hard under the way we have built
the system to find enough people to go
into phase three trials. We could create
interoperable electronic records that
actually mean we know all the people in
the country with a certain disease
pattern and then we could tell them that
there's a trial that could help them. We
do this for a couple of things right
now. It is radically accelerated drug
development for some cancers, but we
don't do it for most things. That's not
like a super sexy fun AI thought
experiment, but it could really matter.
Like you could look at this for energy.
You could look at this for building
efficiency. You could look at this for
how people interact with the government.
My wife Annie Lowry is uh releasing his
book in a couple months on the time
packs. incredible difficulty of
navigating the amount of time it takes
to figure out what the government has to
offer you and what it takes to qualify
for it. There's no actual reason that
needs to be your time. That is a
political choice we have made. It would
be trivial. The IRS has the data on what
your financial situation is. There could
be not only an LLM that helps you with
your taxes, but actually tells you what
you qualify for all across the federal
government or the for that matter state
governments all at once. But in order to
do that, we need to make the data talk
to each other. We need to break down
current privacy regulations that make
that impossible. We are at the point
where AI is material
poss uh possibilities. If we treat it so
speculatively like in some ways I think
that's buying in at this point to the
game the labs are playing, right? I'm
not saying none of that might ever
happen, but I do think that it is
probably a little bit more unlikely to
happen than they want you to think. And
the best way to be able to deal with it
then is to be good at dealing with the
problems we're going to have with it.
Now, I want to turn a question on you
though because you've been doing this
series on it. One of the things I see
happening, we're here at at CAP is
when I wrote abundance, one of the the
big questions in it or the back half of
it was about with Derek Thompson was
about how do you build a left? How do
you build a relationship where the left
doesn't just see technology as a social
problem, but technology as a way to
solve social problems? And my sense is
AI has made this problem much much
worse. Effectively the relationship
between the left and technology is like
worse than it has ever been. I think
climate change was beginning to ease
this because there's a recognition we
needed green energy to solve our
problems and technological innovation
and AI has made it much worse
>> because it does present all these
problems of power and concentration.
Like how do you navigate that tension?
Well, that's why I think you need to
have some I think you have to have some
story of what's in it for people. Um
that is legible and plausible. Um that
because right now I I you know right now
the latest data and I don't think it's
born of AI. I think it's born of a lot
of things has the lowest share of you
know um total income going to labor
versus capital that we've ever seen. Um
the way that the labs again sell
investment into the uh into the models
is that it's going to push that number
even further. Right. That's the whole
point. Like
>> a billboard right outside my office. It
just says stop hiring humans.
>> Yes.
>> Like what a ghoul.
>> To create that.
>> And so I think um I think there's a
there's a sense in which unless there's
some distributive story
and I don't mean distributive in the
sense of like we're going to tax it and
give you a check. I mean, like,
literally, what's in it for me? I I just
think it's a very it's it's it's a very
tough cell. And I also don't think the
skeptic the skepticism doesn't seem at
all crazy to me. It seems totally
rational. Like, we're going to build
this data center. Maybe there's going to
be some jobs here. But fundamentally,
like a bunch of really rich people who
fundamentally
like want to get rid of you are going to
use it to get rid of you is basically
the story now. And I think you're right
to flip it on its head. It's like, well,
what would we want? what we want the
technology to do. What if the LLMs could
be good at doing your taxes? What if we
could unblock all sorts of new ways of
getting drugs?
But I just think what I guess I guess
what I'm saying is you can't I don't
think you could detach it from some
distributive story about who has power
and who's benefiting. And I think if you
if you talk about things like in in the
abstract,
what I think people are gonna
particularly people on the left, but I
think generally people's skepticism of
this is is high anyway, is going to
think that they're going to be left out
in the cold. Um, and right now it's hard
to see a lot of reasons why that's not
the case. Um, in again to your point
about it's not the future, it's now.
like the stock market's booming.
There's going to be trillions of dollars
of capital allocation to this.
Lots of people use the technology. They
they like it. Maybe it drives a few of
them insane. Um
but what the tangible benefits are for
people outside I think um a relatively
small group I think remains very
abstract.
>> And that's where I actually think the
political system is failing. That of
course that's not going to come from the
corporations.
>> Right.
>> Right. They're not going to tell a story
about how they're going to become less
powerful. They're not going to create a
world. I mean, I remember the tour from
OpenAI people some years ago about how
much they wanted to be regulated. And I
look at what um leading the future, the
pack partially funded by OpenAI
co-founder Greg Brockman, how much it is
spending against Alex Boris because in
New York because he has had the tearity
to try to do very modest very modest
safetyoriented regulation of AI. And so
like this this is what I mean that if if
the way the public relates to it is to
just say developing this and deciding
how it's used is entirely the private
markets prerogative and we are just
going to try to prevent harms around the
edge then there's no chance right
>> for that democratic vision you're
talking about
>> and I do think I mean shikott uh shari
who's running in that uh Scott Weiner
district in pelosial district does have
this kind of like public AI model
campaign pain plank which I think is
interesting like that we should have a
government administered LLM that you
know that our own lab that's working on
this that hires the best talent and I do
think thinking about
some public stake or some public part in
this um is one first step in that but I
also think that like I want to ask this
question because we have a question from
the audience and I think it sort of
brings us to the the data center fight
because that's where like the rubber
hits the road on all this like at some
level I'm extremely sympathetic to
people fighting the data centers at the
at another level. There's part of me
that's like, well, this is just the nimi
gun pointed at another target. Usually,
I don't like the target they're pointing
it at, but maybe this target's fine. Um,
and this question for the audience from
the audience is, how would a system of
government in the abundance model
balance ensuring public sector decisions
are both effective and democratic? We're
seeing in these fights over data
centers. How would it resist capture by
big corporations? I
>> It's a big question. Uh I'll to keep it
on the data center point. The thing I
have heard talking to a lot of
governors, mayors, representatives
involved in the data center fights
because like to be blunt about this
question, the way the American political
system tries to balance this is that we
elect people and they're supposed to be
able to balance the various incentives
and interests of society in a way that
makes sense. And the thing that I think
the people who are more forward-looking
on this are saying is look, if you want
all these data centers, what you have to
do is not just pay for the electricity
they're going to use. Like that's table
stakes. This is a tremendous amount of
investment, a railroads level of
investment that is going to genuinely be
either a huge strain or an opportunity
for transformation of a lot of our
infrastructure, particularly our energy
infrastructure. And so the the data
center buildout has to be harnessed in
their view to some public vision about
how it is actually benefiting the
communities it is part of. In this way,
data centers are not like homes. When we
argue that it should be easier to build
homes, the reason it should be easier to
build homes is it is good for people to
live in communities.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> Like the these like the idea is not omni
building, right? I don't want you to be
able to build more coal power plants
because those are bad for communities.
And the question of whether a data
center is good for like the community it
is in. There's questions about the
broader state, about the broader
country, right? There's questions about
the air race with China. But the
question of whether it's good for a
community is in that is something we
actually know how to at least try to
think about balancing. Now you could at
the state level create framework
legislation about what kinds of
investments in the grid, what kinds of
investments in water, what kinds of
investments in modernizing like
desperately needed uh in creating
modernization that is desperately needed
in order to build big buildouts you want
to force. And then if you create a clear
like set of rules of the road, then
there's certainty on how to invest and
what you can get done. But what all the
people actually dealing with this at
town hall meetings tell me and I think
they're right about is that unless you
can tell like a town what is in it for
them. They don't want it. And they're
right that like nothing is in it for
them except like a bit of tax revenue.
So like but that's not impossible if
there's all this money behind it. Money
is fungeible. Money can do a lot of
things and particularly as an
opportunity to modernize our energy
grid. like this is maybe the biggest
opportunity is private capital to do
that ever
>> and yes modernize the grid build out
capacity all that stuff um well you can
mark down at 22958 when we solved all
this uh in your books uh Ezra Klein the
New York Times
>> thank you Chris Hayes MSN now [applause]
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hey everyone. Uh we're going to we're
going to take a quick 10-minute break.
Uh please help yourself to refreshments
um in the foyer and again bathrooms are
downstairs and we'll see you back in
about 10 minutes or so. Thank you.
Thanks so much for tuning in to our
exclusive live programming for the
Center for American Progress's 2026 CAP
Ideas Conference. My name is Colin
Seabberger, senior adviser at CAP. I'm
excited to be joined by my colleague
Toeer Spiro, senior fellow for health
policy at CAP to healthcare
ability. Healthcare is often front of
mind for folks. Um, you know, we've
seen, President Trump said that he was
going to make life more affordable for
folks. And yet, we know that health care
is an area where we've seen, you know,
people experiencing intense financial
distress of late. Congress allowed the
enhanced premium tax credits to expire,
which has helped double premiums for
tens of billions of Americans. What are
you hearing from stakeholders in this
moment?
They also slashed Medicaid by 1 trillion
and throwing 10 million people off of
Medicaid coverage. So, it's that plus
doubling the premiums in the Affordable
Care Act marketplaces. We're uh facing a
breaking point. The system is in crisis.
Poll after poll shows that health care
costs rise to the top. You know, it may
fluctuate between groceries and health
care costs, but health care cost is
always consistently
top one or two issues.
>> And it's durable over time.
>> Durable over time,
>> and it's cost, but it's also people's
other frustrations with their insurance.
So, half of insured adults have had to
get a prior authorization in the past
two years, and this is rising as a top
concern for people. Well, uh, you know,
Democrats particularly of late, uh, have
had a lot of success, um, in making
changes to the health care system. We're
clearly at a breaking point, like you
mentioned, uh, and more changes are
needed in order to be able to uh, help
address some of these challenges. Um,
you know, I know CAP has its own
healthcare plan. Can you tell me a
little bit about it? um and you know
what kind of response you're hearing
from policy makers.
>> Yeah. So I'll give you a brief overview
and then we can dive in to the
particulars as you as you want. Um so I
think people are really clamoring for
immediate relief on premiums on
deductibles and on the insurance denials
and prior authorization. So in addition
to an agenda that expands coverage we
need to address these immediate
concerns. Um so we have a plan that has
four parts. First um making sure that
premium increases do not rise faster
than the actual cost of care is rising.
Secondly, if insurance companies are
getting windfall profits, we need to
return those profits to consumers in the
form of rebates
by limiting extreme hospital prices. And
then fourth, uh ban and replace prior
authorization with independent clinical
review. These reviews would be conducted
by independent clinicians. They would be
subject to a strict 48 hour deadline
free of conflicts of interest and most
highly cost and overused services.
Everything else um would not be subject
to a review. And that's the kind of
agenda that people are clamoring for in
the immediate term.
>> Yeah. I mean really focusing in on those
those cost challenges. Uh you know
Democrats uh historically over the past
several decades have focused a lot on
>> access to coverage right and and the
need to make sure that everybody has
access to health insurance. This is
really focusing in, you know, like a
laser on being sure that you can use
your insurance by going after prior
authorization, but also really getting
at people's financial pay.
>> Yes. The the there are broader reforms
like public option or Medicare for all
>> that are longer term in nature and that
expand coverage and reduce costs. But
what we're saying is it's both and we
need to also have an agenda that
addresses uh the immediate concerns and
provides immediate relief on premiums
and deductibles.
>> Um well, what kind of response are you
getting from uh you know, we've had
several leaders here uh including
California Governor Gavin Newsome uh
several different governors uh and
senators. What kind of response are you
hearing from elected officials in
response to this plan coming out?
>> I would say it's getting good traction
in both the House and the Senate.
>> Um, I'm not going to get ahead of uh
people wanting to uh, you know, finish
it's going so far. And the other
interesting thing is that we've been
talking to um employer groups and
insurers and and there's just a among
stakeholders a general recognition that
something needs to change.
>> Yeah. I mean even small businesses here
and and you know people with employer
sponsored insurance are recognizing that
the system really is at a breaking
point, right? Usually it's those folks
who are on the individual market or or
small business owners who are kind of
having to fend for themselves. That's
right.
>> Usually the ones driving the
conversation here, but really we're even
seeing this, you know, in the ESI
network as well.
>> Yes. And it it it's about market
concentration. Um market concentration
on the hospital side and market
concentration on the insurer side. And
employers, even large employers, I think
are finding it increasingly difficult to
go up against that kind of market power.
And it's that market power and and
market concentration that is really
driving up the prices of medical care
and driving up premiums. And so the
solution has to be to really address
that that market power.
you know, uh, we can't really talk about
healthcare right now and not talk about,
uh, the impact of the cuts that you were
talking about earlier, the cuts to
Medicaid. We're talking a trillion
dollars in cuts to Medicaid.
>> The president's plans are going to
absolutely level many providers,
particularly those in rural communities.
I'm talking about our rural hospitals,
community health centers. Yes.
>> Right.
How do we make sure that they uh kind of
are set on a solid path as we're making
some of these changes to address
people's financial uh anxieties as it
relates to the healthare system?
>> Yeah. I mean, I think the prerequisite
to any plan, any proposal is to restore
those that Medicaid funding that goes to
hospitals and to reverse the the
Medicaid cuts and to extend the um
Affordable Care Act premium tax credits.
Um so unwinding and reversing the damage
that Trump has caused is job number one.
But we cannot stop there. We know uh
from polling that like we need to have
an affirmative agenda. We need to have
new ideas and we need to show that we
understand where people are, understand
their cost concerns and that we're
addressing it. Well, it's really
interesting that it is this president
who has overseen, you know, the largest
cuts to Medicaid in American history,
who has kicked tens of millions or will
have kicked tens of millions of
Americans off their health insurance.
And yet, at the same time, it was Donald
Trump, mind you, who campaigned for
office on making America healthy again.
At the same time, uh, you know, we're
seeing this government, uh, you know,
overturn bans on forever chemicals, on,
uh, you know, uh, wiping out renewable
energy sources and instead preferring
fossil fuels that are, um, you know,
polluting our air and water.
I'm curious, you know, how is CAP
thinking about uh, you know, a plan that
actually would address what I think a
lot of Americans,
you know, rightly identify are um, uh,
you know, fundamental
um, you know, challenges to having a
healthy society. Um, you know, thanks to
uh, food and drug companies, thanks to
the polluters, right? Um, not to
mention, you know, the social media
companies and mental health. Um, so can
you talk a bit about how you're thinking
about actually making America healthy?
>> Yeah, it's a good question. And I think
there's a lot of disillusionment among
the Maha uh movement with what's been
going on with the Trump administration
and their exemption of pesticides
um and uh Roundup and as you mentioned
reversing the regulation of PAS in
drinking water,
you know, the damage they've done to
vaccine
uh recommendations and vaccine supply.
Um, so there's a real opportunity here
for Democrats
to take back that agenda and to show
that we are the ones who care about
protecting health. Democrats are the
party of a strong FDA, a strong CDC
to protect Americans health. and uh
somehow RFK has tried to co-opt that,
but the actions don't match the words.
>> Um so there's a petition right now from
David Kesler, former commissioner before
the FDA
to regulate um ultrarocessed foods and
it's just been sitting there. and RFK
talks a good game about um ultrarocessed
foods, but he hasn't taken action on the
petition. Um so we're going to be
releasing a plan uh in the coming weeks
to say what would an affirmative agenda
on public health actually look like that
gets these toxins out of the food
supply, out of the water supply, and out
of the air. and um what a as you say
what a making America healthy again
agenda would actually look like.
>> Well, I'm sure that is going to be very
popular with uh food and beverage
companies as I'm sure uh some of the
reforms that we were talking about
making to uh the insurance system are
going to be very popular with uh
insurance companies. Uh you know,
>> drug price negotiation. Yeah,
>> you know,
>> I'm I'm curious for your sense like do
you think that we can actually
accomplish these things? Is it going to
take kind of uh a more systemic
um uh political reform effort?
Uh you know, we'll hear a little bit
more about this in just a second. We at
CAP have been um pushing an exciting new
effort uh to
curb the impacts of the Supreme Court
Citizens United decision uh from the
preceding decade. Uh but I'm curious to
get your sense on whether you think we
can actually get these things done uh in
our current politics.
>> I sense that the ground is shifting and
again it goes back to the crisis that
we're in and the the fact that there's a
breaking point. If we're not in the
breaking point right now, it's coming
soon. And what can't continue to happen
won't continue to happen. Eventually,
the demand for reform will be so strong.
And you know, I've been around a long
time since the Affordable Care Act. Um,
at that time,
>> you're not uh [laughter]
>> at that time, you know, it was viewed as
um untouchable during the Affordable
Care Act to to go after big pharma. to
include anything on drug pricing in that
bill. And fast forward to a decade later
with the inflation reduction act,
Democrats finally um capitalized on
bringing Medicare negotiation to
prescription drug prices and you know so
I think that change
>> and it was one of the most uh popular
parts of uh one of the most popular
>> administration's record. Yeah.
>> Right. And actually got it done.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and so
That's what we need to focus on. We have
to have laser-like focus um to continue
the drum beat, continue the advocacy um
and we'll get these things done.
>> Well, you heard it here, folks. We will
keep pressing here at the Center for
America
>> plan as well as uh the make America
healthy again uh effort that you all are
embarking on. And uh you'll have to come
to Americanprogress.org org and make
sure to check out that plan. When should
we expect it?
>> Patience Bill of Rights.
>> The MAHA plan, the the the the actual MA
plan in the next couple weeks.
>> Next couple of weeks. Okay, folks. Stay
tuned. Uh we will make sure uh that uh
we bring uh Toeer under our social media
channels to uh or one of your colleagues
maybe and uh you know have them share
all about it. Uh Toeer, thanks again.
>> Thank you. Yep.
>> All right, folks. We are going to get
back to this conference in just a
second. Uh we've got a few really
exciting additional panels, uh some
additional speakers. We've got Governor
Wes Moore coming up shortly. Uh please
stay tuned. Thanks so much.
Turn your seats. We're going to be
starting the program back up shortly.
Thanks again.
The Supreme Court shattered campaign
finance law with its decision in
Citizens United in 2010. Americans have
been told that there are only two ways
to stop corporate and dark money in
politics. Either amend the US
Constitution or wait generations for a
new Supreme Court. Turns out there's
another way. Hi, my name is Tom Moore.
I'm a senior fellow for democracy policy
at CAP. Let me introduce you to CAP's
corporate power reset. The corporate
power reset is a new legal and
legislative strategy developed by the
Center for American Progress. Instead of
trying to ban or restrict the corporate
political spending that Citizens United
opened up, this plan focuses on the
legal powers granted to corporations by
states. States create corporations. And
corporations have only the powers that
states give them. And what the state
gives, the state can take away by
amending their corporate statutes to say
that corporations no longer have the
power to spend money in politics.
[music] It's not regulation. It's
redefinition. I've been working with
folks on the ground in Montana for a
year and a half on the Montana plan to
help them get this on their ballot this
fall. Last year, CAP's video and digital
teams joined the effort and once they
started sharing this idea with the world
spread like wildfire. In just days, the
video we cut had over 6.7 million views
across social media and tons and tons of
comments. And the next videos reached
even more people.
State lawmakers started hearing from
their constituents about it [music] and
then they started reaching out to us
about how they could do the corporate
power reset in their states. It's been
the easiest sales job ever.
>> And Hawaii will lead in the effort to
end dark money in politics.
>> I want to give you a great deal of
credit. [music] You and Cap. We can get
rid of Citizens United.
>> What?
>> This is very, very important.
>> You don't have to accept the
unacceptable. And that's what the
Montana plan is all about. And it is the
best chance I've seen in a long time to
put the Citizens United decision in its
place, which is the dust bin of history.
>> And it's not just a few states.
Corporate power reset bills have been
filed in more than a dozen legislatores
just this year. Lawmakers in a bunch of
other states have also expressed
interest and Hawaii has gone the
furthest of them all.
>> Governor Josh Green signed several bills
into law today. One would limit
corporate donations in Hawaii politics.
Political action committees will not be
allowed to spend any money received from
corporations.
>> This year next, my job is going to be to
keep all those bills on track in the
states and to prepare for the massive
legal fight that this project is going
to spark. I'm doing the best work of my
career. I feel very grateful and
privileged to have been given the
freedom and support to pursue this idea
and that's CAPS strength. We not only
come up with great ideas, but we have
the teams to make them have real impact
in the world. [music]
Please welcome CAP senior fellow Jared
Bernstein.
[music]
It is my privilege to introduce Senator
Elizabeth Warren. I first met Professor
Warren when she was working on her 2004
book co-written with Amelia Warren Tyagi
called the two income trap. There are
three things this fact tells you about
her. First, she was writing about
affordability literally 22 years before
the rest of us. Second, her views are
informed by datadriven analysis that is
rare to the point of extinction in much
of today's politics. She may not
remember this, but our first
conversation was not about legislation
or economic trends. It was about the
best deflator to use for consumer
expenditure data.
Third, in that book, Senator Warren
examined the relationship between
personal bankruptcies and economic
insecurity.
Years later, she championed bankruptcy
legislation to protect consumers from
the financial abuses that have informed
her writings, her teachings, and her
political ascension, followed a few
years later by her brainchild, the
Consumer Financial Protection Bureau.
Agreed. [cheering]
Talk about turning your analysis into
action. It's a truly remarkable record,
Senator. But all that pales beside the
exchange I recently had with a friend
wherein we were bemoning the situation
we find ourselves in today. As the
conversation became increasingly
depressing, I asked my friend if he was
losing hope. His reply was, "I'll give
up hope when Elizabeth Warren stops
fighting." I think we all know that's
not going to happen. So without further
ado, Senator Elizabeth Warren.
[music]
Hello.
Oh, thank you, Jared. That was a that
was a very generous introduction. Thank
you all for the warm welcome. I love
being in a room full of nerds. Uh my
kind of people. Uh, so I want to say
thank you to Meera and to Cap for
pulling everybody together for this
conference. I think it's terrific. I
love a chance to get together and talk
about ideas. So, a lot of folks in this
room would tell you that costs are way
up and Donald Trump is to blame. Kind of
a simple message here and it is true.
And it is a big reason why Donald
Trump's approval ratings
have now reached record lows.
But Americans are angry and have been
angry for a very long time because costs
have been going up for decades under
both Republican and Democratic
administrations.
If we want to win the 2026 midterms and
have a fighting chance in 2028, then we
need to convince Americans that we're
serious about taking on the big fights
and lowering costs. I think it's that
straightforward.
And that means we have to do more than
just general handwaving. The
handwaving's been going on for a long
time. What it means is specific
proposals that would make meaningful
differences in people's lives. Specific
proposals that we are willing to be held
accountable for delivering on. And I
think the right place to start is with
child care. Now, child care costs have
risen at twice the rate of inflation. In
47 out of 50 states, families are paying
more for child care for two kids than
rent for their whole family. And under
Donald Trump, the crisis has gotten
worse. Now, I've told the story many
times. As a young mom, I was about an
inch away from quitting my job before my
aunt be moved in to help with child
care. That was 40 years ago and the
problem has only gotten worse. And news
flash, not everybody has an aunt B. So
today, half of all children live in
child care deserts, meaning there are
two or three children lined up who need
care for every one care slot that is
available. If you are lucky today in
America, you might get a spot for your
infant if you started today in six
months. And then again, you might get
stuck on a two-year wait list for the
privilege of paying $20,000 plus a year.
So, the question is, how do we get here?
How did this one get so hard over time?
The answer is just plain old econ 101.
Supply and demand. Prices are high
because lots of families need care and
there's nowhere near enough care
providers. So why aren't there enough
care providers? Why aren't there enough
child care workers? Again, econ 101.
There aren't enough workers because
those workers are typically paid at
rates lower than Uber drivers. So why
not pay them more? Well, typically when
you need more workers, you just pay them
more. But families are already getting
flattened by sky-high costs for care,
and they just simply cannot afford to
pay more. In other words, the private
market has not and cannot solve the
child care market problem. The only way
to develop adequate child care is for
the government to fill the gap by
investing in families and workers. And
look, it would be a smart investment
with huge payoffs. Workers would be paid
commensurate with the training and
responsibilities that they take on.
Babies get a very strong start in life
and families get a huge cost relief. As
a nation, we support our economy right
now by investing in roads and bridges
and education so that all of our
businesses and all of our workers can
prosper. It is time to do the same for
child care. Make this investment so that
mamas and daddies can work and we will
all see the payoff.
Child care shouldn't be a privilege
reserved for a handful of the wealthy.
Child care is public infrastructure that
makes our communities and our businesses
flourish. And you can applaud that.
Look, [applause]
but I want to talk about how we got
there because here's a here's a part
where the story takes a little bit of a
twist. When I ran for president in 2020,
I talked about child care literally at
every single stop.
While every other Democrat
supported expanding child care, it just
wasn't the key thing that they talked
about. So when Joe Biden was elected, we
were in the throws of COVID pandemic and
it ripped back the curtain on just how
fragile our cobbled together child care
system really is. Everybody faced it
headon at that point and for the first
time in a long time we had the
Democratic trifecta, the House, the
Senate, the White House. To me, I
thought this is it. This is the golden
chance. This is our moment to deliver
universal child care. And I want to be
clear, I was not alone in fighting for
child care. Patty Murray and I burned up
the phone lines as we strategized with
each other over how to get a child care
bill across the finish line. The
advocates were out. They circulated
data. They told the stories. They got
them published. They brought families to
the Hill to testify about the
differences that a good child care
program could make. And just like in
2020, almost every Democrat would tell
you if asked, "Sure, they supported
child care,
but not enough were willing to fight for
it." They were largely just checking the
box.
The law the Democrats were putting
together, Build Back Better, was never
about how to build a robust, effective
child care center a system. Never.
Instead, it was an exercise in how weak
and how ineffective we could make the
child care program and still call it
child care. How little could we invest
in order to keep the price tag under an
artificial cap? How much could we
discourage statements from states from
implementing the program so the cost on
paper wouldn't scare Joe Mansion or the
tax policies on the other side of the
ledger wouldn't make Kirstston Cinema
give a little curtsy and vote no?
That was a frustrating, aggravating
process right up until the minute that
child care dropped off the bill
entirely.
We lost child care because not enough
Democrats who were already in office
were actually willing to fight for it.
They just backed off. And I believe down
to my bones that Democrats who think
there is no reward for fighting to
deliver universal child care are just
dead wrong today. Cities and states
across the country are the ones who are
actually leading the charge here.
Democrats like Governor uh Mikey Cheryl
in New Jersey and Governor Abigail
Spanberger in Virginia and Mayor um Mom
Donnie in New York. Yes. All of them.
Think about those three. They all
campaigned aggressively on increasing
access to child care and they all won.
And I give them huge respect for that.
But to deliver big for every American
family, to have this influence every
election, states and cities can't be
left to do this alone. And here's the
good news. They don't need to. Universal
child care isn't just good policy. It is
also good politics.
Take a look at the Republican party on
the question of child care.
They are fumbling the child care issue
now at the most basic level. Vice
President J. Dance Vance's solution.
Just have the grandparents move next
door. Heck of a solution. JD. Uh last
month, Donald Trump said out loud on
camera that we can't quote take care of
child care because we have to dump a
billion dollars a day into a war halfway
around the world with Iran. Uh so much
for America first. Look, it would be
political malpractice for Democrats not
to be talking about child care every
chance we get going into the midterms
and beyond.
When I look at the upcoming Democratic
presidential primary, every 2028
candidate who understands what's
happening in this country, who wants to
win, and who will deliver for families
will make universal child care a core
piece of their agenda.
[applause] Yep.
So how do we get it done? First cover
everyone.
We cannot be afraid of big of big
structural change and that means
affordable highquality care for every
single American family. Look, Social
Security is the most popular government
program ever. And the reason is because
it benefits everyone. And the same
should be true of child care. Every
parent, every employer, every worker
needs to see exactly how a child care
program will work for them. We must
cover all families and keep prices
manageable for all families. Let me give
you an example. For the typical family
who might be paying today $25,000 a year
for child care, the proposal we've put
together would save them $15,000
a year. Every year.
Oh, and just to draw a line on this, for
every mother, a single mother making
$60,000 a year, she'd pay nothing at
all. And that is a big deal. [applause]
So that's number one. Make it apply to
everyone. Make it affordable for
everyone. And number two, speed. Speed.
Speed. We need to deliver quickly to
solve the affordability crisis that is
flattening families right now. I'm
talking months, not years. And the only
reason I'm talking months instead of
years is because my team keeps telling
me I can't talk weeks. But that's how we
need to be thinking of this. And that is
the kind of urgency we need to bring to
this. And again, remember what happened
last time the Democrats were in power.
talented, dedicated folks put together a
whole lot of really good policy ideas,
but speed was never baked in. So, it
took a long time for those investments
to help families. Some benefits like
Medicare drug negotiations were actually
passed into law, but they were
deliberately set up so that the price
cuts would not kick in until years
later. So when the election rolled
around and people asked themselves, hey,
what have the Democrats done for me? Too
many of them felt the answer was not
enough or even worse, nothing at all.
Our new child care proposal needs to get
resources to states and localities right
away. And that means setting up strike
teams to help states and cities create
more child care slots now. It means
helping neighbors who babysit get
licensed so they are eligible. It means
rethinking regulations that are keeping
out new providers. And yes, absolutely.
We need to keep our kids safe. And yes,
we need all kinds of providers who can
meet those standards so that we have
abundant, affordable, high quality child
care for every family in America.
[applause]
And the time to do this, to get it
together, is now when we get the next
Democratic trifecta.
We need legislation that is ready to
pass on day one. And our legislation
should make it possible for parents to
access that care at a minimum in the
very same year. Some people might say
that's unrealistic. I say you don't get
what you don't fight for. Now, I am
putting my money where my mouth is on
this. I have teamed up with the top
Democratic appropriator, Senator Patty
Murray, the top House Democrat for
education, Bobby Scott, and the
outstanding Congresswoman from New York,
Alexandria Okasio Cortez.
The four of us are doing the hard policy
work right now, the nuts and bolts, the
wiring. Here's how the pieces will work.
Here's how we get the money in. Here's
how we get the money back out. We are
working on a draft bill that will be
ready as the day one solution when we
take back power. And we need every
Democrat, whether they are in office now
or whether they are running for office
on board. Can I get an amen on that one?
Got to make them do this. [applause]
Look, it is a tough time. costs,
including the cost of child care, are
crushing American families. And Donald
Trump is too busy starting wars and
lining his own pockets to care. We are
in a fight to deliver for the American
people. Not to talk, but to deliver. To
lower costs that are keeping people up
at night and to give people some hope by
showing them what it looks like to have
a government that is on their side. The
impact of universal affordable child
care for all families would be truly
seismic. It would mean a single mother
could go back to school and get her
nursing license. It would mean a young
couple could start that small business
they've been dreaming of. It would mean
a family could start setting aside money
for a down payment on a house. It would
be lifechanging
for literally millions of people across
this country. And whether you have kids
or not, whether you like kids or not,
I know some of you out there. I think
kids, uh, universal child care is truly
the best investment we can make in
strengthening our middle class, and that
should matter to everyone. As Democrats
go around the country over the next five
months and ask people to vote for us,
every single one of us should be talking
about child care. We can take back
Congress, then we can take back the
White House, and then we can deliver
universal child care and help rebuild
America's middle class.
Thank you all. [applause] Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Good to see you
all.
[music]
Please welcome Senator Reverend Raphael
Waro of Georgia and MS Now's Simone
Sanders Townsend.
>> [music]
>> Oh, here we are. Greetings. Greetings.
Greetings, everyone. Greetings, senator.
Thank you for joining us. I know there's
many places you could be like on the
hill voting. Uh, and the senator does
have some votes. So, we're going to get
quickly to the heart of the matter. Uh
obviously voting rights has been on the
hearts and minds of uh lots of people in
this country, Democrats, Republicans and
independents um and our democracy at
large. So I want to start there talking
about um some pushing the conversation
forward given some things you yourself
have said as of late. Uh you have called
Klay which is decision the most recent
decision about the vot uh the VRA Jim
Crow and new clothes. I I Yes, he did.
Now I think the deeper issue frankly um
is that we are watching the same
playbook that dismantled reconstruction
uh after the dismantling of
reconstruction. You have the courts
aiding and embedding in what's going on.
The state legislators are moving at
record speed. Um the federal government
uh is is is here playing a role. And so
what does the next phase of this
actually look like? Is it enough to just
restore the Voting Rights Act uh or does
it need to be bigger? it. Hello
everybody. Good to be here with you.
Thank you so much.
[applause] It It's really hard, if not
impossible, to overstate
how important this moment is.
What the Supreme Court did the other day
is devastating.
It's a massive blow to voting rights in
this country. And if there's anything
that keeps me up at night, it's that it,
you know, there there are a whole range
of issues, right? I'm about to go vote
in a few minutes. We got a vote going
on. But of all, you know, there are a
lot of issues we debate every single
day.
>> But the democracy is the house we live
in and MAGA politicians,
some of them on the Supreme Court
are burning and looting the house. And
so we have to take it seriously. Uh I
have been working ever since I came to
the Senate to pass voting rights. I came
in the 117th Congress and we got a whole
lot done uh that Congress. I sure wish
we had passed the John Lewis Voting
Rights Advancement Act. Um nothing could
be more important. Uh but going forward,
you know, we're focused on winning the
midterms. Uh we've got to set the table
so that when Democrats are back in
power,
we have to pass the Voting Rights
Advancement Act, we've got to do
something about all of this dark money
>> that's in our politics that quite
frankly is behind this Supreme Court.
>> So along those lines then, are you I
mean, how are you going to get that
done? Democrats, it's not as though they
haven't had an answer to what
Republicans have been um doing in terms
of a power grab, as I would call it. I
think at the end of the day, this is all
about power. Um state legislators, uh
governor's races, so on and so forth.
When it comes to voting rights in
America, there have been a number of
bills um in the House and in the Senate,
and none of them have passed. And so,
what is going to happen differently? Are
you endorsing a getting rid of the
filibuster? Like, what how are you going
to get
>> Let me let me be very clear. Uh, no
arcane Senate procedure should block
people's right to have their voices
heard and their votes cast in their
democracy. Uh, that that is my position.
And uh when we are back in power, uh
we've got to pass voting rights. No more
hand ringing, no more delay.
uh you can't fight for the people and
then have the people send you into power
and not fight to give the people the
power for their voices to be heard in
their democracy. So we need to pass the
Voting Rights Advancement Act which
would ban racial gerrymanding gerry
gerrymandering
uh ban partial gerrymandering
uh or uh partisan gerrymandering. Um, I
think DC statehood
is what we need. Uh, and we ought to we
ought to provide a path
for other territories of the United
States, a democratic path for them to
decide whether or not they want
statehood. Here we are approaching the
250th
anniversary of a nation born fighting
taxation without representation
and here we are sitting in this place.
So, so I'm deeply worried. I'm angry
that democ that the democracy is on
fire. I think the answer to fighting
those who are trying to fight the
democracy
>> is more democracy is to make sure that
the people can can that their voices can
be heard and so um uh we we need Supreme
Court reform.
>> Okay, let's talk about Supreme Court
reform. I was going there next. Um you
just as we were sitting here, you talked
about MAGA politicians and you said
quote some of them on the Supreme Court.
recently you called some sitting
justices on the Supreme Court political
hacks as a quote. Um, look, for decades,
I think it is safe to say that both
parties, Democrats and Republicans,
frankly, tried to convince Americans
that the court was apolitical. Now, in
my estimation, I think the Republican
party apparatus uh said that but acted
differently. Uh it seems like now both
parties are waking up to the fact or
have arrived at the same place that the
court is maybe a little more political
than folks led on. So what does court
reform look like? Do you think we need
more justices on the Supreme Court?
Because if the current ones are
political hacks, how do you counter
that?
>> Here's what we know.
We know that what we are witnessing
right now is not working.
I I'm angry about the dismantling of the
Voting Rights Act, section two.
But the same court that dismantled
section two
dismantled section five,
they are also the same court that uh is
responsible for Citizens United.
>> And so while black voters are at the
center of the discussion right now, we
can't lose sight of the bigger picture.
They are after the coalition.
Whether it is giving billionaires
and heavyweight donors and corporations
and outside impact and influence in our
politics through Citizens United or
suppressing the vote by dismantling
section two or gerrymandering folks
through section five or trying to pass
the Save Act which would
disproportionately impact women, women,
black people, brown people, workingclass
people, they are after everyday
Americans. And so it would be
irresponsible for us not to respond. The
court has been reformed before. We
certainly need ethics, a code of ethics.
Let's try that. That'll be a good first
step.
>> Well, there is currently a code, but
it's not enforceable. So what I I mean
this it seems like this is early
conversation.
>> That's a way to fix it. We we we need a
code of ethics.
>> Okay.
>> And then there are a number of reforms
on the table. term limits, expansion of
the court wouldn't be the first time. I
think given the crisis we're in, Simone,
all of those things have to be on the
table.
>> And you are willing to have not just
have those conversations, but that's a
vote you're also willing to take.
>> Everything should be on the table.
>> Everything should Okay. Everything
should be on the table. You all heard
that. Look, I think that the American
people um I I think what you just said
is refreshing to hear because
I don't know how any politician in this
country can credibly say that our
democracy is in danger and then not be
willing to take the steps to address the
democracy being in danger. And so, um
there's a a poem by Edgar's Edgar Guest
that talks about doing the things that
haven't been done before. Do you think
Democrats need to, not just when it
comes to the courts, but voting rights,
but also our economy, need to do some
things that haven't been done before?
And if so, what are those things?
>> We we owe it to the people. On the
voting rights piece, I just want to, you
know, remind everybody that we look, we
had every Democrat on board
>> for those voting bills that we were
trying to pass. But what happened
>> at the end of the day? There were two
United States senators who were no
longer in the caucus uh who were not
willing to do what was necessary to pass
it. And I I thought then that we should
have gotten voting rights done. I'm I'm
proud to have come into Congress at a
time where when you think about the
amount of legislation we passed when I
got elected in 21 and we wouldn't have
done any of that had I not gotten
elected. and John Oaw. Georgia, I just
want to say Georgia saved the whole
country. Um but
but and and we got to send John Oaf back
to the United States Senate. Um but
think about what we did that Congress.
We passed the American Rescue Plan,
which which included in that was the
child tax credit. So we cut child
poverty 40% for six months. We passed a
bipartisan infrastructure bill. We
passed a chips and science bill, the
most significant industrial policy we
had seen in a very long time. We passed
the first gun safety bill in 30 years.
We passed the burn pits uh uh bill which
helped the veterans. We passed the
inflation reduction act uh which was the
largest investment in clean energy ever
in human history. and it capped the cost
of prescription drugs, gave Medicaid the
ability to negotiate the price of
prescription drugs. All of that and all
of those are things that I support. I'm
proud that we did it, but we're watching
them burn that stuff down right now.
We're seeing them undermine it. And if I
had all of those things
and the John Lewis Voting Rights
Advancement Act on the other hand along
with court reform
uh and a an expanding democracy, I take
the voting rights bill over all all of
those bills, we have to save the
democracy.
>> Uh you know, as we have this
conversation, there is talk about voting
on Capitol Hill. There's a a piece of
legislation, the SCORE Act, that
particularly deals with athletics,
colleges, so on and so forth. And it was
a bipartisan bill, is my understanding.
I bring this up because the
Congressional Black Caucus um of which
you are a member. um the Congressional
Black Caucus on the House side, they
have said that they are not voting for
that legislation or any other
legislation um like it until the schools
and and and the administrators in the
south speak to what is happening uh on
the attack of for black representation
and black voters. I'm wondering your
take on this. There have been a lot of
folks that have said the athletes at
these schools in the south need to speak
up. Um, I am somebody that believes the
administrators and everybody needs to
speak up, not just the athletes and not
just the black athletes. But where do
you come down on this? Because there is
money in to be made in the sports
situation here. And I feel like if those
folks were speaking up about the attack
on our democracy, then maybe things
would be happening a little differently.
But maybe you disagree.
>> I think we all have a role to play and
I'm committed to doing my part. I I love
this country.
I'm willing to take my chances at the
end of the of the day with the people
with democracy.
And so, you know, that's that's what I'm
deeply committed to. I'm a child of the
South. I was born and raised in Georgia.
And, you know, I talk to Andy Young
about this all the time. You know,
people think about the Civil Rights
Movement, which gave us the Voting
Rights Act and the Civil Rights Act, as
something that saved black people. The
reality is it saved the country
>> cuz it was about democracy
>> and it especially helped the south. The
south would not be enjoying
>> the prosperity that it enjoys. The
Atlanta that we know that you just left
this weekend with the big football
stadiums and the superighways
and the innovation that's happening in a
whole range of human fields. All of that
would not be happening uh on the other
side of a Jim Crow curtain. And so we're
witnessing right now with this attack on
voting rights, Jim Crow and new clothes.
We owe it to the whole republic. We owe
it to our children uh to fight for it
with all of our might. We need all hands
on deck. And the good news is right now,
as I'm speaking, Georgia voters are
turning out in record numbers. We've got
two Supreme Court seats up. They're
taking it seriously.
[applause]
And at the end of the day, it's really
the people. It is the people who are
going to take their democracy back so
that we can move forward and get some of
these incredible things done. Whether
we're talking about child care or health
care or dealing with the housing crisis,
where we live in a country where the
average age of the firsttime homeowner
is age 40.
>> We can fix that, but we've got to think
a lot bigger than we've been thinking.
and um uh really take seriously the
moment that we're living in.
>> Let's talk about uh thinking a bit
bigger. You mentioned all of the things
that did get done um during the first
couple years of the after you came into
office in the Senate and there are some
things that didn't get done. You
mentioned child care. That was the
second part of Build Back Better.
And now what we talk about is the
affordability crisis in America is just
really the care economy. it just keeps
getting a new name. I'm wondering if
there are any lessons that you you
learned um during those negotiations
when it came to the the care economy
part of Build Back Better or even the
the failure of of the voting rights bill
in the Senate. What lessons did you
learn that you will take into this next
fight? Because there is a real chance
that Democrats um take back the United
States Senate and that's not something I
would have said a year ago.
>> Courage.
I mean, we you we need moral courage in
this moment. And at every inflection
point in this country, whether we're
talking about civil rights movement or
women's suffrage or the advancements of
member of members of the LGBTQ community
fighting for their humanity, it's just
been people who are willing to stand up
and center the concerns uh of ordinary
people. Uh and so that's what we need in
this moment. We we need that kind of
leadership. And you know, as I sit here,
here's what I'm not about to do. I'm not
about to give in to those who are trying
to weaponize despair because we'll win
some of these battles. And if we're
honest, we'll lose some. We'll win some
elections. We'll lose some elections.
But the battle we cannot lose is the
battle between hope and despair.
Because we lose that battle, then we
stop fighting. And then when we stop
fighting, we don't Here. Here's why I
can't stop. I mean, you you you see me
sitting here. I'm a United States
senator, but I'm also a product of good
public policy, good federal legislation.
I'm a Head Start alone long before any
of those other degrees. You know, I was
a kid in Head Start.
That program gave me access to literacy
and learning and a love of reading. And
then when I was in high school, my
principal summoned me to the office. So,
I thought I was in trouble. She wanted
to tell me about a program called
Upwardbound,
>> a good federal program that put a kid
growing up in public housing
on a college campus on Saturdays and on
the weekends. So, I knew I could I could
go to college because I was already on
the campus. And then when I got ready to
attend Morehouse, it was Pell Grants and
lowterest student loans uh that provided
a path for me. And so every day I'm
thinking about that kid because it would
be harder for me to do those things now.
>> All of those programs you just mentioned
have been cut under this administration.
>> Yeah. Attacks on the on the Department
of Education. And so I'm fighting for
that kid every single day who grew up on
Cape Street and kids like that all
across my state and all across our
country.
>> You know, I know we need to let you go.
The last thing I'll say is often um you
are a pastor as well as a senator. And
somebody said, "Mhm." And um you
pastored the same church uh in Ebenezer
Baptist Church as Dr. King.
>> That's right.
>> Once uh Helmmed. And I I have to wonder
oftentimes he is regularly quoted, you
know, the arc of the moral universe. It
bends towards just toward justice.
>> And I I find myself struggling right now
with the question of does it bend on its
own or do people like right like it it
doesn't just bend on its own. People
have to bend it. And so you talk about
hope. What gives you hope in this
moment? That the people are going to
bend the arc of the moral universe
toward justice.
>> Absolutely. It does not bend on its own.
That we we've got to bend that arc. And
it has always been the people. I I'll
close very quickly and nobody believes a
Baptist preacher when he says as I
close.
>> That usually means that means another 10
minutes, but he has votes. But look, I
walk around Atlanta, Georgia, which
means I get to hang out with giants.
>> Uh CT Vivian, I was watching a video of
him earlier today. The courage with
which he stood up to just brute force
fighting for voting rights.
John Lewis, my parishioner, is gone.
Andy Young is still with us. He tells me
the story about when they passed the
civil rights bill in the law. Dr. King
went to see President Johnson and and
Johnson was celebrating the fact that
they had passed a civil rights bill in
the law. Dr. King said, "Great." And
without skipping a beat, he said,
"That's great. We need a voting rights."
Didn't waste it didn't waste a moment.
And the president kept saying, "Martin,
you're right. I just don't have the
power to do that right now. I just don't
have the power." And they left the
meeting and the staff was feeling all
demoralized like some of us now and
dejected and said, "What are we going to
do?" The president said he can't get us
voting rights. He said he doesn't have
the power. Dr. King said, "Well, if the
president doesn't have the power, I
guess we're going to have to go to the
south and get him some." And so that's
what we got to do. We got to go to the
south and get the people some power. Uh
because when we stand up, we win.
>> That is a perfect place to end. Senator
Raphael Waro of the great state of
Georgia, thank you for your time.
>> Thank you. [applause]
Thank you.
[music]
Heat.
Please welcome Senate Democratic Leader
Chuck Schumer of New York.
[music]
Thank you everybody and good afternoon.
Thank you to the Center for American
Progress for bringing us all together,
especially near a tandem. Let's give a
shout out to her [applause and cheering]
for her steadfast leadership. Now,
you've heard a lot today about 2028,
about our party, our country, and the
ideas that will shape America's future.
But I want to start with the truth at
the center of it all. We don't get to
build the future if Donald Trump gets to
rig the rules and cherrypick who has a
voice in our democracy.
No economic agenda matters if Trump
intimidates voters.
No healthc care plan matters if
Republicans can choose the electorate
before the electorate chooses them.
No vision for 2028 matters if 26 is not
free and fair. So let me say this
plainly. The fight for the future is
already here and Democrats will win that
fight.
[applause]
Trump is already escalating attacks on
our elections for one reason. He knows
his agenda is failing. Costs are too
high. Families are getting squeezed. His
approval is falling. And the American
people are seeing through the same old
Donald Trump grift.
Rick the system, enrich himself. You saw
what he just did with his tax returns
while you were here. He's going to
exempt him and his family from all tax
investigation or prosecution. Can you
believe this?
With him, you never know how low he
goes. He's going to enrich himself and
he's going to blame everyone else and
dare people to stop him. He's fleecing
America's families to line his own
pockets without doing a thing about
costs, chaos, corruption endemic to his
administration.
And when Trump cannot win people over,
he tries to shut people out. When he
cannot defend his record, he attacks the
rules. And when he thinks he's losing,
he does what he has done his entire
life. He tries to cheat his way through.
For months, for months, Trump has been
sewing seeds of doubt about the
midterms, claiming that if Republicans
don't win, the elections must be rigged.
And last week when he asked whether he'd
deploy his masked agents to polling
stations for the midterms, Donald quote
said, Donald Trump said, quote, "I do
anything necessary."
And we all know what that means. Trump
will do everything necessary to make
sure he wins. Donald Trump and the GOP
know they're losing right now.
Inflation's hit its worst level in
years. The cost of everything from gas
to groceries to healthcare to housing is
through the roof. America and America
knows who's caused it. Donald Trump. 77%
of Americans blame their high cost of
living on the president. Only 30% of
them approve his handling of the economy
and even fewer believe that Trump's war
with Iran, which has sent gas soaring
towards $5 a gallon, has been
worthwhile.
If Republicans want to win back voters,
they could change their policies.
They could lower costs. They could
protect health care. They could stop
handing out favors to billionaires and
corrupt buddies. They could try just
once, just once
to make life easier for working
families.
With policies so unpopular, what do
wannabe autocrats do?
They launch a coordinated multiffront
campaign to subvert the election. That's
what the Save Act is all about.
Republicans call it election integrity.
It is not. It is voter suppression with
a suit and tie.
Right now in Congress, Trump's MAGA
majorities are trying to usher in Jim
Crow 2.0
by by pushing the Save Act to dis
disenfranchise tens of millions of
voters.
Up to now, we have thwarted them. But
the fight goes on.
Donald Trump
will not give up in his fight to subvert
the elections. And we must be ever, ever
vigilant. The Save Act would actually
purge millions of Americans. People in
this room would show up at their voting
place, the same place you voted at year
after year, and they'd say, "Sorry,
you're no longer on the books.
What do I do?" Well, next week, go to
the Board of Elections. It's estimated
over 20 million people, many of them
people of color, many of them in blue
areas,
would lose their right to vote under the
Save Act.
And it's all done through a screening
algorithm designed by Donald Trump,
Russell Vote, and Elon Musk's Doge
Squad.
As I've been saying for months, it's Jim
Crow 2.0. And when I say that, it steams
up the MAGA. They go after me because
they know it's true, and they also know
it's the only way they can win the
election.
The Save Act would make it harder for
eligible Americans to register to vote.
It would put up new barriers for working
people, seniors, students, rural voters,
married women who change their names,
and communities of color. The Save Act
would also dismantle the most common and
accessible ways to register to vote.
Mail and registration, gone. Registering
at churches and college campuses,
illegal. Registering when you get your
driver's license or sign up for social
security, no more. Under the Save Act,
the only path to register to vote once
they kick you off the rolls, would be in
person or at the state or local election
office, which is out of the question for
many voters. So, that's not about
protecting democracy. It's about
protecting Republicans from the American
people and from democracy.
And the Save Act is only one piece of
the scheme. Trump has elevated election
deniers. He has threatened election
officials. He has attacked mail voting.
He's his administration has gone after
voting voter data. He has targeted
democracy organizations.
It's amazing what they try to come up
with.
on the Supreme Court. The radical
Republicanappointed majority is doing
its part to gut the voting rights after
chipping away at it for years. Advancing
Trump's demand for Republicans to redraw
congressional districts to steal seats
mid mid decade is a blatant attempt
to prevent a Democratic majority in the
House. It's shameful.
Chief Justice Roberts, that ain't
calling balls and strikes.
And now the right-wing Supreme Court
is continuing to weaken voting rights to
invite more gerrymandering and open the
door to more chaos in many different
rulings before the midterms.
Let's call it what it is, a coordinated
campaign to rig the 2026 election before
a single vote is cast.
Trump's unprecedented plan to rig the
2026 election requires an unprecedented
response.
That's why I'm launching the Senate
Democrats Election Protection Task
Force, the most expansive election
protection effort our caucus has ever
undertaken.
This is not a messaging exercise.
because it's a real operation focusing
on what they can do before the election,
on the day of the election, and after
election day.
We're going to have lawyers and
observers and response rapid response
teams, cyber security experts, state and
local coordinate coordinating with state
and local elected officials already in
key battlegrounds and high-risisk
jurisdictions to protect voters,
election workers, to protect the count
and the certification process. Our task
force is bringing together 11 senators
and some of the sharpest election
experts in the country. People like Mark
Elias and Eric Holder and Venita Gupta
and Norm Eisen and Sky Perryman and so
many others. We're meeting and talking
on a weekly basis. We will work with
state and local officials. We will
identify where voters and election
workers are most at risk and we will be
ready to respond the moment Trump or his
allies try to intimidate voters,
interfere with the count, disrupt a
recount or corrupt the certification.
We will we are already preparing and we
will mount lawsuit after lawsuit after
lawsuit at every stage of the process.
Mark my words, we are ready
to protect free and fair elections at
every polling place, every precinct,
every county office, every courthouse.
And let me be clear, local officials run
elections. Voters decide elections.
Donald Trump does not.
This is not about process.
It's about power.
Republicans are already ignoring your
wages, your health care, your rent, your
grocery bill, and your freedom. Now,
they want to ignore your vote.
That's what Trump's election scheme is
all about. But in America, voters choose
their leaders. Leaders do not choose
their voters. So, in conclusion, the
fight for 2028 starts now in 2026.
and Senate Democrats are going to fight
like hell to make sure our elections
belong to the voters, not to Donald
Trump. Thank you. [applause]
[music]
>> [music]
>> Please welcome Senator Corey Booker of
New Jersey.
[music]
So, I want to thank everybody uh that's
here. It's so good to have a forum where
we're not just talking about what we're
against. We're talking about what we're
for. We're challenging the moral
imagination of our country about who we
can be, not just who we're against. So,
I want to talk about a quiet emergency
that's unfolding in this country and
it's making us sicker and poorer at the
same time. sicker because the food we
are feeding our families is driving the
worst chronic disease epidemic in the
history of our nation. and poorer
because a handful of big corporations
have created systems that drive up
grocery costs, drive up the cost of
insurance, drive up the cost of
prescription drugs Americans now depend
upon to manage diseases they should have
never gotten in the first place.
Big food companies, big pharmaceutical
companies profiting off of our pain,
getting richer while American families
get sicker and bills pile higher and
higher.
Every single day in America, 2,700
people die from diet related diseases.
That's nearly a million people dead
every year from what we eat. More than
die from Alzheimer's, accidents on our
highways, strokes combined.
And we in this country have normalized
it. Half of our adults are diabetic or
pre-diabetic. One in four teenagers
adult onset diabetes had to be changed
in name. Half the children alive in this
country right now today are projected to
be obese by the time they are 35.
Cancer rates in young people are
skyrocketing. Dementia rates in elderly
people are skyrocketing. And a chorus of
doctors, researchers, and experts are
now tying much of this American health
crisis to ultrarocessed foods Americans
are eating every single day. Diet
related chronic disease is now the
number one killer of Americans more than
guns, more than cars, more than opioids,
more than anything.
We don't have a health care system in
this country.
We have a sick care system. We wait for
people to get sick and then we charge
them a fortune to manage the symptoms of
an illness the big food companies
engineered on their dinner plates. And
here is the part that should make every
taxpayer in America furious, ticked off
because we are paying for this crisis
twice. We pay on the front end when our
tax dollars incentivize farmers to grow
massive amounts of corn and soybeans
which are primarily used to feed animals
on factory farms or as ingredients in
cheap ultrarocessed foods that are
making us sick. Then we pay a second
time at the back end when those same
Americans show up at the hospital with
type 2 diabetes or other ailments.
Think about this. Nearly one out of
every $3 in the federal budget now goes
to health care. Type 2 diabetes alone,
just one of many diet related diseases,
costs us taxpayers $300 billion a year
in direct medical costs. And that's just
diabetes. Cancer rates up, dementia
rates up, hypertension up, heart disease
up, kidney failure, fatter fatty liver
disease in children, all of it
skyrocketing.
Put it all together and we are spending
trillions of dollars every year treating
diseases that would not exist at this
scale if big corporations had not built
a food system designed to make us sick.
And at every step of this crisis,
someone is getting rich off of it. The
food companies that make us sick, the
insurance companies that ration our
care, and the prescription drug
companies charging Americans the highest
prices in the world for medications this
broken system makes you need,
profiting
off our pain.
We are subsidizing the sickness. Then we
are subsidizing
the medicine. And American families,
American taxpayers are losing twice.
Take for example my own neighborhood in
New York. A kid walks into the corner
bodega. And a Twinkie like product is
cheaper than an apple. Let that sink in.
Because of what we subsidize, the
Twinkie-like product is cheaper than the
apple. Multinational corporations have
built a food system where the food that
will kill us is cheaper than the food
that will save us. And they use our tax
dollars to make it that way. This is not
the free market. This is not by
accident. This is a policy choice.
Corporate lobbyists wrote it this way.
Both parties signed it and the American
people are paying for it with their
wallets, with their wasteland lines,
and with their lives. So, here's my big
idea, and it actually fits on a bumper
sticker. It's food is medicine, and it's
time to heal America. H E A L. Healthy
eating for American lives. It's not a
slogan. It's a policy agenda. And here's
what it looks like.
Three moves right now. Number one,
double the bucks. Right now, a tiny
pilot program lets some SNAP recipients
double a portion of their benefits when
they buy fresh fruits and vegetables. It
It works. I met a woman on an urban farm
in my city, Newark, whose diabetes
reversed because of the abundance of it.
I met another woman on that farm whose
gut disease where she paid $700 a month
on medication only $100 came from her
600 from the taxpayer. That disease
vanished once she was able to purchase
all of those fruits and vegetables. We
need to scale that program up. Make it
universal. SNAP dollars spent on real
food fruit real vegetables. Real food
from a real farm counts double. We turn
a $113 billion grocery program into the
largest preventative medicine program in
American history. And we make healthy
food more affordable for families that
need it most. Number two,
feed the kids and the troops, right? The
federal government is the largest food
buyer on the planet Earth. USDA,
Pentagon, school lunches, military
bases, VA hospitals. We spend billions
of dollars a year. And too often we use
it to buy ultrarocessed slop laden with
chemicals and serve it to our children
and our soldiers. That ends, every meal
the federal government pays for will be
a healthy meal sourced from American
family farmers. and we restore and we
expand the local farmtoschool
and farmtof food bank money that the
Trump administration cancelled. And
look, while we're talking about kids,
let me say it plainly. Hunger in the
wealthiest nation in human history is a
moral obscenity.
No child in America should go to bed
hungry. No child in America should be
fed poison because poison is all their
family can afford. Ending child hunger
is one of the great unfinished tasks of
our nation. The fight is about the child
tax credit. This is a fight about wages.
This is a fight about housing. This is a
fight for big ideas for another speech.
But know this, feeding our kids is
healthy food. That that's where it
starts. And so number three, and
finally, pre-tax
produce. If you can spend pre-tax
dollars right now on band-aids and
aspirin in your health savings account,
you should be able to spend pre-tax
dollars on broccoli and blueberries.
Food is medicine. Let the tax code
finally treat it that way. And that's
it. That's the big idea. Double the
bucks. Feed our kids and our troops,
right? leverage all that money from the
federal government and pre-tax produce.
Scaling up programs like SNAP double
bucks and re-imagining federal food
procurement would not only pri provide
tens of millions of Americans with
accessible affordable foods, it would
also provide transformative economic
opportunities for family farmers across
our country. Since the last farm bill in
2018,
150,000 American family farmers have
gone out of business. These investments
would enable farmers to grow healthy
food for their neighbors and build
resilient local and regional food
systems. So, let me end by saying
something to my fellow Democrats. Some
of you might be surprised that I came
here to talk about food. Don't be.
Because while we're debating other big
things, millions of American moms and
dads turned their attention to what is
on their dinner plate. And a movement
called MA caught fire in the vacuum we
left behind.
We should not be fighting that movement.
We should be telling those loving moms
and dads that they
are right. Write about the chemicals.
Write about the ultrarocessed foods.
Write about the chronic disease.
Write that something in America is
profoundly broken. And we need to talk
about how those moms and dads are being
betrayed by the current administration
who says it supports them while its
lawyers walk into the Supreme Court to
protect pesticide companies while they
cut funding for school lunches and
betray those moms and dads.
I've said it before about other issues.
This is not left or right. It's right
versus wrong.
This is America versus big corporations
who are making us sick. And it's time
for Democrats not to lead from the left,
but lead America as a whole. Because
earning back trust means showing up
where people are actually living.
And people in America live in their
homes and at their kitchen tables. And
too often, because of this broken
system, they live at the pharmacy
counter.
So, I'm going to say it simple. We can
keep paying twice, subsidizing the
sickness, then subsidizing the medicine,
watching another generation of American
kids grow sicker than their parents, and
watching American families grow poorer
paying for it. Or we can decide that the
wealthiest nation in human history will
not also be the sickest. and that we
will no longer accept a system where
corporations get rich profiting off of
our pain. Food is medicine. It is time
to heal America for real. It is time to
speak to our entire nation who has more
in common, has common pain, but they're
looking for leaders who bring forth
again our common purpose. Thank you.
Heat. Heat.
Please welcome Senator Corey Booker,
former chair of the Council of Economic
Adviserss, CAP Senior Fellow. fellow
Jared Bernstein and co-founder and
partner center view partners Blair Efron
and as moderator CAP president and CEO
Nerra Tanden.
[music] How's everyone doing?
Great. Are you still hanging in?
>> [applause]
>> Uh thank you Senator Booker for those uh
excellent remarks. I appreciate new
idea, simple idea, powerful idea. Really
appreciate that.
>> I understood the assignment. [laughter]
>> Excellent. Uh so this panel we're
changing a little bit. We're talking
about uh the economy overall. We talked
about cost of living this morning and in
this panel our goal is to talk about um
what's happening in the economy and also
how do we create more opportunity
economywide. So Jared, I'm going to
start with you. Um when you look at the
broad data, it doesn't look like the
worst of times in 70 years, but consumer
confidence is at a 70-year low. Why is
everyone angry?
Well, let me take you back uh you've
been there to uh when we used to go out
to uh WHNL, White House North Lawn, and
talk to cameras about uh some new data
report and we might be
>> when you were chair of the Council of
Economic Advisors for President Biden.
>> Thank you. and uh the uh you know the
GDP report or strong jobs report or
inflation was 9% and now it's two and a
half percent and we would be talking
about these improvements and people
would be essentially thinking well okay
so now you're telling me that my bag of
groceries which is already too expensive
is getting more expensive less quickly
than it used to uh and the cost of
living was huge for folks folks and they
remembered their prices and damn it they
wanted them back. And so I've spent a
lot of time and near I know you have as
well. We've done a lot of this at CAP on
um trying to solve the affordability
crisis and we've heard lots of good
commentary about that today. But I
actually think the answer to your
question is why people are so mad.
Affordability is a symptom and it's a
symptom of three large structural
problems I'm going to name and not give
details on just in the interest of time.
And that's the fact that there is an
implicit social contract that if you
work hard, you play by the rules, you go
to work, maybe your spouse does too,
probably your kids, uh, if they're old
enough do as well, you ought to be able
to not just get by, but to save
something and be able to access some
future opportunity. And when that
contract breaks, and it's it's it's
broken um, I think now particularly, but
it's as as as we heard earlier from
Senator Warren, it's been that way for a
while. Um, that's one source. Part two,
and boy, this 1.8 billion slush fund
that we were just reading about, classic
example of what I'm about to say. Part
two, game is rigged. All right, so
social contract broken game rigged. Part
three,
look, you could say part one and two,
you could blame Republicans for that, I
guess, to some extent. But part three,
nobody's got your back. Who's got my
back? If I'm somebody trying to get by,
I like to feel that if there's barriers
to my getting ahead, there's
vulnerabilities that I experience,
there's discrimination, there's uh
inaccessibility to upward ladders of
mobility, you need to know that
somebody's out there trying to help you
in much the ways we we've heard from
folks today, including Senator Booker
just a few minutes ago. And I think if
you put all that together, the
affordability, cost of living problem on
top of these three structural issues of
a broken implicit social contract, uh
the fact that uh the game looks rigged
and nobody's got your back, you can go
pretty far to explaining what it makes
people so angry.
>> Thanks, uh Blair. Um I think a lot of
people, including Jared, have written
about the K-shaped economy, how the top
uh you know, 20 30 40% are doing well.
the bottom 60 70% really struggling, 50
60 70% struggling. Uh you work with a
lot of business leaders. Um how can we
over the long term have sustainable
growth if a large share of the economy
or a large share of the population and
the economy are not keeping up or have a
sense of optimism about the future?
>> So it's very simple. We can't keep
growing the economy. We don't have that.
Uh the upper third right now just since
COVID uh has 6% more wealth than it had
during COVID. Obviously stock markets at
a record high corporate profits remain
robust. That's one third the two/3s
last month real wages flat and you point
out earlier near about uh confidence.
So, in order to Jared mentions the
social contract, it's true and if you're
going to want to keep growing the
economy, you need broad-based growth.
Now, I would tell you um most business
leaders absolutely recognize that. And I
think that with the right incentives
would be encouraged to
put in programs that would start to help
the bottom twothirds. So, what does that
mean? One, if you're making a lot more
money as a company, you have to figure
out how to share it.
>> Okay? Whether it's
>> excellent idea
>> not [laughter] so hard right whether
it's um in around wages whether it's
employment two the idea of skills I
don't think the private partner public
partner partnership makes a lot of sense
I do think the private sector knows how
to reskill retrain and they know where
the jobs are so the idea that the
government would provide incentives to
make that happen I think would be uh
highly attractive and um you know
finally what I would say is this
question obviously around technology and
I say technology technology not AI. I
think often there's a confusion. Um
workers are scared because their skills
are getting in certain places outdated.
Um so what does that mean? AI has two
impacts. Either you can have companies
think about it as productivity tool
i.e. take cost out or you can think
about it as a revenue tool. What can we
do as a company to uh foster even more
growth? That to me over the long term is
how companies will get rewarded and how
um we'll see the greatest economic
impact.
>> Um Senator Booker, uh you have um well,
let me start with Jared. Jared has
talked about um the idea of getting
people's back and the idea that the
social contract is fraying. An important
element of that is people have you a lot
of people are gaining from the stock
market but not most people a lot of
people aren't um aren't invested in the
stock market you've had uh you've
champion ideas we appreciate the new
idea today but I also want to recognize
as Governor Nuome did earlier your ideas
around sharing wealth more broadly uh
baby bonds other ways in which we can
ensure um not just a few but everyone
gains from um the kind of levels we're
seeing in the stock market and
elsewhere. Um in terms of getting
people's back, what ideas do you think
would help in that regard?
>> Well, look, I I want to frame this
really quickly that we are a nation that
is yet again at a point where we are at
a crossroads. Either the American
experiment will begin to decay and die
and I would argue it's been decaying for
a long time or we in our generation with
a new generation of leaders as the last
baby boomers are beginning to leave the
stage. John Lewis, Jesse Jackson, I can
go through. We could either renew
America like past generations did at
times of darkness and crisis. We're at
that crossroads. To me, this reminds me
of the 1930s when most black people in
America were Republicans and a new guy
came along and said, "The deal is not
working anymore. Everybody is getting
screwed. It's time for a new deal."
Coming out of the depression, we saw a
radical change in our politics with a
new vision for America that made my
parents live, my grandparents lived in
Detroit. Thm switch the entire city from
Democrat from Republican to Democrat
because suddenly you had a party that
was speaking to the rural farmer and the
urban factory worker which my
grandfather was on on assembly lines. We
are exactly in that point and there's so
many parallels between the massive uh uh
uh expansion in wealth disparities, the
cor concentration of corporate power and
so in the secrets of that and remember
Democrats coming out of the New Deal
held durable majorities in Congress for
over 40 years until Tip O'Neal and the
Reagan era ended the era of shared
growth where America had the largest
expansion of the middle class before. So
what I am saying right now is some of
the same pillars of ideas. They need to
now be ideas for the 21st century and a
renewal of our country. That means a lot
of the same things. Breaking up big
concentrated corporate power. Ending
mass corruption. Every branch of your
government at the federal level is
seriously corrupted. When Supreme Court
justices can take unlimited gifts from
billionaires. Corrupted. when senators
can trade stocks and corporate packs are
putting unconscionable amounts of money
into our system right now, raining it
down. It's one of the reasons why I
don't take corporate packs. I don't take
issue area packs. And then I don't even
need to talk about the executive branch.
Donald Trump is showing America how you
could grift off of that office. So there
has to be the Democratic Party defined
themselves by simple big ideas that
inspired my grandfather's generation to
to run towards the Democratic Party and
actually solve the problems that we
have. One of those pillars has got to be
raising the floor in this country so we
banish forever the idea of a working
poor. If you work in America, you should
be able to meet the basic needs of your
family. Another one of those pillars has
got to be an anti-corruption pillar that
puts term limits on the Supreme Court,
that ends this kind of unlimited cash
flowing into our politics, that actually
creates fair maps, all the things that
are corrupting our democracy. And
remember, corruption drives up prices.
Look at anybody from the oil industry
all the way to the pharmaceutical
industry who are writing the rules. And
then finally, what what was inspiring
about America more than any other
country was that this was the best
nation to be born poor into or
workingass because when my grandfather
was born and raising my parents'
generation, 95% did better than their
parents. But all of those things we did
to give them a a a lift to make this the
best place to raise a family, affordable
child care, God, prenatal care,
affordable college. I could go through
all the things that made this the best
place to be born uh have been eroded or
eviscerated or the prices are out of the
reach of people. Those three things are
vital that you have a vision that makes
this the nation where everybody who is
born feels like they have a fair shot.
And in each of those buckets, there are
policy things we can discuss. But if the
Democratic Party doesn't make it simple
and plain that inspires the moral
imagination of this country, we will
miss an opportunity to save this nation
and get it on the right track and and
and we could go to massive extremes on
either side. Uh that like they had in
the 30s and the 40s with Nazis rallies,
anti-semitism off the charts or even
some people on the far left were talking
about storming the capital and taking
back our government. the middle has got
to hold and that means making a vision
for this country that speaks to the
whole nation.
>> Thank you. Thank you. [applause]
Thank you for that. Uh Senator Booker
talked about um basically our
institutions have come from the 1930s.
Most of the federal agencies come from
the 1930s or the 1960s. We have one more
recent. We have two more recent.
Consumer Financial Protection Board,
great agency. DHS maybe not so great. Um
but Jared, how do you look at the need
to renew or think aresh about how we
basically oversee our economic
institutions and what you know take just
jumping off of what Senator Booker said,
what do you think we should be doing
going forward to ensure opportunity is
real for everyone? I think that in the
time that uh in our history that Senator
Booker just took us through with great
analysis and great passion, my favorite
combination uh is a time when
institutions and policies were worker
centered, family centered, mobility
centered. So the labor department
actually thought about ways in which we
could increase unionization. Now, one of
the pieces we recently wrote for CAP
that uh I thought I thought was
important, I was a co-author, so maybe I
can't say that, but my the work that my
other my co-authors did was important.
Uh
asked what would happen to union density
in this country if we moved to sectoral
bargaining. And the answer is it would
double or triple. And that's a policy
change uh that we could make. And if you
want workers to have a better chance at
getting a fair share of the pie, uh
that's what unions do. Uh so that's
that's part of of the solution. And by
the way, one of the things we cited in
that piece is that there is a lot more
demand for that kind of collective
bargaining for more power in the
workplace, which shouldn't surprise
anyone uh than than people are able to
access because the playing field is so
tilted. That's another institutional
reform. You know, we have a national
labor relations board that is more often
than not on on on the wrong side of
these issues, you know, when Republicans
are in charge. So, uh, I I think it's I
don't think it's particularly
complicated. I think I could take you
through pretty much every, uh,
government agency and ask the question,
is this worker centered? Is this
mobility centered? Is this affordability
centered? What's the plan for housing
affordability? And I don't mean over two
or three years, but I mean helping
people with rent in the near term while
we push out the supply curve in the long
term. What's the plan for health care
affordability? What's the plan for child
care? In the spirit of earlier comments,
it's it's these institutions, as you
said, near these institutions remain in
place, but they've been hollowed out
because they've lost this worker
centered, family centered mission.
>> Thank you for that. Um uh and also just
to build on both of your comments, um I
think one great example of how as a
country we did invest was the GI Bill of
Rights. We had people um coming back
from the war.
>> My father
>> and
>> wouldn't be here without it.
>> Yeah. And we as a country decided it was
it was part of the sacred obligation to
provide opportunities like access to
housing, access to college. Um and that
con that level of investment contributed
to an incredibly strong economy for the
country, for families, and for business.
Um we've in in the years since uh we've
had multiple rounds of tax cuts for the
wealthiest Americans and there is a lot
less support for working families.
>> We disinvested.
>> We disinvested. Absolutely. So as we
look at how to make the economy grow
grow strongly for business for but for
consumers for families Blair what are
some ideas on taxes to make the world
more fair
>> good
>> um and investments to make to create
more opportunity
>> and you said your father you got to
thank your mother also [laughter] um so
there's obviously a a laundry list I
think the key thing in business
generally era is war happens when you
think in transformational ways.
>> You want to just hold it closer.
>> Uh transformational ways than in
tactical ways. Okay. So the first thing
to do is to
uh get us back on uh the footing that
this country's always had until until
recently. Immigration
you have 50% of all CEOs
were either born out of the country or
their parents born out of the country.
it makes no sense to figure out uh how
to keep them out instead of how to keep
them in. You have six to seven million
jobs that need to be filled. You need uh
the innovation that comes from a lot of
our uh immigrants um who end up staying
here. Big area number one. Big area
number two, trade. Obviously, there's
been a ton of discussion around it. Uh
we want to in a planful way figure out
how to uh back off of tariffs. um has to
be plentiful because you have to glide
it down. Um but that's been a toll tax
on Americans. And I know people say,
"Well, you haven't actually recognized
it." Actually, we have, but companies
have done a good job making up for it.
Okay. The fact of the matter is it's
probably half point worth of growth.
>> Um R&D, it makes no sense for the
government, which has always been doing
moonshots, to cut back R&D. Let's get
the $30 billion back into NIH into Okay.
Um you mentioned taxes. Fact of the
matter is it's regressive. We should
think about a system that is more
broad-based. That means more consumers.
And I'm not sure that a tax code with
37% at the top rate at 650 odd thousand
given the increases in in wealth is
actually the right way to be thinking
about it today. And then finally,
business likes certainty. The idea that
we know what we're investing against for
the long term really does matter and you
want to do it in a way that we attract
capital globally. You don't want our
friends to quote have to work with us as
opposed to want to work with us. It
makes a big difference.
>> Um but I will also say this. I do think
the business community at large
recognizes and would love something that
invests for long-term strategic future
rather than quarter quarter. I think we
can reook everything.
>> Thanks. Thank you, Blair. And then, um,
Senator Booker, uh, I'd love you to just
close us out, um, on on ideas that you
think are important for us to chart a
path forward to creating more
opportunity for all Americans. Um,
because I know you have so many.
>> Yeah. Look, I first of all, there's a
there is a helplessness that people feel
right now, which I think is intentional
to make people believe that we cannot
get our way out of these problems. We
are here, in fact, American history is
this perpetual testimony to the
achievement of impossible things against
impossible odds. But what was really
important to me and the reason why I'm
such a raving fan of my friend here
since law school is because some people
thinks we need to get radical and
extreme and abandon the very things that
have defined America for generations.
The things that a black family from the
poor south put their faith in when they
came up to the north and found
opportunities. And so what you just
heard were a few ideas that if we were
able to implement them would make
radical change uh bargaining by sector,
doubling or massively expanding the
child tax credit. Not a sexy policy, but
we know factually that would cut child
poverty in America in half. And kids
that are raised above the poverty line
have massive more earnings over a
lifetime. It is possible. We can do this
with common sense pra rad radically
pragmatic ideas. But the one last idea
I'm going to leave you with is maybe one
of the more controversial things said
because I'm saying it at a time that
Republicans control the House, the
Senate, and the White House. When we do
this big effort to win an election and
suddenly Joe Biden, for example, has
three, one of the big things that are
stopping big pragmatic ideas on
immigration. We know protect strong
border protection, but the thing that's
going to grow our economy the quickest
is having people who are smart and
hardworking into our country. The thing
that stops it is something in the Senate
called the filibuster. And I am telling
you right now, it is the biggest
impediment that is to big ideas getting
done, pragmatic ideas, and is also the
thing that's driving the most cynicism.
as I go back to a black community in New
York who feels like, God, we rallied. We
were the biggest voting block uh in the
country, but we're not seeing the
change. The filibuster needs to be not
eliminated, but reformed to a real
filibuster. If you were going to stop
legislation, you need to be like Mr.
Smith going to Washington and standing
on that floor and take it for somebody
who stood for over 25 hours. Make it
hard.
Those are the kind of big ideas that
will enable the American way to happen
again. This is the challenge NRA and
this is why I love you. It is the
American dream is in crisis. It is time
to redeem the dream with big ideas that
work.
>> Love you back sir and I will say
[applause]
you need to ensure as you're saying and
you are doing democracy delivers. Thank
you. Thank you.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Heat up
here. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> Please welcome back to the stage CAP
president and CEO Nerra Tanden.
>> [music]
>> Thanks everybody. How you doing? Hey,
what an amazing day. What an amazing
day. And we are so thrilled for our uh
our home run hitter here, Governor Wes
Moore. Uh, our next speaker has presided
over one of the most significant public
safety turnarounds in the country. When
Governor West Moore took office in
Maryland over three years ago, Baltimore
was averaging close to a homicide a day.
Non-fatal shootings were spiking.
Autothefts were near record highs.
Today, the picture looks extremely
different. Statewide homicides are down
44% since Governor Moore took office.
Non-fatal shootings down 40%. Robberies
down 25% alone. I used to track these
statistics very closely for President
Biden and I know this data well from
Baltimore. They are uh Baltimore and
Maryland are really hallmarks for the
country. I also think it's important for
all of us to remember that as we think
about the agenda for the future, it is
hard for people to hear us if they don't
think we understand
core issues like how to keep them safe.
So, in this whole day, I am so glad we
have Governor Moore here to talk about
his record and his vision to ensure that
we care and are actually delivering on
public safety. Governor Moore proved
something too easily forgotten. That you
can be tough on violent crime and
serious about prevention. That you can
support law enforcement and community
organizations. That public safety is a
right, not a privilege, and that we are
all invest in invested in ensuring all
our communities are safe. Please join me
in welcoming the amazing Governor Moore
to the stage.
>> [music]
[music]
[applause]
>> Hi everybody. Good afternoon.
Um Ner, I just want to first want to say
thank you. Um thank you not just for for
the introduction but also for your
remarkable leadership and just for the
leadership for Center for American
Progress. uh that that it's not just
that ideas matter, but you all continue
to show the results matter. And so I am
deeply humbled and honored uh to be able
to be here and to spend a little bit of
time talking about something that is
fundamental to our sense of belonging
and to our sense of community and that
is the issue of public service uh and
public safety that I know I you know I I
learned uh in this role uh that you know
that that when my phone rings in the
middle of the night I'm never about to
get good news that uh no one ever calls
me at 3 in the morning and says says,
"Hey, go. I got great news for you."
It's always the things that will break
your heart are the things that will wake
you up. And I know that uh ever so often
when my phone rings in the middle of the
night, and I first saw that in my first
year as governor when I got one of those
calls from the mayor of Baltimore City,
Brandon Scott.
And when I heard his voice on the other
end, he told me that there had been a
mass shooting in Baltimore's Brooklyn
neighborhood.
The more I learned about what happened
that night, I learned that not only was
it the largest mass shooting in
Baltimore's history,
I also learned that some of the people
who pulled the trigger
were children.
And I learned that every single one of
the victims
were children.
Every one of them.
That when I went to go to the hospital
to go spend time with people who were
just recovering from surgeries,
people who doctors were working to save
their lives,
it was not lost to me that every single
one of the people that I visited was a
child.
And the thing that most got me also was
not just the heartbreak of that moment,
but was also the days and the months
that followed that I realized that there
was a much bigger tragedy that we could
not ignore.
The bigger tragedy that we couldn't
ignore was this, that in that area in
Baltimore, in Brooklyn,
about one in two children are growing up
in poverty.
one and two
and that we'd seen similar numbers in
Brooklyn for well over a decade
and the people in Brooklyn knew it
that this was an area that was left
behind.
And you cannot understand what happened
that night
without understanding all of the nights
that came before. You cannot just simply
mourn the micro
if you're not willing to do something
about the macro.
And for me, this issue
was and continues to be deeply personal
because I grew up in a community that
was overpoliced.
That I felt handcuffed from my wrist by
the time I was 11 years old.
that I lived in a community where we
were both scared of the kids with the
guns
and scared of the police officers with
the badge,
that the pitch of a police siren
had a different tone depending on what
neighborhood that you called home.
And that people should not have to
choose
between feeling safe in their skin
or feeling safe in their communities.
That's not how things should work.
And so when I took office in 2023, we
made a pledge that this was something
that we were going to focus in on every
single day because if people do not feel
safe, they will not come. And if people
do not feel safe, they will not stay.
And so as Nerra mentioned that Maryland
was suffering from an absolute crisis of
violence, but even more dangerous than
that crisis of violence, what we saw was
that there was a crisis of apathy
towards the violence. that the pain that
people in Maryland were feeling was no
longer a piercing pain.
It was now a chronic one,
one that people just became accustomed
to.
That Baltimore was averaging almost a
murder a day, that Maryland families did
not feel safe,
and that people were then being asked to
choose
between who you support to make sure
that our communities were safe. Do you
support law enforcement or do you
support building stronger communities?
People were forcing us to pick a side.
And I realized and I still believe and I
want to be very clear that often times
the ones who are telling us to pick a
side on public safety are ones who
actually have no desire of actually
addressing public safety.
That too often it's people who have no
interest in strengthening public safety.
that too often it's the ones who do not
live in the communities who are telling
the communities to pick a side that too
often that it's people who think this is
an ideology or some kind of academic
exercise.
Do you know who does not ask you to
choose a side?
The people that this is their everyday
reality.
The people who actually live in the
communities.
So I'm clear. I do not take my talking
points when it comes to public safety
from a political party or from someone
who wants to do an academic exercises
about it.
And in the wake of Brooklyn,
the state of Maryland decided that we
would take a different type of approach.
In the wake of Brooklyn, the state of
Maryland decided that we would take an
all of the- above approach when it came
to public safety. And that all of the
above approach would rest on three
commitments.
The first commitment was accountability.
The second commitment was intervention
or basically increasing resources to the
people who are protecting our
communities.
And the third was prevention
and increasing the opportunities for
those who are living in the communities
where violent crime actually exists in
the first place.
And first,
we focus on accountability.
That I've been clear that loving and
supporting your young people does not
mean abandoning accountability.
Accountability is actually how you show
support.
This is what our administration passed
and signed
when it came to making sure that when a
child
is in trouble in need, the answer is not
just to tell them that it's okay,
but that accountability must take a
holistic form in the way that we are
addressing it. That for too long, our
system was not holding our young people
accountable and it was not setting them
up to be rehabilitated either.
that the Juvenile Law Reform Act of 2024
brought together those two things
because I believe in second chances.
I'm the recipient of second and third
and eighth and ninth chances,
but I will not tolerate lawlessness.
And next week I will sign the Youth
Charging Reform Act that right now too
many young people in Maryland are
automatically charged in adult court and
they will wait an average of four months
before a judge even decides whether
their case belongs in adult court or
juvenile court. And in some cases, we've
got children who were waiting much
longer.
85% of those cases ultimately get
dismissed or sent back to juvenile
court. But here's the thing, those
months matter.
And that delay matters.
It matters to that child. It matters to
that community. It matters to that
family. And it matters to the entire
system because it means that
accountability comes too late. It means
that services to support that child come
too late. It means that we miss that
critical window to change behavior and
to improve outcomes.
Now, the most serious offenses like
murder and rape and carjacking, they
will stay in adult court as they should.
But for the cases that belong in
juvenile court,
we are going to act faster and make sure
that accountability can actually mean
something.
We're going to deliver accountability
faster. We're going to make better use
of our juvenile system. We're going to
deliver safer outcomes to the
communities across our state
and we're going to do it now.
The second
increased intervention and providing
support to those who keep us safe.
Today, Maryland is delivering record
funding to local law enforcement, over
$124
million this year alone.
That's money for new equipment. That is
money for overtime. That is money for
sustained backing and sustainably
backing officers who have been asking
for it for years. I am a deep believer
that you can have a law enforcement
agency that moves with appropriate
intensity and absolute integrity and
full accountability and you do not have
to compromise on those things.
[applause]
And that's money that's matched by the
oversight and accountability that make
sure that every dollar is delivering
what it says it's going to deliver. And
our law enforcement professionals
will be expected to follow the highest
of standards.
We made a landmark investment in the
Baltimore State's Attorney's Office. We
back their work of prosecuting violent
crime.
We asked them to do something different
which is actually to partner on re-entry
programming for people who are coming
home because the reality is 95% of
people who are incarcerated they are
coming home. So we must do a better job
of both preparing them for re-entry but
also preparing society for their
re-entry as well.
That the work of public safety does not
end on arrest nor on conviction. that if
you want fewer crimes tomorrow, it means
you break the cycle today.
Maryland is now one of the only states
in the country that hires state lawyers
and partners them inside of the US
Attorney's Office. They work
shoulder-to-shoulder with federal
prosecutors to ensure that violent
criminals are held accountable
and to connect federal and state and
local law enforcement in real time. We
have built out the Maryland Criminal
Intelligence Network since its
inception. It has disrupted more than
3,900
criminal organizations. It has removed
more than 4,800 illegal firearms from
our streets. It has seized nearly $80
million in drugs and cash and other
assets.
It's done what it's intended to do
where just a few weeks ago I stood with
the sheriffs of Worcester and Wcomo
County. And for those who don't know
Maryland, uh, Worcester and WCOM County
aren't necessarily Democratic areas.
These are two rural counties in reliably
Republican areas of our state.
These are both counties that I lost by
thousands of votes.
But public safety doesn't care about
politics.
It cares about results.
And after a year'sl long investigation,
we dismantled a drug trafficking organ
drug trafficking or organization pushing
narcotics across the Eastern Shore and
Baltimore and Pennsylvania and Virginia
and Delaware. We brought together 13
federal, state, and local agencies. We
delivered more than 80 search warrants.
We seized more than 42 kilograms of
cocaine, one of the largest seizures in
the history of Wcomako County.
and we worked together to make sure we
didn't just get the job done, but we
sent a message that if we said it, we
meant it.
But we also know that delivering
intervention doesn't just mean
supporting law enforcement.
Because we've also dedicated funding for
community violence intervention programs
like the Baltimore Safe Streets
Initiative.
This program deploys credible messengers
to provide support for those at risk of
committing crime. It helps to address
the issue of retaliatory crime
because we know that often times that's
the crime and the violence that we are
talking about. It is retaliatory by
nature. So those who are closest to the
community have got to be the ones who
were first at the table.
Third, prevention.
We dedicated our time to get tough on
the root causes of crime.
That in Maryland, nearly half of all
drug arrests in the 2000s were for
cannabis.
Black Marylanders were three times more
likely to be arrested for cannabis than
white Marylanders before legalization.
And every one of those misdemeanor
convictions was making it harder to get
a job, making it harder to find housing,
making it harder to start a business,
making it harder to come home.
In 2022, our state voted to have a
recreational cannabis market. And so I
pledged that we would make sure that the
cannabis market was rolled out equitably
and safely.
But I also knew that I refused to
celebrate the benefits of legalization
if we did not also address the
consequences of criminalization.
And that's why in 2024,
I signed pardons for more than 175,000
cannabis convictions. It was the largest
mass pardon in the history of the United
States of America. [applause]
Because you cannot reduce violent crime
if you're not addressing the conditions
in the communities where the violence
actually exists.
That means investing state resources in
a way that will strengthen communities.
By delivering more support for public
education, by building out job training
programs and re-entry programs, by
supporting behavioral health, and by
fighting child poverty.
It's why our administration raised the
minimum wage, giving over 160,000
Maryland workers a pump in the a pay
raise bump. It's why we have expanded
the child tax credit and the earn income
tax credit inside of the state of
Maryland. It is why we launched the most
ambitious state-led place-based
anti-poverty effort in this country's
history called the Enough Initiative.
And by the way, Enough is an acronym.
stands for engaging neighborhoods,
organizations, unions, governments, and
households or basically liy everybody.
And the premise of enough is simple.
Our communities provide the vision. The
state, the private sector, and
philanthropy provide the support,
and not the other way around as it's
often done.
We have delivered almost $70 million to
28 communities across our state. These
are urban, rural, and suburban
communities. And these communities have
been dealing with the issue of not just
concentrated poverty, but generational
poverty.
That if you looked at the poverty map in
2023,
it's not just that it's everywhere.
It's that if you looked at the same map
in 2013, it looks exactly the same
or in 2003.
The only difference is the red areas
have just gotten redder.
concentrated generational poverty.
These areas and communities are now
developing their own plans to address
poverty in their own communities. Every
dollar that the state has put in through
enough philanthropy and state agencies
have put in three more. That turns $70
million into nearly $280 million. And
the community decides where that capital
goes. If you look at McGeldery Park on
the east side of Baltimore, a community
organization called Tandia Family used
their enough grant to launch a program
called the drug-free down the hill. It's
a neighborhood patrol, but not like one
that you probably have heard about.
They actually actively find people who
are struggling with addiction.
They connect them with recovery and job
training and housing. They offer free
haircuts and food and clothing.
They provide mental health supports.
They came up with the idea,
not the state.
Earlier, I talked about how we
strengthen coordination amongst law
enforcement to go after people who hurt
our community, but we also strengthen
coordination between those who are
working to help our communities, too.
That public safety requires violence
prevention, direct violence
intervention, and maintaining
accountability. And that's why we
created a program called the Thrive
Academy that focuses on youth that have
the highest probability of either being
the victim or the perpetrator of gun
violence.
The youth who are going through the most
challenges and now we have seen that
nine out of 10 participants have not had
a gunrelated offense post enrollment.
And for the first time ever, Maryland's
Department of Public Safety, Human
Services, and Juvenile Services are
working together to integrate violence
prevention.
That's more than 2,000 families
concentrated in 14 zip codes across our
state that are receiving supports.
Communities in Hagerstown and Western
Maryland, Salisbury, the Eastern Shore,
East Baltimore, Capitol Heights,
District Heights, and Prince George's
County.
that regardless of your background, we
are going to focus on your future.
That no matter the obstacles you might
have faced, we're going to provide
supports and family navigators through
our safer, stronger together initiative
that's going to focus on your
opportunities.
that we made sure that high schools are
not being evaluated exclusively on their
four-year college acceptance rate
because that is an input but it is not a
key performance indicator that every
single child whether you head to a
four-year college or not needs to find a
pathway to work and wages and wealth
that I can say that that I'm very proud
I believe I'm one of the only governors
in this country that graduated from a
two-year college
>> [applause]
>> that I joined the army when I was 17
years old.
I did not I did not have a traditional
background and things worked out just
fine.
[applause]
And we want to make sure that every
single child knows that they can find
their pathway
no matter their origin story.
And since 2023, we have more than
doubled the number of youth apprentices
in our high schools. Since 2023, we have
grown our apprenticeship network to over
1,200 participating employers statewide.
Since 2023, we have partnered with
unions and employers to graduate over
5,000 apprentices. And by the end of my
second term, we have set our goal to
have 4,000 Maryland high schoolers
graduating with registered
apprenticeships every single year.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> The reason I bring that up is this. As
I'm coming to a close,
it's not just what we did.
Is that results actually matter, too.
That 3 years after I took office,
homicides are down more than 40%
statewide.
Non-fatal shootings are down more than
50%. Juvenile homicides are down 29%.
Robberies are on track to have the
lowest number that we have seen in
decades. And the progress is sustainable
because while violent crime saw historic
drops last year, I know because we off
we are doing our performance cabinets on
public safety and I know for a fact cuz
I had one this morning that so far this
year homicides are now down statewide
over 25% again after historic drops of
last year.
[applause]
Now, I know that the president of the
United States likes to call Baltimore
City a hell hole,
but I've learned that trying to fact
check the president
[laughter] is an exhausting and a
completely fruitless exercise.
And frankly, none of us have enough time
in our day because we actually want to
get real work done.
But [applause]
he should check his his facts around
Baltimore. And better yet, he should
actually come visit Baltimore. But he
should come visit Baltimore, not to
lecture. He should come visit Baltimore
to learn. Because if he did, he would
learn about the all the above strategy
that Maryland has employed when it comes
to public safety. He would learn that
homicides in Baltimore are now down 58%
since I was inaugurated. he would learn
that this past year alone, Baltimore
recorded the large the largest year
overyear drop in homicides ever measured
in the city, the last time the homicide
rate was this low in Baltimore City. I
was not born yet. I would love for him
to come and learn
because he could learn
that these results are not an accident.
They're proof of what happens when you
reject false choices and you don't
succumb to ideologies.
That after Brooklyn,
we did not make Maryland safer by
militarizing our neighborhoods.
We did not make Maryland safer by
calling in the National Guard.
We made Maryland safer despite the fact
that the FBI and the DEA and the ATF
agents were being pulled
off of drug and and gun trafficking
investigations.
We made Maryland safer by saying our
communities do not need us to save them.
We needed to stop passing bad policies
that were hurting them.
that we needed to allow our communities
the space and the grace to save
themselves.
We did not have to save Brooklyn.
Brooklyn saved itself.
And that's why I keep on coming back
to that night in Brooklyn.
That's why I keep coming back to Crystal
Gonzalez, whose daughter
was shot and killed in Brooklyn that
night.
And that night, I made her a promise
that I would never spend my time as
governor
simply giving thoughts and prayers.
I would not spend my time as governor
just simply attending funerals and not
passing a single piece of legislation.
I would not spend my time as governor
just giving eulogies.
that good government is about making
strong choices
and it's not about making choices for
communities.
It's about making choices with them.
The president thinks our job is to
oversee communities.
I think our job is to actually see
communities.
Our job is to leave no one behind. So,
God bless you guys and thank you so
much.
>> [applause]
[music]
>> Oh, we're [music] good. How's everyone
doing? You made it through the day.
>> [applause]
>> All right. I'm really here to say thank
you, but really um I want to give us all
a charge. And that charge is when people
ask you where are all our leaders, now
you have an answer. And when they ask
you
where are all our ideas, you also have
an answer.
uh we pulled together this ideas
conference because we know that to win
the future, we have to tell people where
to go, what the path is, what the path
is forward. So, we're thrilled to have
you all here. We're thrilled with the
fantastic speakers we've had all day,
governors, mayors, members of Congress,
future speakers, uh future Senate
majority leaders, and uh we are thrilled
with the feedback. We will have more
ideas for you in the months to come. Uh
and we are excited for the next ideas
conference. Thank you all for being
here. Have a wonderful evening.
[applause]
>> [music]